<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
    xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
    <channel>
        <title>BabylonCandle</title>
        <link>http://blog.ssanj.net</link>
        <description><![CDATA[The blog of Sanjiv Sahayam]]></description>
        <atom:link href="http://blog.ssanj.net/feed.xml" rel="self"
                   type="application/rss+xml" />
        <lastBuildDate>Wed, 17 Jun 2015 00:00:00 UT</lastBuildDate>
        <item>
    <title>How Many Coffees should one Person have a Day?</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-06-17-how-many-coffees-should-one-person-have-a-day.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<iframe width="100%" height="100" scrolling="no" frameborder="no" src="https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/210730718&amp;auto_play=false&amp;hide_related=false&amp;show_artwork=false&amp;show_comments=true&amp;show_user=false&amp;show_reposts=false&amp;visual=false">
</iframe>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jun 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-06-17-how-many-coffees-should-one-person-have-a-day.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>sanjiv sahayam</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Buy the Impossible Cheap</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-06-14-buy-the-impossible-cheap.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.jamesaltucher.com/2015/02/10-things-i-learn-from-richard-branson">Something James Altucher learned from Richard Branson</a> is that:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>When people think a problem is impossible they value it at zero. Successful people buy ideas low (zero) and sell them high.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>What problems do you perceive as “impossible”?`</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 14 Jun 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-06-14-buy-the-impossible-cheap.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>sanjiv sahayam</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Where&apos;s your Git HEAD at?</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-06-07-where%27s-your-git-HEAD-at.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Sometimes you want to know which branch and commit HEAD points to. With this magical Git incantation you can:</p>
<pre class="command"><code>git log --oneline --decorate --graph --all</code></pre>
<div class="figure">
<img src="/images/git_head_branch.jpg" alt="showing git branches with HEAD" />
<p class="caption">showing git branches with HEAD</p>
</div>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 07 Jun 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-06-07-where%27s-your-git-HEAD-at.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>sanjiv sahayam</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Obstacle Subtraction</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-06-07-obstacle-subtraction.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>James Altucher in his <a href="http://www.jamesaltucher.com/2015/02/10-things-i-learn-from-richard-branson">Things I learned from Richard Branson</a> blog post, talks about what he calls “idea subtraction”. He removes any perceived obstacles he may encounter when pursuing an idea. He then finds that he is left with more possibilities:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>I call this IDEA SUBTRACTION. Subtract the perceived obstacles to an idea and (BAM!) you find that many more ideas are born from that.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I prefer to call this “obstacle subtraction”.</p>
<p>The next time you are faced with some obstacles, think about what you could do if these obstacles didn’t exist. What would be your next move?</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 07 Jun 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-06-07-obstacle-subtraction.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>sanjiv sahayam</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Fear at the Dinner Table</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-06-07-fear-at-the-dinner-table.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>“I used to drink a carton of beer and a bottle of whisky every night” said the man at the other table to his teenage son. He was joined by his wife, and three young teenage daughters.</p>
<p>My wife and I looked at each other in disapproval. This was hardly the story any parent should be recounting to his teenage children.</p>
<p>A few minutes later his son received a text message and was looking at his phone. “What have I said about phones at the dinner table?” he boomed. This drama was starting to get quite uncomfortable. He then followed that with an exclamation of: “Give me your phone. NOW!”. Everyone else at his table went quiet. His wife said nothing. His daughters didn’t know what to do. His son handed over his phone. The fear at their table was palpable.</p>
<p>My wife and I wondered what would happen to the kid once he got home.</p>
<p>I really felt for the kid. I felt like saying “Don’t worry kid. Your life is going to get better. You will leave your parents one day. You can have your own life. You can do anything you want to do. Hang in there in the meantime.”</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 07 Jun 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-06-07-fear-at-the-dinner-table.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>sanjiv sahayam</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Do Better</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-06-07-do-better.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>It doesn’t matter how badly you failed yesterday. Decide to do better tomorrow.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 07 Jun 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-06-07-do-better.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>sanjiv sahayam</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Apple is Light Years Ahead</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-06-07-apple-is-light-years-ahead.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>I came across this slogan for the new MacBook on the Apple site:</p>
<div class="figure">
<img src="/images/light_years_ahead.jpg" alt="Light. Years ahead" />
<p class="caption">Light. Years ahead</p>
</div>
<p>I love the word play. :)</p>
<p>Sneaky Apple. Very sneaky!</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 07 Jun 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-06-07-apple-is-light-years-ahead.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>sanjiv sahayam</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Show Source Changes for Each Git Commit</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-05-31-show-source-changes-for-each-git-commit.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>An easy way to display source changes per Git commit is:</p>
<pre class="command"><code>git log -p -num_commits</code></pre>
<p>Eg:</p>
<pre class="command"><code>git log -p -2</code></pre>
<p>Running this on the <a href="https://github.com/scalaz/scalaz">Scalaz</a> project gives us the source updates across the last 2 commits:</p>
<pre class="terminal scrollx"><code>commit 93c6e378d705205ec9afbd64799cf9ff068cf9d5
Author: xuwei-k &lt;6b656e6a69@gmail.com&gt;
Date:   Fri May 22 00:39:00 2015 +0900

    reduce jar size

diff --git a/core/src/main/scala/scalaz/Coyoneda.scala b/core/src/main/scala/scalaz/Coyoneda.scala
index a2c9b57..dd86d12 100644
--- a/core/src/main/scala/scalaz/Coyoneda.scala
+++ b/core/src/main/scala/scalaz/Coyoneda.scala
@@ -233,7 +233,7 @@ private trait CoyonedaFoldable[F[_]] extends Foldable[Coyoneda[F, ?]] {
   def F: Foldable[F]

   override final def foldMap[A, B: Monoid](fa: Coyoneda[F, A])(f: A =&gt; B) =
-    F.foldMap(fa.fi)(i =&gt; f(fa.k(i)))
+    F.foldMap(fa.fi)(fa.k andThen f)
   override final def foldRight[A, B](fa: Coyoneda[F, A], z: =&gt; B)(f: (A, =&gt; B) =&gt; B) =
     F.foldRight(fa.fi, z)((i, b) =&gt; f(fa.k(i), b))
   override final def foldLeft[A, B](fa: Coyoneda[F, A], z: B)(f: (B, A) =&gt; B) =
@@ -244,7 +244,7 @@ private abstract class CoyonedaFoldable1[F[_]] extends Foldable1[Coyoneda[F, ?]]
   def F: Foldable1[F]

   override final def foldMap1[A, B: Semigroup](fa: Coyoneda[F, A])(f: A =&gt; B) =
-    F.foldMap1(fa.fi)(i =&gt; f(fa.k(i)))
+    F.foldMap1(fa.fi)(fa.k andThen f)
   override final def foldMapRight1[A, B](fa: Coyoneda[F, A])(z: A =&gt; B)(f: (A, =&gt; B) =&gt; B) =
     F.foldMapRight1(fa.fi)(i =&gt; z(fa.k(i)))((i, b) =&gt; f(fa.k(i), b))
 }

commit a8bb05f8d024c94b94b96e8a83912e66fa84269a
Author: xuwei-k &lt;6b656e6a69@gmail.com&gt;
Date:   Thu May 21 19:22:28 2015 +0900

    kind-projector 0.5.4

diff --git a/project/build.scala b/project/build.scala
index 7473615..74ebbd9 100644
--- a/project/build.scala
+++ b/project/build.scala
@@ -168,7 +168,7 @@ object build extends Build {
       ),
     // kind-projector plugin
     resolvers += &quot;bintray/non&quot; at &quot;http://dl.bintray.com/non/maven&quot;,
-    addCompilerPlugin(&quot;org.spire-math&quot; % &quot;kind-projector&quot; % &quot;0.5.3&quot;  cross CrossVersion.binary)
+    addCompilerPlugin(&quot;org.spire-math&quot; % &quot;kind-projector&quot; % &quot;0.5.4&quot; cross CrossVersion.binary)
   ) ++ osgiSettings ++ Seq[Sett](
     OsgiKeys.additionalHeaders := Map(&quot;-removeheaders&quot; -&gt; &quot;Include-Resource,Private-Package&quot;)
   )</code></pre>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 31 May 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-05-31-show-source-changes-for-each-git-commit.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>sanjiv sahayam</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Ignore Everybody - Hugh MacLeod</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-05-31-ignore-everybody-hugh-macleod.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Ideas from the book <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Ignore-Everybody-Other-Keys-Creativity/dp/1400113393">Ignore Everybody by Hugh MacLeod</a>.</p>
<h2 id="ideas">Ideas</h2>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>The more original your idea is, the less good advise people will be able to give you.</li>
<li>You don’t know if your idea is any good the moment it’s created. Neither does anyone else.</li>
<li>A big idea will change you.</li>
<li>Good ideas alter the power balance in relationships. That is why good ideas are always initially resisted.</li>
<li>Good ideas come with a heavy burden which is why so few people execute them.</li>
<li>Sovereignty is to have complete freedom - without the need for somebody else’s money or approval.</li>
<li>The sovereignty you have over your work will inspire far more people than the actual content ever will.</li>
<li>Your sovereignty will inspire other people to find their own sovereignty.</li>
<li>Your idea doesn’t have to be big. It has to be yours alone.</li>
<li>The more idea is yours alone, the more freedom you have to do something really amazing.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="put-in-the-work">Put in the work</h2>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>Doing anything worthwhile takes forever.</li>
<li>Ninety nine percent of what separates successful from unsuccessful people is time, effort and stamina.</li>
<li>If somebody in your industry is more successful than you it’s probably because he works harder at it than you do.</li>
<li>When starting out don’t quit your day job.</li>
<li>Having a day job, balances the need for making a living while still maintaining ones creative sovereignty.</li>
<li>Being good at something is being able to make it look easy. But it’s never easy.</li>
<li>Put the hours in, do it for long enough, and magical, life-transforming things happen eventually.</li>
</ol>
<div>
<div class="quote">
Go ahead and make something. Make something really special. Make something amazing that will blow the mind of anybody who sees it.
</div>
</div>
<h2 id="pillars">Pillars</h2>
<div>
<div class="quote">
Meeting a person who wrote a masterpiece on the back of a deli menu would not surprise me. Meeting a person who wrote a masterpiece with a silver Cartier fountain pen on an antique writing table in an airy SoHo loft would seriously suprise me.
</div>
</div>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>The more talented someone is the less they need props.</li>
<li>There is no correlation between creativity and tools.</li>
<li>A fancy tool gives a second-rater one more pillar to hide behind.</li>
<li>All you can do is to keep asking yourself the question, “Is this a pillar?” about every aspect of your business, your craft, your reason for being alive, and go from there.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="stand-out">Stand out</h2>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>Don’t try to stand out from the crowd; avoid crowds altogether.</li>
<li>Your plan for getting your work out there has to be as original as the actual work.</li>
<li>Question how much freedom your path affords you. Be utterly ruthless about it. It’s your freedom that will get you where you want to go.</li>
</ol>
<div>
<div class="quote">
Is your plan unique? Is there nobody else doing it? Then I’d be excited. A little scared maybe, but excited.
</div>
</div>
<h2 id="pain">Pain</h2>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>If you accept the pain, it can’t hurt you.</li>
<li>The pain of making necessary sacrifices always hurts more than you think its going to.</li>
<li>Doing something seriously creative is one of the most amazing experiences one can have.</li>
<li>Even if you don’t end up pulling it off, you’ll learn many incredible, magical, valuable things.</li>
<li>You are better off doing something on the assumption that you will <em>not</em> be rewarded for it, that it will not receive the recognition it deserves, that it will <em>not</em> be worth the time and effort invested.</li>
<li>Once you realise there is no reward ask yourself, “should I make this exist or not?”. Once you can answer that truthfully for yourself, the rest is easy.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="rewards">Rewards</h2>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>The more you practise your craft, the less you confuse worldly rewards with spiritual rewards and vice versa.</li>
<li>Never sell something you love. You will subconsciously sabotage yourself from making a sale.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="the-line">The line</h2>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>The most important thing a creative person can learn professionally is where to draw the red line that separates what you are willing to do from what you are not.</li>
</ol>
<div>
<div class="quote">
Art suffers the moment other people start paying for it. The more you need the money, the more people will tell you what to do. The less control you will have. The more bullshit you will have to swallow. The less joy it will bring you. Know this and plan accordingly.
</div>
</div>
<h2 id="trust">Trust</h2>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>The people you trust and vice versa are what will feed you and pay for your kids’ college. Nothing else.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="new-world-order">New World Order</h2>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>The old ways are dead. You need to spend more time around creative people - the real visionaries. Think more about what they need and respond accordingly.</li>
<li>The only people who can change the world are the people who want to.</li>
</ol>
<div>
<div class="quote">
If you are creative, if you can think independently, if you can articulate passion, if you can override the fear of being wrong, then your company needs you now more than ever. And now you company can no longer afford to pretend that isn’t the case.
</div>
</div>
<h2 id="weakness">Weakness</h2>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>No one person can be good at everything.</li>
<li>If you want to be really good, figure out how to circumvent your limitations and how to turn weaknesses into strengths.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="inspiration">Inspiration</h2>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>Find a way of working that makes it easy to take advantage of your inspired moments.</li>
<li>If you have nothing to say, go do something else.</li>
</ol>
<div>
<div class="quote">
The less you can live on, the more chance your idea will succeed. This is true even after you have “made it.”
</div>
</div>
<h2 id="truths">Truths</h2>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>Don’t turn a hobby into a job. A man needs both.</li>
<li>No painting ever sells for as much as it cost for the artist to make.</li>
<li>You can never predict how you will be successful.</li>
</ol>
<div>
<div class="quote">
Work hard. Keep at it. Live simply and quietly. Remain humble. Stay positive. Create your own luck. Be nice. Be polite.
</div>
</div>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 31 May 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-05-31-ignore-everybody-hugh-macleod.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>sanjiv sahayam</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>White Trails</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-05-28-white-trails.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<div class="haiku">
I look to the sky
</div>
<div class="haiku">
I see a long white trail
</div>
<div class="haiku">
The sun shines
</div>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Thu, 28 May 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-05-28-white-trails.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>sanjiv sahayam</dc:creator>
</item>

    </channel>
</rss>
