<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
    xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
    <channel>
        <title>BabylonCandle</title>
        <link>http://blog.ssanj.net</link>
        <description><![CDATA[The blog of Sanjiv Sahayam]]></description>
        <atom:link href="http://blog.ssanj.net/feed.xml" rel="self"
                   type="application/rss+xml" />
        <lastBuildDate>Wed, 16 Sep 2015 00:00:00 UT</lastBuildDate>
        <item>
    <title>The Most Important Criteria.</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-09-16-the-most-important-criteria.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>When we approach a job opportunity we mostly look for things that are not all that important. How much does it pay? Can I use technology X? How close is it to my home?</p>
<p>What we should be looking for are two main things:</p>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>Ethical leaders.</li>
<li>Meaningful work.</li>
</ol>
<p>Everything else is irrelevant.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 16 Sep 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-09-16-the-most-important-criteria.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>sanjiv sahayam</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Seth Godin on After You&apos;ve Done Your Best Work.</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-09-16-seth-godin-on-after-you%27ve-done-your-best-work.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Seth Godin in his article <a href="http://sethgodin.typepad.com/seths_blog/2015/08/after-youve-done-your-best-work.html">After You’ve Done Your Best Work</a> says that if your best work has been ignored then:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>You really have no choice but to do it again. To do your best work again, as impossible and unfair as that seems.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Because:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>It compounds over time.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>And:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Best work followed by best work followed by more best work is far more useful and generous than merely doing your best work once and insisting we understand you.</p>
</blockquote>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 16 Sep 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-09-16-seth-godin-on-after-you%27ve-done-your-best-work.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>sanjiv sahayam</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Secrets.</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-09-16-secrets.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Will destroy your company. There is no place for secrets - especially in small close-knit teams. Secrets lead to speculation, gossip and worse - people leaving for the wrong reasons. It also gives employees the message that “you can’t handle the truth” or “you’re not in the inner circle”. Both these messages should be avoided.</p>
<p>This takes me back to a client-site I worked at a few years back. There were two team leaders across the various teams. One day one of the team leaders just stopped coming in. There were rumours of “disciplinary action”. But no announcement was made. When I asked the surviving team lead what had happened he said “We don’t talk about X”. I never saw team lead X again. It was like the company wanted to erase all evidence his existence. It felt like anyone could be “erased” at a moments notice.</p>
<p>This type of reality distortion just doesn’t work. It would have good to know what had happened to team lead X. After all how would we know not to do what he did? Unfortunately this was a missed opportunity to reinforce the company code of conduct or to behave in a decent way.</p>
<p>Secrets are about fear. If sharing some information with your employees has got you scared then you absolutely must share it with them. If they find out your secret from other sources or figure it out for themselves the consequences will be much worse.</p>
<p>Contrast this with companies like <a href="https://buffer.com/about">buffer</a> that are <a href="https://open.bufferapp.com/transparent-pricing-buffer">open</a> about most things like <a href="https://open.bufferapp.com/introducing-open-salaries-at-buffer-including-our-transparent-formula-and-all-individual-salaries">salaries</a>, <a href="https://open.bufferapp.com/buffer-values">core values</a> etc.</p>
<p>And the most important reason not to have secrets is because it’s not a decent way to operate any company.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 16 Sep 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-09-16-secrets.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>sanjiv sahayam</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>No Matter What Stones</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-09-16-no-matter-what-stones.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<div>
<div class="quote">
To stand for your dreams + heart’s desires and deepest values no matter what stones those who do not understand may toss at you.
</div>
<div class="attribution">
<a href="http://www.robinsharma.com/blog/08/for-real-human-beings-only">Robin Sharma</a>
</div>
</div>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 16 Sep 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-09-16-no-matter-what-stones.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>sanjiv sahayam</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Negotiate for the One Thing you Need.</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-09-16-negotiate-for-the-one-thing-you-need.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Many workplaces have the “potential” to be great. Few rarely live up to that potential. If you’ve been contemplating leaving unless things change, try to be clear about what will make you stay. Discard any notions about what “should” have happened or what was “owed” to you or how you were “lied” to.</p>
<p>Ask yourself “what would it take to make me stay?”. Once you have the answer negotiate to achieve that. Only that. Or leave.</p>
<p>When negotiating make sure to only talk with decision-makers. You are wasting your time with anyone else.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 16 Sep 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-09-16-negotiate-for-the-one-thing-you-need.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>sanjiv sahayam</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Seth Godin on The One Thing that will Change Everything.</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-09-06-seth-godin-on-the-one-thing-that-will-change-everything.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Another great article sent to me by my friend <a href="http://ryandrake.com">Ryan</a> was this one by <a href="http://sethgodin.typepad.com/seths_blog/2015/08/the-one-thing-that-will-change-everything.html">Seth Godin on waiting for the one thing that will change everything</a>. In it Seth talks about that one thing:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>That introduction you need.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The capital that your organization is trying to raise.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The breakthrough in what you’re building…</p>
</blockquote>
<p>And the real effect that one thing has once you get it:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Have you noticed that as soon as you get that one thing, everything doesn’t change? In fact, the only thing that changes is that you realize that you don’t need that one thing as much as you thought you did.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>He advises to stop waiting for a silver bullet:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>It turns out that nothing will change everything for the better. It works better to focus on each step instead of being distracted by a promised secret exit.</p>
</blockquote>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 06 Sep 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-09-06-seth-godin-on-the-one-thing-that-will-change-everything.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>sanjiv sahayam</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Seth Godin on Creating Something Remarkable</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-09-06-seth-godin-on-creating-something-remarkable.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Seth Godin in his <a href="http://sethgodin.typepad.com/seths_blog/2015/06/pulling-a-hat-out-of-a-rabbit.html">article on pulling a hat out of a rabbit</a> says that:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>It’s tempting to do what’s been done before, certain in the belief that if you do it, it’ll be a little better and a little more popular, merely because you’re the one doing it.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>In fact, though, that’s unlikely. You’ll care more, but it’s unlikely the market will.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Consider doing it differently:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Consider the alternative, which is choosing to turn the question upside down, to do it backwards, sideways, or in a significantly more generous or risky way.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Remarkable often starts with the problem you set out to solve and the way you choose to solve it.</p>
</blockquote>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 06 Sep 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-09-06-seth-godin-on-creating-something-remarkable.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>sanjiv sahayam</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Seth Godin on Averages</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-09-06-seth-godin-on-averages.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>My friend <a href="http://ryandrake.com">Ryan</a> sent me an <a href="http://sethgodin.typepad.com/seths_blog/2015/08/the-average.html">interesting post by Seth Godin</a> which states:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Everything you do is either going to raise your average or lower it.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Every choice makes you better or worse:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Progress is almost always a series of choices, an inexorable move toward mediocrity, or its opposite.</p>
</blockquote>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 06 Sep 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-09-06-seth-godin-on-averages.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>sanjiv sahayam</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Robin Sharma on The Methods for Superhuman Productivity</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-09-06-robin-sharma-on-the-methods-for-superhuman-productivity.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>My friend <a href="http://ryandrake.com">Ryan</a> can’t stop sending me cool articles to read! Thanks Ryan! :) In this one <a href="https://blog.growth.supply/the-methods-for-superhuman-productivity-de4452af7cfb">Robin Sharma talks about how to achived Superhuman productivity</a>. Robin says that:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>We live in The Age of Dramatic Distraction. Many shiny toys to chase every waking moment yet so few of those pursuits create real value and grow a life brilliantly lived.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Too many of us are overscheduled, overconnected and overstimulated by all the noise, interruptions and complexity of current society.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The cost of this way of operating? You’ll arrive at the last hour of your final day and realize you spent your highest potential on your lowest leverage activities.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The 20/20/20 formula:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The way you start your day powerfully shapes how productively you live it. Reserve the first 60 minutes for personal preparation.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Start your day with some exercise:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>As the Spartan warriors said: “Sweat more in training and you’ll bleed less at war.” Spend your first 20 minutes in intense exercise. Sweating releases BDNF, a brain chemical that actually grows neural connections. Working out also releases dopamine (the neurotransmitter of motivation) and serotonin, which makes you feel happy.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Next review your annual plan:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>For the next “20 minute pocket”, review your annual plan and reflect deeply on your quarterly goals. Clarity precedes mastery and this practice will deepen your focus through the day.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Next inspire yourself:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Invest the final 20 minutes of this morning routine on learning (i.e., read autobiographies of great humans or listen to a leadership podcast or download the lessons of yesterday into &gt; your journal).</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Learn how to recover effectively:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Good research confirms that what makes the best athletes the best in the world was not what they did in their sport but how effectively they recovered. For example, it was the rituals that star tennis players did in between points that made them stars. What made the Russian weightlifters so undefeatable was their “work-rest ratios”</p>
</blockquote>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 06 Sep 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-09-06-robin-sharma-on-the-methods-for-superhuman-productivity.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>sanjiv sahayam</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Not finished or Full of Bugs?</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-09-06-not-finished-or-full-of-bugs.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>I was recently asked:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Is it “not finished” or “full of bugs”?</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Not finishing something implies that the system does not do what you want it to - yet. It’s part way there.</p>
<p>Having lots of bugs implies there is a mismatch between what a system should do and what it does.</p>
<p>They sound about the same to me.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 06 Sep 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-09-06-not-finished-or-full-of-bugs.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>sanjiv sahayam</dc:creator>
</item>

    </channel>
</rss>
