<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>BabylonCandle</title>
        <link>http://blog.ssanj.net</link>
        <description><![CDATA[The blog of Sanjiv Sahayam]]></description>
        <atom:link href="http://blog.ssanj.net/feed.xml" rel="self"
                   type="application/rss+xml" />
        <lastBuildDate>Sun, 31 May 2015 00:00:00 UT</lastBuildDate>
        <item>
    <title>Show Source Changes for each Git Commit</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-05-31-show-source-changes-for-each-git-commit.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>An easy way to display source changes per Git commit is:</p>
<pre class="command"><code>git log -p -num_commits</code></pre>
<p>Eg:</p>
<pre class="command"><code>git log -p -2</code></pre>
<p>Running this on the <a href="https://github.com/scalaz/scalaz">Scalaz</a> project gives us the source updates across the last 2 commits:</p>
<pre class="terminal scrollx"><code>commit 93c6e378d705205ec9afbd64799cf9ff068cf9d5
Author: xuwei-k &lt;6b656e6a69@gmail.com&gt;
Date:   Fri May 22 00:39:00 2015 +0900

    reduce jar size

diff --git a/core/src/main/scala/scalaz/Coyoneda.scala b/core/src/main/scala/scalaz/Coyoneda.scala
index a2c9b57..dd86d12 100644
--- a/core/src/main/scala/scalaz/Coyoneda.scala
+++ b/core/src/main/scala/scalaz/Coyoneda.scala
@@ -233,7 +233,7 @@ private trait CoyonedaFoldable[F[_]] extends Foldable[Coyoneda[F, ?]] {
   def F: Foldable[F]

   override final def foldMap[A, B: Monoid](fa: Coyoneda[F, A])(f: A =&gt; B) =
-    F.foldMap(fa.fi)(i =&gt; f(fa.k(i)))
+    F.foldMap(fa.fi)(fa.k andThen f)
   override final def foldRight[A, B](fa: Coyoneda[F, A], z: =&gt; B)(f: (A, =&gt; B) =&gt; B) =
     F.foldRight(fa.fi, z)((i, b) =&gt; f(fa.k(i), b))
   override final def foldLeft[A, B](fa: Coyoneda[F, A], z: B)(f: (B, A) =&gt; B) =
@@ -244,7 +244,7 @@ private abstract class CoyonedaFoldable1[F[_]] extends Foldable1[Coyoneda[F, ?]]
   def F: Foldable1[F]

   override final def foldMap1[A, B: Semigroup](fa: Coyoneda[F, A])(f: A =&gt; B) =
-    F.foldMap1(fa.fi)(i =&gt; f(fa.k(i)))
+    F.foldMap1(fa.fi)(fa.k andThen f)
   override final def foldMapRight1[A, B](fa: Coyoneda[F, A])(z: A =&gt; B)(f: (A, =&gt; B) =&gt; B) =
     F.foldMapRight1(fa.fi)(i =&gt; z(fa.k(i)))((i, b) =&gt; f(fa.k(i), b))
 }

commit a8bb05f8d024c94b94b96e8a83912e66fa84269a
Author: xuwei-k &lt;6b656e6a69@gmail.com&gt;
Date:   Thu May 21 19:22:28 2015 +0900

    kind-projector 0.5.4

diff --git a/project/build.scala b/project/build.scala
index 7473615..74ebbd9 100644
--- a/project/build.scala
+++ b/project/build.scala
@@ -168,7 +168,7 @@ object build extends Build {
       ),
     // kind-projector plugin
     resolvers += &quot;bintray/non&quot; at &quot;http://dl.bintray.com/non/maven&quot;,
-    addCompilerPlugin(&quot;org.spire-math&quot; % &quot;kind-projector&quot; % &quot;0.5.3&quot;  cross CrossVersion.binary)
+    addCompilerPlugin(&quot;org.spire-math&quot; % &quot;kind-projector&quot; % &quot;0.5.4&quot; cross CrossVersion.binary)
   ) ++ osgiSettings ++ Seq[Sett](
     OsgiKeys.additionalHeaders := Map(&quot;-removeheaders&quot; -&gt; &quot;Include-Resource,Private-Package&quot;)
   )</code></pre>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 31 May 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-05-31-show-source-changes-for-each-git-commit.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Ignore Everybody - Hugh MacLeod</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-05-31-ignore-everybody-hugh-macleod.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Ideas from the book <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Ignore-Everybody-Other-Keys-Creativity/dp/1400113393">Ignore Everybody by Hugh MacLeod</a>.</p>
<h2 id="ideas">Ideas</h2>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>The more original your idea is, the less good advise people will be able to give you.</li>
<li>You don’t know if your idea is any good the moment it’s created. Neither does anyone else.</li>
<li>A big idea will change you.</li>
<li>Good ideas alter the power balance in relationships. That is why good ideas are always initially resisted.</li>
<li>Good ideas come with a heavy burden which is why so few people execute them.</li>
<li>Sovereignty is to have complete freedom - without the need for somebody else’s money or approval.</li>
<li>The sovereignty you have over your work will inspire far more people than the actual content ever will.</li>
<li>Your sovereignty will inspire other people to find their own sovereignty.</li>
<li>Your idea doesn’t have to be big. It has to be yours alone.</li>
<li>The more idea is yours alone, the more freedom you have to do something really amazing.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="put-in-the-work">Put in the work</h2>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>Doing anything worthwhile takes forever.</li>
<li>Ninety nine percent of what separates successful from unsuccessful people is time, effort and stamina.</li>
<li>If somebody in your industry is more successful than you it’s probably because he works harder at it than you do.</li>
<li>When starting out don’t quit your day job.</li>
<li>Having a day job, balances the need for making a living while still maintaining ones creative sovereignty.</li>
<li>Being good at something is being able to make it look easy. But it’s never easy.</li>
<li>Put the hours in, do it for long enough, and magical, life-transforming things happen eventually.</li>
</ol>
<div>
<div class="quote">
Go ahead and make something. Make something really special. Make something amazing that will blow the mind of anybody who sees it.
</div>
</div>
<h2 id="pillars">Pillars</h2>
<div>
<div class="quote">
Meeting a person who wrote a masterpiece on the back of a deli menu would not surprise me. Meeting a person who wrote a masterpiece with a silver Cartier fountain pen on an antique writing table in an airy SoHo loft would seriously suprise me.
</div>
</div>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>The more talented someone is the less they need props.</li>
<li>There is no correlation between creativity and tools.</li>
<li>A fancy tool gives a second-rater one more pillar to hide behind.</li>
<li>All you can do is to keep asking yourself the question, “Is this a pillar?” about every aspect of your business, your craft, your reason for being alive, and go from there.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="stand-out">Stand out</h2>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>Don’t try to stand out from the crowd; avoid crowds altogether.</li>
<li>Your plan for getting your work out there has to be as original as the actual work.</li>
<li>Question how much freedom your path affords you. Be utterly ruthless about it. It’s your freedom that will get you where you want to go.</li>
</ol>
<div>
<div class="quote">
Is your plan unique? Is there nobody else doing it? Then I’d be excited. A little scared maybe, but excited.
</div>
</div>
<h2 id="pain">Pain</h2>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>If you accept the pain, it can’t hurt you.</li>
<li>The pain of making necessary sacrifices always hurts more than you think its going to.</li>
<li>Doing something seriously creative is one of the most amazing experiences one can have.</li>
<li>Even if you don’t end up pulling it off, you’ll learn many incredible, magical, valuable things.</li>
<li>You are better off doing something on the assumption that you will <em>not</em> be rewarded for it, that it will not receive the recognition it deserves, that it will <em>not</em> be worth the time and effort invested.</li>
<li>Once you realise there is no reward ask yourself, “should I make this exist or not?”. Once you can answer that truthfully for yourself, the rest is easy.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="rewards">Rewards</h2>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>The more you practise your craft, the less you confuse worldly rewards with spiritual rewards and vice versa.</li>
<li>Never sell something you love. You will subconsciously sabotage yourself from making a sale.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="the-line">The line</h2>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>The most important thing a creative person can learn professionally is where to draw the red line that separates what you are willing to do from what you are not.</li>
</ol>
<div>
<div class="quote">
Art suffers the moment other people start paying for it. The more you need the money, the more people will tell you what to do. The less control you will have. The more bullshit you will have to swallow. The less joy it will bring you. Know this and plan accordingly.
</div>
</div>
<h2 id="trust">Trust</h2>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>The people you trust and vice versa are what will feed you and pay for your kids’ college. Nothing else.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="new-world-order">New World Order</h2>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>The old ways are dead. You need to spend more time around creative people - the real visionaries. Think more about what they need and respond accordingly.</li>
<li>The only people who can change the world are the people who want to.</li>
</ol>
<div>
<div class="quote">
If you are creative, if you can think independently, if you can articulate passion, if you can override the fear of being wrong, then your company needs you now more than ever. And now you company can no longer afford to pretend that isn’t the case.
</div>
</div>
<h2 id="weakness">Weakness</h2>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>No one person can be good at everything.</li>
<li>If you want to be really good, figure out how to circumvent your limitations and how to turn weaknesses into strengths.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="inspiration">Inspiration</h2>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>Find a way of working that makes it easy to take advantage of your inspired moments.</li>
<li>If you have nothing to say, go do something else.</li>
</ol>
<div>
<div class="quote">
The less you can live on, the more chance your idea will succeed. This is true even after you have “made it.”
</div>
</div>
<h2 id="truths">Truths</h2>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>Don’t turn a hobby into a job. A man needs both.</li>
<li>No painting ever sells for as much as it cost for the artist to make.</li>
<li>You can never predict how you will be successful.</li>
</ol>
<div>
<div class="quote">
Work hard. Keep at it. Live simply and quietly. Remain humble. Stay positive. Create your own luck. Be nice. Be polite.
</div>
</div>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 31 May 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-05-31-ignore-everybody-hugh-macleod.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>White Trails</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-05-28-white-trails.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<div class="haiku">
I look to the sky
</div>
<div class="haiku">
I see a long white trail
</div>
<div class="haiku">
The sun shines
</div>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Thu, 28 May 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-05-28-white-trails.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>The Cultivation of Virtues</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-05-28-the-cultivation-of-virtues.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Galatians 5:22-23, speaks of the “fruits” of the Holy Spirit. Even if you don’t believe in Christianity, the fruits are a fine list of virtues for anyone to cultivate:</p>
<div class="haiku">
Love
</div>
<div class="haiku">
Joy
</div>
<div class="haiku">
Peace
</div>
<div class="haiku">
Patience
</div>
<div class="haiku">
Kindness
</div>
<div class="haiku">
Moral Excellence
</div>
<div class="haiku">
Faithfulness
</div>
<div class="haiku">
Gentleness
</div>
<div class="haiku">
Self-control
</div>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Thu, 28 May 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-05-28-the-cultivation-of-virtues.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Make Time for some Awe</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-05-28-make-time-for-some-awe.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Awe is defined as:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>an overwhelming feeling of reverence, admiration, fear, etc., produced by that which is grand, sublime, extremely powerful.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>A commentary about why we need more awe in our lives from the <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2015/05/24/opinion/sunday/why-do-we-experience-awe.html">New York Times</a> via <a href="http://ma.tt">Ma.tt</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>We believe that awe deprivation has had a hand in a broad societal shift that has been widely observed over the past 50 years: People have become more individualistic, more self-focused, more materialistic and less connected to others. To reverse this trend, we suggest that people insist on experiencing more everyday awe, to actively seek out what gives them goose bumps, be it in looking at trees, night skies, patterns of wind on water or the quotidian nobility of others — the teenage punk who gives up his seat on public transportation, the young child who explores the world in a state of wonder, the person who presses on against all odds.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><a href="http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/quotidian">Quotidian</a> is such a cool word. :)</p>
<p>Through various social experiments they found that:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Participants experiencing awe, more so than those participants experiencing emotions like pride or amusement, cooperated more, shared more resources and sacrificed more for others — all of which are behaviours necessary for our collective life.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Their thoughts on how awe works:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>One answer is that awe imbues people with a different sense of themselves, one that is smaller, more humble and part of something larger.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Let’s make time for some awe in our lives. :)</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Thu, 28 May 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-05-28-make-time-for-some-awe.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>But a Good Life ...</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-05-28-but-a-good-life.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<div>
<div class="quote">
But a good life is like the flame of a bonfire. It builds slowly, and because it’s slow and warm it caresses the heart instead of destroys it.
</div>
<div class="attribution">
James Altucher
</div>
</div>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Thu, 28 May 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-05-28-but-a-good-life.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Scala Compilation Speed on MacBook Pros</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-05-24-scala-compilation-speed-on-mbp.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://sanj.ink/posts/2015-05-21-between-apple-and-despair.html">After deciding to take the plunge and buy the new MBP 15“</a>, I thought a little benchmarking would be a nice confirmation that my “upgrade” made sense. Most times I use my laptop for Scala development and writing my blog. I thought I’d run some tests around the Scala compilation times for some well-known projects.</p>
<p>Here’s how I tested each project:</p>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>Git cloned the project.</li>
<li>Connected my laptop to the mains (to ensure no energy saving was sacrificing performance).</li>
<li><p>Downloaded the world with:</p>
<pre class="terminal"><code>sbt clean compile</code></pre></li>
<li><p>Ran a clean compilation four times and took the average, min and max times:</p>
<pre class="terminal"><code>sbt &quot;set offline := true&quot; clean compile</code></pre></li>
</ol>
<p>Scala open source projects used:</p>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li><a href="https://github.com/scalaz/scalaz">Scalaz</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/spray/spray">Spray</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/milessabin/shapeless">Shapeless</a></li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>Model A =&gt; 2010 15&quot; MBP 2.4GHZ i5, 8GB, SSD.</li>
<li>Model B =&gt; 2014 15&quot; MBP 2.2GHZ i7, 16GB, SSD. (<em>This is not the 2015 model but is pretty close to it</em>.)</li>
</ul>
All compilation times are in seconds (s).
<div>
<table>
    <thead>
        <tr>
            <th>
Project
</th>
            <th colspan="2">
Average (s)
</th>
            <th colspan="2">
Minimum (s)
</th>
            <th colspan="2">
Maximum (s)
</th>
        </tr>
        <tr>
            <th></th>
            <th>
2010
</th>
            <th>
2014
</th>
            <th>
2010
</th>
            <th>
2014
</th>
            <th>
2010
</th>
            <th>
2014
</th>
        </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
        <tr>
            <td class="left">
Scalaz
</td>
            <td>
234
</td>
            <td>
77
</td>
            <td>
232
</td>
            <td>
76
</td>
            <td>
264
</td>
            <td>
79
</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
            <td class="left">
Spray
</td>
            <td>
183
</td>
            <td>
49
</td>
            <td>
173
</td>
            <td>
48
</td>
            <td>
203
</td>
            <td>
52
</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
            <td class="left">
Shapeless
</td>
            <td>
189
</td>
            <td>
57
</td>
            <td>
178
</td>
            <td>
55
</td>
            <td>
208
</td>
            <td>
59
</td>
        </tr>
    </tbody>
</table>
</div>
<div class="caption section">
Averages
</div>
<div id="averageChart">

</div>
<div class="caption section">
Min/Max Variations
</div>
<div id="variationsChart">

</div>
<div class="caption section">
Speed Increase
</div>
<div id="speedIncreaseChart">

</div>
<!-- Load d3.js and c3.js -->
<script src="../js/d3.min.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<script src="../js/c3.min.js"></script>

<script>
c3.generate({
    bindto: '#averageChart',
    data: {
      columns: [
        ['2010 Avg', 234, 183, 189],
        ['2014 Avg', 77, 49 ,57],
      ],
      types: {
        '2010 Avg': 'bar',
        '2014 Avg': 'bar'
      }
    },
    axis: {
        x: {
            type: 'category',
            categories: ['scalaz', 'spray', 'shapeless']
        }
    },
});

c3.generate({
    bindto: '#variationsChart',
    data: {
      columns: [
        ['2010 Min', 232, 173, 178],
        ['2010 Max', 264, 203, 208],
        ['2014 Min', 76, 48, 55],
        ['2014 Max', 79, 52, 59]
      ],
    },
    axis: {
        x: {
            type: 'category',
            categories: ['scalaz', 'spray', 'shapeless']
        }
    }
});

c3.generate({
    bindto: '#speedIncreaseChart',
    data: {
        columns: [
            ['speed increase', 69]
        ],
        type: 'gauge'
    }
});
</script>

]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 24 May 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-05-24-scala-compilation-speed-on-mbp.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Between an Apple and Despair</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-05-21-between-apple-and-despair.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>The new MBP 15&quot; was just announced and I am #disappointed. No new processor. Just the same one from last year with higher clock rates. No USB type C connectors. No form-factor changes. No “innovation”</p>
<p>I had waited patiently for the last six months for this update. Talk about underwhelmed. I did what any underwhelmed person would do - look for alternatives.</p>
<p>I did find some interesting alternatives in <a href="http://www.dell.com/au/p/alienware-15/pd">Alienware</a> and <a href="http://www.engadget.com/2014/12/19/msi-gt72-dominator-review">Msi</a>. They were also not constrained by Apple’s release cycles. They could in theory release laptops with the newest processors as soon as they were released. I wanted to run Linux on any laptop I buy. When I did some research around the two options, I came across troubling issues like: “can’t boot to Ubuntu” or “doesn’t have drivers for the wireless card”.</p>
<p>Then it hit me. There was a good reason why I had moved to Apple instead of using my own screamingly fast Linux laptop. I didn’t want to waste my time trying to get the hardware to work with the software. I wanted things to “Just work” - (c)Apple. The Apple, drivers were all there. The software was good-ish. More importantly I knew that if something as basic as a wireless card driver was broken that it would be fixed pretty quick. Not so with Linux and custom hardware.</p>
<p>With Apple I was purchasing the hardware and software, along with an implicit promise that they would work together.</p>
<p>The lack of proper support for Linux from hardware manufacturers is really surprising. Most programmers I know use either Linux or MacOSX. Surely we make up a large percentage of the laptop-buying population? Are Windows developers and gamers the core laptop-buying demographic? Or is it corporate types that love Microsoft Office and other Windows shackles?</p>
<p>If I were given another alternative to using Apple, I would definitely use it. The troubling fact is there are none - if you don’t want to use Windows.</p>
<p>I’ve decided to take the plunge and upgrade my 2010 MBP to the latest 2015 “update”. A friend said I should wait for the new processors coming later this year:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“you are going to be kicking yourself when the new ones come out though”.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>That would mean maybe another six months waiting for an update that would hopefully be worthy of a year of waiting. My only regret is that I hadn’t upgraded six months ago. I would have had a hearty laugh when the current update came out.</p>
<p>And then there’s more interesting news with Intel’s plans for Skylake “leaked” by some so and so. <a href="http://appleinsider.com/articles/15/05/22/rumor-intel-prepping-next-gen-skylake-chips-for-august-debut-may-curtail-broadwell-sales">Skylake is supposed to drop in August</a> and with it bring in a 15% speed increase plus usher in a revolutionary wireless peripheral era. So even if, Intel deliver Skylake in August - and that’s a big “if”, given that they are so behind on Broadwell promises there’s also this:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Intel’s launching Skylake-S early to take advantage of the buffer zone while taking their time with Skylake-K so that any bugs that hinder clock speed have been ironed out. That would involve solving the TDP problem and eventually rolling out some very impressive unlocked processors.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><a href="http://wccftech.com/intels-broadwell-skylake-uarch-transition-big-prescott-conroe">Read more about that at wccftech</a></p>
<p>So do I want to buy a processor where Intel is trying to iron out its bugs? No thanks. This indicates that the faster Skylake, less “buggy” processors will only start showing up maybe mid 2016. Another reason to buy a MBP now!</p>
<p>So my wait is over. I’m taking the plunge. I hope not to kick myself in August! :)</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Thu, 21 May 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-05-21-between-apple-and-despair.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Reading List</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-05-17-reading-list.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>I’ve decided to geek-out and put my <a href="https://github.com/ssanj/ReadingList">reading list on Github</a>.</p>
<p>If you have any book recommendations that you think I should check out send me a pull request or leave me a comment.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 17 May 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-05-17-reading-list.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Know When to Rest</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-05-17-know-when-to-rest.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>It’s great to a have a routine. It’s great to have goals. It’s great to work consistently day in and day out.</p>
<p>Sometimes you just don’t feel like you have the motivation. Your work feels like a chore. Or that you’ve done all you want to do for the moment. You may have lost your “flow” - where your craft just pours out of you without any provocation.</p>
<p>When this happens, take a break from your routine. You can never produce your best work when your heart is not in it.</p>
<p>Take a day, a week or even a month off. You could even build it into your routine. This time off will help you to revitalise your creative spirit and come back refreshed and renewed to do awesome work.</p>
<p>Don’t be afraid to break your routine when you need to.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 17 May 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-05-17-know-when-to-rest.html</guid>
</item>

    </channel> 
</rss>
