<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>BabylonCandle</title>
        <link>http://blog.ssanj.net</link>
        <description><![CDATA[The blog of Sanjiv Sahayam]]></description>
        <atom:link href="http://blog.ssanj.net/feed.xml" rel="self"
                   type="application/rss+xml" />
        <lastBuildDate>Wed, 29 Apr 2015 00:00:00 UT</lastBuildDate>
        <item>
    <title>Automatic Salary Upgrades</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-04-29-automatic-salary-upgrades.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>One of the many reasons people leave a workplace is to gain a higher salary. Employers, never really review salaries relative to their current market rate. Employers see this as investment in their bottom line: “Don’t pay employees more than you have to”. Employees, usually get a small raise to placate them until the next review with a list of “reasons” as to why the increment wasn’t higher. The whole review-mediocre-salary-increment cycle then repeats in the next review period.</p>
<p>Employees, at the back of their minds know, they are are worth more. They feel undervalued. Cheated. They start looking for a new job. The money saved by not paying employees what they are worth is soon going to cost the company many times more than they “saved”.</p>
<p>When a great employee leaves, the company loses a lot. A lot of money. A lot of time. A lot of energy. A lot of credibility. Other employees might start to wonder: “Why did Sam leave for another job?” “Does he know something we don’t?” “Should we be looking for jobs too?”</p>
<p>So how can a company retain its great staff?</p>
<p>What if employees didn’t have to ask for a raise?</p>
<p>What if a company noticed employee contributions?</p>
<p>What if employees didn’t have to worry about their salary at all?</p>
<p>What if the company automatically upgraded employee salaries to the current market rate?</p>
<p>What kind of workplace would that be?</p>
<p>As direct result employees would:</p>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>Feel more valued.</li>
<li>Stop stressing out about salary.</li>
<li>Stop stressing out about salary reviews and “asking” for a raise.</li>
<li>Stop making themselves “look” important and contribute instead.</li>
<li>Stop looking jobs to get more money.</li>
<li>Give their full attention to the tasks at hand.</li>
</ol>
<p>Wouldn’t that be nice?</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 29 Apr 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-04-29-automatic-salary-upgrades.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>People Safari</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-04-28-people-safari.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Observe what people <strong>do</strong>, as opposed to what they <strong>say</strong> they do. In most cases you’ll find there is a sharp contrast. Actions portray a more authentic story.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Tue, 28 Apr 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-04-28-people-safari.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Get Away from the Computer</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-04-26-get-away-from-the-computer.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>For most programmers, programming is usually our day job as well as our hobby. But “working” all the time dulls our intuition.</p>
<p>We think we get a “lot done” but in reality we might be efficiently working on something that we shouldn’t work on at all.</p>
<p>Take time to get away from the computer. Spend time with nature. Catch up with friends or family. Do something fun! Get some exercise!</p>
<p>You will find that rather than hindering your “progress”, it leads to insights and questions you would never have had otherwise. “Obvious” answers will pop into your head. Your brain just needs the time to find the connections between all the information you feed it on a daily basis.</p>
<p>Most of all it will help you balance your life.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 26 Apr 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-04-26-get-away-from-the-computer.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Get a Different Perspective</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-04-26-get-a-different-perspective.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://twitter.com/pamelafox">Pamela Fox</a> shared this idea on Twitter a while back:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Do something in a new way each day. Whether it’s eating a different lunch or walking a different way to work or writing with your left hand. Keep doing things that give you a new perspective.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Doing something differently to the way you “always do it” has the side effect of waking up your brain. You are forced to “tune in” as opposed to “tuning out”. You notice new things. You enjoy your experience more. You learn. :)</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 26 Apr 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-04-26-get-a-different-perspective.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Show Committers on a Git Repository</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-04-24-show-committers-on-a-git-repository.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>How is git so awesome? Today I was wondering how I’d go about listing all the unique committers to a git repository. As usual there was some git fu that I had yet to learn:</p>
<pre class="command"><code>git shortlog -ns</code></pre>
<p>Running this on the Scala <a href="https://github.com/puffnfresh/wartremover">Wartremover repository</a> returns the following:</p>
<pre class="terminal"><code>   126  Brian McKenna
    15  Michal Rus
     9  Michał Rus
     7  Rob Norris
     7  George Leontiev
     6  Nikolay Stanchenko
     6  Pedro Furlanetto
     3  Maxwell Swadling
     3  Jonathan Ferguson
     2  xuwei-k
     2  James Earl Douglas
     2  Dale Wijnand
     2  Cody Allen
     2  Zach Weatherby
     1  Leif Warner
     1  Peter Hausel
     1  Lars Hupel
     1  Jason Zaugg
     1  ChrisNeveu
     1  Vladimir Kostyukov</code></pre>
<p>If you want to further order by email use:</p>
<pre class="command"><code>git shortlog -nes</code></pre>
<p>enjoy! :)</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Fri, 24 Apr 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-04-24-show-committers-on-a-git-repository.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Do Something Nice</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-04-22-do-something-nice.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Try to do something nice for a complete stranger at least once a week. I’m not sure where I came across this idea but it’s a good one. If you find it hard to do things for strangers, try this on your work colleagues, friends or family.</p>
<p>This practice helps you to stop focussing on yourself all the time. It enables you think about someone else at least once a week. It also makes you feel great. :)</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 22 Apr 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-04-22-do-something-nice.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Disconnect</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-04-22-disconnect.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>People are too “connected” these days. Connected with their devices that is. The more “connected” we are with our devices, the less connected we seem to be with real people and the world around us.</p>
<p>Take time everyday to disconnect. Put away your mobile phone. Unplug those headphones. This practice will help you reconnect with the physical world and people around you. It will make your life a lot richer than when staring at a screen all day.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 22 Apr 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-04-22-disconnect.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Banishing Multitasking from our Repertoire</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-04-22-banishing-multitasking-from-our-repertoire.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Ideas from the chapter “Banishing Multitasking from our Repertoire” from the book <a href="http://99u.com/book/manage-your-day-to-day-2">Manage Your Day-To-Day</a> by Christian Jarrett.</p>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>Switching tasks sends us down a rabbit hole, pulling our attention away from our priority work for much longer than we anticipate.</li>
<li>A good stopping point on a project helps to free your mind from nagging questions and gives you mental closure.</li>
</ol>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 22 Apr 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-04-22-banishing-multitasking-from-our-repertoire.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Ignore Everybody</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-04-20-ignore-everybody.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Ideas from the chapter “Ignore Everybody” from the book <a href="http://gapingvoid.com/ie">Ignore Everybody And 39 other Keys to Creativity</a> by Hugh MacLeod.</p>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>The more original your idea is, the less good advice other people will be able to give you.</li>
<li>You don’t know if your idea is any good the moment it is created. Neither does anyone else.</li>
<li>A big idea will change you.</li>
<li>Good ideas alter the power balance in relationships. That is why good ideas are initially resisted.</li>
<li>Good ideas come with a heavy burden, which is why so few people execute them.</li>
</ol>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Mon, 20 Apr 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-04-20-ignore-everybody.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Honing your Creative Practice</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-04-20-honing-your-creative-practice.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Ideas from the chapter “Honing your creative practice” from the book <a href="http://99u.com/book/manage-your-day-to-day-2">Manage Your Day-To-Day</a> with Seth Godin.</p>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>Lots and lots of people are creative when they feel like it, but you are only going to become a professional if you do it when you don’t feel like it. And that emotional waiver is why this is your work and not your hobby.</li>
<li>Practice is a big part of being creative.</li>
<li>Being creative means you have to sell your ideas. Selling is part of it because if you don’t sell it, there is no art.</li>
<li>It’s much easier to whine and sabotage yourself and blame the client, the system, and the economy. This is what you hide from - the noise in your head that says you are not good enough, that says it is not perfect, that says it could have been better.</li>
</ol>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Mon, 20 Apr 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-04-20-honing-your-creative-practice.html</guid>
</item>

    </channel> 
</rss>
