<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
    xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
    <channel>
        <title>BabylonCandle</title>
        <link>http://blog.ssanj.net</link>
        <description><![CDATA[The blog of Sanjiv Sahayam]]></description>
        <atom:link href="http://blog.ssanj.net/feed.xml" rel="self"
                   type="application/rss+xml" />
        <lastBuildDate>Wed, 15 Jul 2015 00:00:00 UT</lastBuildDate>
        <item>
    <title>Using Sublime for Scala Development</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-07-15-using-sublime-for-scala-development.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Writing Scala code with <a href="https://www.jetbrains.com/idea">Intellij</a> has become quite annoying. Intellij is definitely the tool of choice for Java coding. With all that “enterprisey” brew-ha going on you need all the help you can get.</p>
<p>Lately, Intellij has started to get bloated. And unreliable. It’s always indexing things at the most inconvenient times. This is specially the case when you open a project and hope to start working. It also has quite a few bugs and crashes frequently. It’s also in competition with sbt for its lock file. Forget about running sbt and Intellij at the same time.</p>
<p>I’ve started playing around with using <a href="http://www.sublimetext.com">Sublime Text</a> as a Scala IDE. Initially I did not know how to start work. I had become so dependent on Intellij to tell me everything about anything that I had no clue how to proceed. I couldn’t CTRL + Click. I couldn’t CMD + SPACE. I was powerless.</p>
<p>After persisting for a few hours and after installing a bunch of useful plugins I was getting somewhere.</p>
<p>I found that it was much easier to focus on the code. Intellij was not constantly prompting me for stuff, or indexing or crashing or doing something else distracting. I ended up writing simpler code as I had to use less tooling. The whole experience was much more enjoyable.</p>
<p>In a subsequent article I’ll get into the details on how I customised my Sublime environment to make it useful for Scala development. If in the meantime you are considering leaving Intellij for Sublime, Vim, Atom or some other editor, definitely go for it. You will not regret it.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jul 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-07-15-using-sublime-for-scala-development.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>sanjiv sahayam</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Stop Complaining on Twitter</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-07-15-stop-complaining-on-twitter.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>It almost seems like Twitter was built for complaining. You often see people ranting and raging about some inanity. I recently had one of those “ranty” moments and almost tweeted about.</p>
<p>This time I chose to do something different. I chose to disguise my rant in a (bad) joke. Safari on my iPhone was crashing. A lot. Instead of ranting, here’s what I said:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Safari on the iPhone can’t stop crashing. I’m tempted to let Google record all my conversations so that I can browse the Internet. #apple</p>
</blockquote>
<p>So it’s not that funny, but at least it ties together two recent events. It also made me use my brain and made me smile. :)</p>
<p>The next time you want to rant or complain about something on twitter, consider writing something humorous instead.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jul 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-07-15-stop-complaining-on-twitter.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>sanjiv sahayam</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Show the Content of a Git Stash Index</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-07-15-show-the-content-of-a-git-stash-index.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>If you’ve ever wondered how to see the contents of files within a Git stash, you are not alone.</p>
<p>List your Git stashes with:</p>
<pre class="command"><code>git stash list</code></pre>
<p>Then show the contents of the stash with:</p>
<pre class="command"><code>git stash show -p stash@{stash_number}</code></pre>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jul 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-07-15-show-the-content-of-a-git-stash-index.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>sanjiv sahayam</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Three Hundred Percent Better</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-07-12-three-hundred-percent-better.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>I was recently having a conversation with a co-worker. He mentioned that he had come into a work place where someone who had recently left was “three hundred percent better” than everyone else there. He went on to say that people had compared themselves with this “genius” and then felt horrible about themselves. They thought they were no longer good enough to do anything important. They thought they knew nothing. They were “broken”.</p>
<p>Working with someone three hundred percent better than myself would be a dream come true. I would join a workplace just to be around such an individual. My thinking is that even if I improve on myself by ten percent by being around this genius, it would be an awesome win. How did this guy or gal become so good? How do they think about things? How can I learn to be more like them?</p>
<p>The real clincher was that I had worked with this individual at a previous workplace. He had put me on a path to learning that I would not be on otherwise. I feel deeply indebted to him. I have improved by much more than ten percent by being around him. By learning from him I was forced to put away any arrogant notions that I knew everything. I found it refreshing to be around someone who was that good at what they did. It made me want to become an improved version of myself. I still have much to learn and I am happy with that. I try to improve in small increments everyday. I actively seek out other “geniuses” to learn from.</p>
<p>What’s fascinating is that different people reacted to the same stimulus in different ways. For some, it was the end of all they held dear, for others it was the road to mastery they always dreamt of.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-07-12-three-hundred-percent-better.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>sanjiv sahayam</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>How to Install Yosemite on a New SSD</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-07-12-how-to-instal-yosemite-on-a-new-ssd.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>After I got my new MBP, I decided to sell my old 2010 MBP. I wanted to keep all my existing data on my old laptop, so I decided to swap out its SSD and to put in a brand new one.</p>
<p>The process of installing Yosemite on the new SSD was not as straightforward as I would have liked. I thought I’d blog about it to help anyone else who needed to do the same.</p>
<p>Basically I was trying to sell a 2010 MBP with a new SSD, with Yosemite installed but not configured.</p>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>Download Yosemite installation from the App store. It might complain that you already have it installed but download it anyway. It will be downloaded to <strong>/Applications</strong> and be named <strong>Install OS X Yosemite.app</strong></li>
<li><a href="https://support.apple.com/en-au/HT201372">Create a bootable image from the Yosemite installer</a> on a USB stick larger than 6GB. In a terminal run:</li>
</ol>
<pre class="terminal scrollx"><code>sudo /Applications/Install\ OS\ X\ Yosemite.app/Contents/Resources/createinstallmedia --volume /Volumes/MyVolume --applicationpath /Applications/Install\ OS\ X\ Yosemite.app</code></pre>
<p><em>where MyVolume is the name of your USB stick. Change this to match the name of your USB stick.</em></p>
<ol start="3" style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>Physically install SSD into the target laptop.</li>
<li>Insert the Yosemite USB stick into the target laptop and power up. (<em>This might take a while.</em>)</li>
<li>When the menu finally turns up, choose <strong>Disk Utility</strong> and format the SSD as <strong>Mac OS Extended (Journaled)</strong> with a unique name.</li>
<li>Once complete, exit from <strong>Disk Utility</strong> and return the main menu.</li>
<li>Choose to <strong>Install OS X</strong> on the formatted SSD.</li>
<li>Follow the prompts until Yosemite is installed.</li>
</ol>
<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=F82ThP-6jeA">Here’s link to a video on how to physically install the SSD as well as run the software installation</a>.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jul 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-07-12-how-to-instal-yosemite-on-a-new-ssd.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>sanjiv sahayam</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>We need Guts</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-07-08-we-need-guts.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Not in a zombie apocalypse-kind of way. Seth Godin in <a href="http://sethgodin.typepad.com/seths_blog/2015/06/the-fruitless-search-for-extraordinary-people-willing-to-take-ordinary-jobs.html">The fruitless search for extraordinary people willing to take ordinary jobs</a> says that:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Building an extraordinary organization takes guts. The guts to trust the team, to treat them with respect and to go to ridiculous lengths to find, keep and nurture people who care enough to make a difference.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>He also says that amazing people need to be nurtured:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>It’s unreasonable to expect that you’ll develop amazing people when you don’t give them room to change, grow and fail.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I couldn’t agree more.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jul 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-07-08-we-need-guts.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>sanjiv sahayam</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Take a Breath</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-07-08-take-a-breath.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>As developers we are constantly working on the “next critical” task. This could be a new feature that was promised to a customer. It could be some infrastructural change that we need to juggle without disruption to our usual services. It could be a bug that is costing us money by the hour.</p>
<p>Whatever it is, we need to learn to take a break and do some review after we finish one of these tasks. Mostly, we move directly to the next critical task. No break. No reward. No time to review what we’ve learned. No time to revel in the fact that we achieved something significant. That we added value.</p>
<p>There would definitely have been some late nights and some very stressful moments in getting to the finish line. The business needs to acknowledge this. There should be some scheduled down time at the end of every critical task. This might mean giving the team involved a few days off to recover. It might also mean having a small celebration to mark the occasion. There could be other types of rewards like money or time to work on their own projects.</p>
<p>This rest and reward will help the team to de-stress and replenish. It will help them return to work enthusiastic about the next task on their list. In addition there should be a retrospective where the team understand their successes and try to learn from their mistakes. All useful information for the next task.</p>
<p>Having this rest, reward and review can help sustain a team through many critical tasks without burning out. It would be myopic to burn out a great team that consistently delivers value.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jul 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-07-08-take-a-breath.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>sanjiv sahayam</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>What Happens when you don&apos;t Care</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-07-05-what-happens-when-you-don%27t-care.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>In <a href="http://www.jamesaltucher.com/2015/06/what-happens-when-you-dont-care">his post on not caring</a>, James Altucher shares some keen insights.</p>
<p>Only say “yes” to opportunities you love:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>I say “No” to any opportunities that will take me from what I love doing.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Do what you love to have more opportunities:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>I have NEVER seen someone who ultimately couldn’t get opportunities that they wanted if they simply stopped caring and started doing the best at what they loved.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Speak less and listen more:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>I like to try and speak less than that. It builds up mental energy to speak less. And forces me to listen more when everyone else has their opinions.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Push the boundaries of what’s possible:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>When I don’t care, it’s much easier to over-promise and over-deliver. That’s what makes you a magnet of opportunity.</p>
</blockquote>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 05 Jul 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-07-05-what-happens-when-you-don%27t-care.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>sanjiv sahayam</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>How to Destroy your Business</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-07-05-how-to-destroy-your-business.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Something I’ve been doing to <a href="http://sanj.ink/posts/2015-04-26-get-a-different-perspective.html">get a different perspective</a> has been to visit different coffee shops during the week.</p>
<p>A few weeks ago I had seen an interesting coffee shop near the train station and thought I’d give it a try. This coffee shop that will go unnamed, broke one of the golden rules of running a business:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Never deliver a sub par product in a highly competitive market.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Given the number of coffee shops per square metre in the Brisbane CBD, a coffee shop can’t afford to serve bad coffee. This is coffee shop suicide. If that wasn’t bad enough, I was hit with the “Five dollar minimum on fpos” statement. This was followed by the “you can pre-purchase your weekly coffee on this card” scam. Um, no thanks.</p>
<p>Five minutes later I dumped their crappy coffee in the bin and headed back to <a href="https://www.facebook.com/coffeeanthology">my usual</a> for an awesome coffee.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 05 Jul 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-07-05-how-to-destroy-your-business.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>sanjiv sahayam</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Your App should Release Endorphins</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-07-02-your-app-should-release-endorphins.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Most current apps are frustrating to use. They constantly crash - an <a href="http://theleanstartup.com/principles">MVP</a> mentality where we are the guinea pigs in an elaborate entrepreneurial experiment.</p>
<p>They are cluttered and chaotic. We are constantly bombarded with decisions we don’t want or need to make. “Would you like to subscribe to this newsletter?” or “App X wants to access your contacts/your friends list/your location”. Hell no! These apps cause stress hormones like Adrenaline and Norepinephrine to be released into our bloodstream. Shitty apps are bad for our health.</p>
<p>I recently read about <a href="http://blog.invisionapp.com/why-empty-states-deserve-more-design-time">why empty states deserve more design time</a>. This made me think about how apps could be different.</p>
<p>What if apps were fun to use? What if they were so enjoyable that it resulted in the release of Endorphins into our bloodstream? What if the guiding principle of apps design was to never stress the user? How would we need to change our current design mindset to achieve that?</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Thu, 02 Jul 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-07-02-your-app-should-release-endorphins.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>sanjiv sahayam</dc:creator>
</item>

    </channel>
</rss>
