<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>BabylonCandle</title>
        <link>http://blog.ssanj.net</link>
        <description><![CDATA[The blog of Sanjiv Sahayam]]></description>
        <atom:link href="http://blog.ssanj.net/feed.xml" rel="self"
                   type="application/rss+xml" />
        <lastBuildDate>Wed, 13 May 2015 00:00:00 UT</lastBuildDate>
        <item>
    <title>The Tim Ferriss Show Interviews Matt Mullenweg</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-05-13-the-tim-ferriss-show-matt-mullenweg.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Some interesting ideas from <a href="http://fourhourworkweek.com/2015/02/09/matt-mullenweg">The Tim Ferriss Show’s interview with Matt Mullenweg</a></p>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>Open source was the most important idea he was exposed to in his lifetime.</li>
<li>Open source is a bill of rights for software. The four freedoms of <a href="http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/gpl.html">GPL</a>:
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>You can use it for any purpose.</li>
<li>You can deconstruct the software to understand how it works.</li>
<li>You can modify it.</li>
<li>You can distribute your modifications.</li>
</ol></li>
<li>The (famous) 5 minute installation of Wordpress. It was not famous, but became so. It did something totally different to the big players in the market.</li>
<li>Philosophy and political science help you to think about systems and incentives.</li>
<li>How do you self-enable people?</li>
<li>If you do X today, what does that result in tomorrow, a year from now, ten years from now?</li>
<li>The dog chasing the car Metaphor. What does the dog do if it catches the car?</li>
<li>Plan for success. What is the natural conclusion of your idea if it’s really successful?</li>
<li>Gives the Wordpress community a nudge to go in directions they would not go by themselves.</li>
<li>Uses Dvorak as an alternative keyboard.</li>
<li>Automattic does not send email. They use <a href="http://p2theme.com">P2</a>. Threads help follow a conversation. How does a new employee follow ten years of email?</li>
<li>Keep information public. Trust people.</li>
<li><a href="https://slack.com">Slack</a> is “consumer grade” - it doesn’t suck like most enterprise software.</li>
<li>Rig the game so you can win. Eg. Doing one push-up a day.</li>
</ol>
<div class="quote">
Unschedule more of your life. Create space. Read a lot more to give yourself creative inspiration or the ideas for the next big thing.
</div>
<ol start="15" style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>The hardest thing is spending time on the most important things in life.</li>
<li><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parkinson%27s_law_of_triviality">Bike shedding</a> - Spending a lot of time on discussions on relatively unimportant but simple issues, while neglecting the more important but complex issues.</li>
<li>Playing Saxophone taught him how to breathe, how to be on stage in front of people, how to listen and respond, how to co-composing on the fly, how to learn new things and how to practice deliberately.</li>
<li>If you only practise the things you are good at you’ll never get better at the things you are not good at.</li>
<li>Business Judo: what can we do that google can’t do?</li>
<li>Advice to his twenty year old self: Slow down to go further. Build foundations. Build things that last long term.</li>
<li>Take time for yourself, meditate, focuss on the present moment.</li>
</ol>
<div class="quote">
Everyone is interesting! If you’re bored, the problem is with you not the other person. It’s all about figuring out what someone is into or what they are passionate about.
</div>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 13 May 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-05-13-the-tim-ferriss-show-matt-mullenweg.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Meritocracy over Dictatorships</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-05-12-meritocracy-over-dictatorships.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>I had lunch with a close friend of mine today. He mentioned how his ideas for improvements were continually shot down at work. Even when he could point to legitimate reasons for wanting to change something that was clearly broken, his lead overrode his decision and continued to work in a sloppy fashion. This all sounded very demoralising.</p>
<p>This is troubling on multiple levels. For one, all ideas should be evaluated scientifically on its merit and not on the whims and fancies of those “leading” the team. A sign of a good leader is someone who can discuss the pros and cons of any solution and give legitimate reasons as to why one course of action should be preferred over another. He should also be willing to continually experiment with improving how work is done.</p>
<p>Secondly, if the leaders of any team are not continually learning and questioning their assumptions they will stop improving. In the long run they will become a cancer that attacks the motivation and innovation of all employees of the company that want to do a good job.</p>
<p>If you see these sorts of dictators at work, it’s time to overthrow them.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Tue, 12 May 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-05-12-meritocracy-over-dictatorships.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Continually Invest in ...</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-05-12-continually-invest-in.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<div>
<div class="quote">
Continually investing in the success of others is what will eventually lead to success for yourself.
</div>
<div class="attribution">
Chris Hadfield
</div>
<div>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>Tue, 12 May 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-05-12-continually-invest-in.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Secondary Constructors in Scala Case Classes</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-05-10-secondary-constructors-in-case-classes.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Recently I needed to add a secondary constructor to a case class and came across a strange problem. The secondary constructor was not visible.</p>
<p>Given the following case class:</p>
<pre class="sourceCode scala"><code class="sourceCode scala"><span class="kw">final</span> <span class="kw">case</span> <span class="kw">class</span> <span class="fu">SomeThing</span>(x:String)</code></pre>
<p>I can call it as follows:</p>
<pre class="sourceCode scala"><code class="sourceCode scala"><span class="fu">SomeThing</span>(<span class="st">&quot;test&quot;</span>)</code></pre>
<p>I add a secondary constructor that takes in an Int:</p>
<pre class="sourceCode scala"><code class="sourceCode scala"><span class="kw">final</span> <span class="kw">case</span> <span class="kw">class</span> <span class="fu">SomeThing</span>(x:String) {
    <span class="kw">def</span> <span class="kw">this</span>(n:Int) = <span class="kw">this</span>(n.<span class="fu">toString</span>)
}</code></pre>
<p>When I try to use use the secondary constructor:</p>
<pre class="sourceCode scala"><code class="sourceCode scala"><span class="fu">SomeThing</span>(<span class="dv">3</span>)</code></pre>
<p>We get the following compiler error:</p>
<pre class="terminal"><code>Error:(19, 23) type mismatch;
 found   : Int(3)
 required: String
    SomeThing(3)
              ^</code></pre>
<p>It looks like the primary constructor that takes in a String can be seen but not the secondary one that takes in an Int. What’s the problem?</p>
<p>This post on <a href="http://www.scala-lang.org/old/node/976">case class auxiliary constructors</a> explains how to work around it:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>at present you have to use “new” on any constructor except the primary.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Right. So we can call the secondary constructor like so:</p>
<pre class="sourceCode scala"><code class="sourceCode scala"><span class="kw">new</span> <span class="fu">SomeThing</span>(<span class="dv">3</span>)</code></pre>
<p>That’s a bit inconsistent.</p>
<p><a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/2400794/overload-constructor-for-scalas-case-classes">This SO article</a> explains that defining a secondary constructor on the companion object would remove any need for using the <strong>new</strong> keyword from the calling site:</p>
<pre class="sourceCode scala"><code class="sourceCode scala"> <span class="kw">object</span> SomeThing {
    <span class="kw">def</span> <span class="fu">apply</span>(b:Boolean) = <span class="kw">new</span> <span class="fu">SomeThing</span>(b.<span class="fu">toString</span>)
 }

 <span class="fu">SomeThing</span>(<span class="kw">true</span>)</code></pre>
<p>The above workaround gives the impression that the secondary constructor behaves much like the primary constructor. This seems to be the “cleanest” solution for using secondary constructors, at least for now.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 10 May 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-05-10-secondary-constructors-in-case-classes.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Reasons</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-05-07-reasons.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Stop working just for money. You can earn money in many different ways. Chances are that you can earn a lot more money for the work you do now at another workplace.</p>
<p>Any job you take should give you something money can’t buy directly. It could be technological know-how, a great team, perks like working from home or the freedom to work on open source projects as part of your work day.</p>
<p>You need to know <strong>why</strong> you work at any workplace. Why this company and not any other? These reasons will help you to focus on what is important to you. They will help you avoid all that is not in alignment with your vision. You will stop doing “busy work” and reacting to things that do not concern you in the least. Your list of reasons guides you through it all.</p>
<p>At some point the reasons that kept you at a workplace will no longer exist. Your vision of what you want can change. When this happens it is a clear indication that it is time to move on. Your list of reasons will take any emotion out of the decision. It will also clarify whether to stay at a company or whether to leave.</p>
<p>Have these reasons clearly in your mind as you go about your work everyday.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Thu, 07 May 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-05-07-reasons.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Counting Straws</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-05-07-counting-straws.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>The last straw. It gets all the attention. “It was the last straw” people say. People think that the “last straw” is what causes disastrous consequences. Consequences like someone quitting their job or leaving a relationship or giving up on a business venture. It is not.</p>
<p>What people forget to notice is the other hundred little straws that made this last one matter. People only remember the last bad thing that happened to someone before they quit or leave or do something else permanent.</p>
<p>Try to seek out the trail of penultimate straws that lead to any catastrophic event. You’ll find there are many.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Thu, 07 May 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-05-07-counting-straws.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Understanding our Compulsions</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-05-03-understanding-our-compulsions.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Ideas from the chapter “Understanding our Compulsions” from the book <a href="http://99u.com/book/manage-your-day-to-day-2">Manage Your Day-To-Day</a> with Dan Ariely.</p>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>In order manage your time better you need some way of measuring your progress. Big tasks that take a lot of effort over a long time can be seen as wasteful. This is because we can’t sometimes measure our progress.</li>
<li>If you work on a computer you can’t see all the effort of your previous work - it is lost in deletes and updates.</li>
<li>Keep a diary of your progress. Keep older versions around.</li>
</ol>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 03 May 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-05-03-understanding-our-compulsions.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Tell me what You...</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-05-03-tell-me-what-you.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<div>
<div class="quote">
Tell me what you pay attention to and I will tell you who you are.
</div>
<div class="attribution">
José Ortega Y Gasset
</div>
<div>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 03 May 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-05-03-tell-me-what-you.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Learning to Create Amidst Chaos</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-05-03-learning-create-amidst-chaos.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Ideas from the chapter “Learning to Create Amidst Chaos” from the book <a href="http://99u.com/book/manage-your-day-to-day-2">Manage Your Day-To-Day</a> by Erin Rooney Dolan.</p>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>Negative distractions interfere with our creative work. (Eg. TV, Social Media, Chatting with coworkers etc.)</li>
<li>Positive distractions help us to do more creative work. (Eg. Rewards after completing a task, going for a walk etc.)</li>
<li>Developing any habit can strengthen willpower in other areas of your life.</li>
<li>Once a new habit is ingrained and can be completed without much effort or thought, that energy can be turned to other activities requiring more self-control.</li>
<li>Tasks done on “autopilot” do not use up our stockpile of energy like tasks that have to be consciously completed.</li>
<li>Getting a good night’s sleep will help you improve your self-control.</li>
<li>Shifting from mindful to mindless work gives the brain time to process complex problems in a relaxed state and also restores the energy necessary for the next round of mindful work.</li>
<li>Repetition is a form of mesmerism. Mesmerise yourself to reach a deeper state of mind.</li>
<li>To hold repetition for a long period of time requires mental and physical strength.</li>
</ol>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 03 May 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-05-03-learning-create-amidst-chaos.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Cushy Lives</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-05-03-cushy-lives.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Recently when having lunch with a friend at a very busy restaurant in Brisbane, our waitress offered us the choice of sharing a table with some other patrons. While it was not ideal we agreed and sat down at this shared table. Given the choice we probably wouldn’t have shared a table with anyone.</p>
<p>We had our lunch with absolutely no dramas at all. It was kind of liberating to be seated next to strangers. Many different conversations were taking place. Many different dishes arrived. People came and went. We had all come for some yummy food. We all needed a seat. So why not share? Why isn’t this something we naturally do?</p>
<p>I think part of the problem is that we have it so good here in Australia - Brisbane especially. We have loads of personal space. Parking is not a problem. Traffic is minimal. Commutes are short. I wonder if we have become victims of our cushy lives?</p>
<p>Another example is seating on the train. Commuters often choose to either sit in an empty two seater or to stand, rather than sharing a seat with someone else. The train is full of half empty seats with loads of people standing. This would never happen in a third-world country. Again I blame this, which I myself am guilty of, on our rather cushy life. If we have ten times more people on the train, there’d be a mad rush to share any seat in sight. Maybe we need more people on the train. Or less trains. I wonder if strife creates a more caring society?</p>
<p>Don’t get me wrong. I am happy that life in Brissy is so nice. I just don’t want to forget to connect with society when the opportunity arises.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 03 May 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-05-03-cushy-lives.html</guid>
</item>

    </channel> 
</rss>
