<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>BabylonCandle</title>
        <link>http://blog.ssanj.net</link>
        <description><![CDATA[The blog of Sanjiv Sahayam]]></description>
        <atom:link href="http://blog.ssanj.net/feed.xml" rel="self"
                   type="application/rss+xml" />
        <lastBuildDate>Sun, 03 May 2015 00:00:00 UT</lastBuildDate>
        <item>
    <title>Understanding our Compulsions</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-05-03-understanding-our-compulsions.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Ideas from the chapter “Understanding our Compulsions” from the book <a href="http://99u.com/book/manage-your-day-to-day-2">Manage Your Day-To-Day</a> with Dan Ariely.</p>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>In order manage your time better you need some way of measuring your progress. Big tasks that take a lot of effort over a long time can be seen as wasteful. This is because we can’t sometimes measure our progress.</li>
<li>If you work on a computer you can’t see all the effort of your previous work - it is lost in deletes and updates.</li>
<li>Keep a diary of your progress. Keep older versions around.</li>
</ol>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 03 May 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-05-03-understanding-our-compulsions.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Tell me what You...</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-05-03-tell-me-what-you.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<div>
<div class="quote">
Tell me what you pay attention to and I will tell you who you are.
</div>
<div class="attribution">
José Ortega Y Gasset
</div>
<div>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 03 May 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-05-03-tell-me-what-you.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Learning to Create Amidst Chaos</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-05-03-learning-create-amidst-chaos.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Ideas from the chapter “Learning to Create Amidst Chaos” from the book <a href="http://99u.com/book/manage-your-day-to-day-2">Manage Your Day-To-Day</a> by Erin Rooney Dolan.</p>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>Negative distractions interfere with our creative work. (Eg. TV, Social Media, Chatting with coworkers etc.)</li>
<li>Positive distractions help us to do more creative work. (Eg. Rewards after completing a task, going for a walk etc.)</li>
<li>Developing any habit can strengthen willpower in other areas of your life.</li>
<li>Once a new habit is ingrained and can be completed without much effort or thought, that energy can be turned to other activities requiring more self-control.</li>
<li>Tasks done on “autopilot” do not use up our stockpile of energy like tasks that have to be consciously completed.</li>
<li>Getting a good night’s sleep will help you improve your self-control.</li>
<li>Shifting from mindful to mindless work gives the brain time to process complex problems in a relaxed state and also restores the energy necessary for the next round of mindful work.</li>
<li>Repetition is a form of mesmerism. Mesmerise yourself to reach a deeper state of mind.</li>
<li>To hold repetition for a long period of time requires mental and physical strength.</li>
</ol>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 03 May 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-05-03-learning-create-amidst-chaos.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Cushy Lives</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-05-03-cushy-lives.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Recently when having lunch with a friend at a very busy restaurant in Brisbane, our waitress offered us the choice of sharing a table with some other patrons. While it was not ideal we agreed and sat down at this shared table. Given the choice we probably wouldn’t have shared a table with anyone.</p>
<p>We had our lunch with absolutely no dramas at all. It was kind of liberating to be seated next to strangers. Many different conversations were taking place. Many different dishes arrived. People came and went. We had all come for some yummy food. We all needed a seat. So why not share? Why isn’t this something we naturally do?</p>
<p>I think part of the problem is that we have it so good here in Australia - Brisbane especially. We have loads of personal space. Parking is not a problem. Traffic is minimal. Commutes are short. I wonder if we have become victims of our cushy lives?</p>
<p>Another example is seating on the train. Commuters often choose to either sit in an empty two seater or to stand, rather than sharing a seat with someone else. The train is full of half empty seats with loads of people standing. This would never happen in a third-world country. Again I blame this, which I myself am guilty of, on our rather cushy life. If we have ten times more people on the train, there’d be a mad rush to share any seat in sight. Maybe we need more people on the train. Or less trains. I wonder if strife creates a more caring society?</p>
<p>Don’t get me wrong. I am happy that life in Brissy is so nice. I just don’t want to forget to connect with society when the opportunity arises.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 03 May 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-05-03-cushy-lives.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Creation is in Part...</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-05-03-creation-is-in-part.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<div>
<div class="quote">
Creation is in part merely the business of foregoing the great and small distractions.
</div>
<div class="attribution">
E.B. White
</div>
<div>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 03 May 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-05-03-creation-is-in-part.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Autumn</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-05-03-autumn.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<div class="haiku">
It’s cold outside
</div>
<div class="haiku">
the kettle boils
</div>
<div class="haiku">
the cup awaits
</div>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 03 May 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-05-03-autumn.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>The Tim Ferriss Show Interviews James Altucher</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-05-02-the-tim-ferriss-show-james-altucher.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Some interesting ideas from <a href="http://fourhourworkweek.com/2014/07/11/james-altucher">The Tim Ferriss Show’s interview with James Altucher</a>:</p>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>You are the average of the 5 people you spend time with the most.</li>
<li>You should be grateful for abundance. Stop behaving like you are awesome and that you deserve greatness.</li>
<li>Having a routine is one way to mitigate risk.</li>
<li>Read inspiring writers before you start writing yourself.</li>
<li>Try to improve by 1% a week. This leads to enormous improvements over the course of a year.</li>
<li>It’s only through failure that we can find our way to success.</li>
</ol>
<div class="quote">
It’s like a blind man seeing the colour red - he’s not going to understand what I’ve been through.
</div>
<ol start="7" style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>If you loose a $100 you can easily make it back. If you loose 5 minutes you can never get that back.</li>
<li>Say no to things that you do not want to do.</li>
<li>Time is not money. Time is more valuable than money.</li>
</ol>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sat, 02 May 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-05-02-the-tim-ferriss-show-james-altucher.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Automatic Salary Upgrades</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-04-29-automatic-salary-upgrades.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>One of the many reasons people leave a workplace is to gain a higher salary. Employers, never really review salaries relative to their current market rate. Employers see this as investment in their bottom line: “Don’t pay employees more than you have to”. Employees, usually get a small raise to placate them until the next review with a list of “reasons” as to why the increment wasn’t higher. The whole review-mediocre-salary-increment cycle then repeats in the next review period.</p>
<p>Employees, at the back of their minds know, they are are worth more. They feel undervalued. Cheated. They start looking for a new job. The money saved by not paying employees what they are worth is soon going to cost the company many times more than they “saved”.</p>
<p>When a great employee leaves, the company loses a lot. A lot of money. A lot of time. A lot of energy. A lot of credibility. Other employees might start to wonder: “Why did Sam leave for another job?” “Does he know something we don’t?” “Should we be looking for jobs too?”</p>
<p>So how can a company retain its great staff?</p>
<p>What if employees didn’t have to ask for a raise?</p>
<p>What if a company noticed employee contributions?</p>
<p>What if employees didn’t have to worry about their salary at all?</p>
<p>What if the company automatically upgraded employee salaries to the current market rate?</p>
<p>What kind of workplace would that be?</p>
<p>As direct result employees would:</p>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>Feel more valued.</li>
<li>Stop stressing out about salary.</li>
<li>Stop stressing out about salary reviews and “asking” for a raise.</li>
<li>Stop making themselves “look” important and contribute instead.</li>
<li>Stop looking jobs to get more money.</li>
<li>Give their full attention to the tasks at hand.</li>
</ol>
<p>Wouldn’t that be nice?</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 29 Apr 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-04-29-automatic-salary-upgrades.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>People Safari</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-04-28-people-safari.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Observe what people <strong>do</strong>, as opposed to what they <strong>say</strong> they do. In most cases you’ll find there is a sharp contrast. Actions portray a more authentic story.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Tue, 28 Apr 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-04-28-people-safari.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Get Away from the Computer</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-04-26-get-away-from-the-computer.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>For most programmers, programming is usually our day job as well as our hobby. But “working” all the time dulls our intuition.</p>
<p>We think we get a “lot done” but in reality we might be efficiently working on something that we shouldn’t work on at all.</p>
<p>Take time to get away from the computer. Spend time with nature. Catch up with friends or family. Do something fun! Get some exercise!</p>
<p>You will find that rather than hindering your “progress”, it leads to insights and questions you would never have had otherwise. “Obvious” answers will pop into your head. Your brain just needs the time to find the connections between all the information you feed it on a daily basis.</p>
<p>Most of all it will help you balance your life.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 26 Apr 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-04-26-get-away-from-the-computer.html</guid>
</item>

    </channel> 
</rss>
