<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>BabylonCandle</title>
        <link>http://blog.ssanj.net</link>
        <description><![CDATA[The blog of Sanjiv Sahayam]]></description>
        <atom:link href="http://blog.ssanj.net/feed.xml" rel="self"
                   type="application/rss+xml" />
        <lastBuildDate>Sun, 17 May 2015 00:00:00 UT</lastBuildDate>
        <item>
    <title>Reading List</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-05-17-reading-list.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>I’ve decided to geek-out and put my <a href="https://github.com/ssanj/ReadingList">reading list on Github</a>.</p>
<p>If you have any book recommendations that you think I should check out send me a pull request or leave me a comment.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 17 May 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-05-17-reading-list.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Know When to Rest</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-05-17-know-when-to-rest.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>It’s great to a have a routine. It’s great to have goals. It’s great to work consistently day in and day out.</p>
<p>Sometimes you just don’t feel like you have the motivation. Your work feels like a chore. Or that you’ve done all you want to do for the moment. You may have lost your “flow” - where your craft just pours out of you without any provocation.</p>
<p>When this happens, take a break from your routine. You can never produce your best work when your heart is not in it.</p>
<p>Take a day, a week or even a month off. You could even build it into your routine. This time off will help you to revitalise your creative spirit and come back refreshed and renewed to do awesome work.</p>
<p>Don’t be afraid to break your routine when you need to.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 17 May 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-05-17-know-when-to-rest.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>But All the Good Stuff ...</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-05-17-but-all-the-good-stuff.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<div>
<div class="quote">
But all the good stuff comes from leaping. From doing the things that might not work.
</div>
<div class="attribution">
Seth Godin
</div>
<div>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 17 May 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-05-17-but-all-the-good-stuff.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Why I don&apos;t use a Coffee Loyalty Card</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-05-14-why-i-dont-use-a-loyalty-card.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Loyalty cards. You can’t buy anything these days without being prompted for one. By name they seem to imply some kind of loyalty which I doubt exists.</p>
<p>I have my coffee at an <a href="https://www.facebook.com/coffeeanthology">awesome coffee shop</a> everyday. I don’t keep going back because I can get one free coffee for every nine I buy. Quite the contrary. I find getting your loyalty card stamped or lining up your phone with some app to register your purchase quite annoying.</p>
<p>I go there because the coffee is good and it is reasonably priced. If the coffee stops being good or if the price rises exponentially, no amount of “loyalty” is going to get me to go back there.</p>
<p>Also, I like knowing that when I buy my tenth coffee, the owners of the coffee shop, a small business, don’t have to lose some of their profits just to keep me “loyal”.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Thu, 14 May 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-05-14-why-i-dont-use-a-loyalty-card.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Reset Everyday</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-05-14-reset-everyday.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Forget about past achievements or failures. Start anew everyday. Be a beginner. Forget about expectations. Enjoy your daily clean slate.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Thu, 14 May 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-05-14-reset-everyday.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>It&apos;s Good to be Alive</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-05-14-its-good-to-be-alive.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>It’s good to be alive. Always remember that. Everything else is unimportant. Enjoy the gift of today.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Thu, 14 May 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-05-14-its-good-to-be-alive.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>The Tim Ferriss Show Interviews Matt Mullenweg</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-05-13-the-tim-ferriss-show-matt-mullenweg.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Some interesting ideas from <a href="http://fourhourworkweek.com/2015/02/09/matt-mullenweg">The Tim Ferriss Show’s interview with Matt Mullenweg</a></p>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>Open source was the most important idea he was exposed to in his lifetime.</li>
<li>Open source is a bill of rights for software. The four freedoms of <a href="http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/gpl.html">GPL</a>:
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>You can use it for any purpose.</li>
<li>You can deconstruct the software to understand how it works.</li>
<li>You can modify it.</li>
<li>You can distribute your modifications.</li>
</ol></li>
<li>The (famous) 5 minute installation of Wordpress. It was not famous, but became so. It did something totally different to the big players in the market.</li>
<li>Philosophy and political science help you to think about systems and incentives.</li>
<li>How do you self-enable people?</li>
<li>If you do X today, what does that result in tomorrow, a year from now, ten years from now?</li>
<li>The dog chasing the car Metaphor. What does the dog do if it catches the car?</li>
<li>Plan for success. What is the natural conclusion of your idea if it’s really successful?</li>
<li>Gives the Wordpress community a nudge to go in directions they would not go by themselves.</li>
<li>Uses Dvorak as an alternative keyboard.</li>
<li>Automattic does not send email. They use <a href="http://p2theme.com">P2</a>. Threads help follow a conversation. How does a new employee follow ten years of email?</li>
<li>Keep information public. Trust people.</li>
<li><a href="https://slack.com">Slack</a> is “consumer grade” - it doesn’t suck like most enterprise software.</li>
<li>Rig the game so you can win. Eg. Doing one push-up a day.</li>
</ol>
<div class="quote">
Unschedule more of your life. Create space. Read a lot more to give yourself creative inspiration or the ideas for the next big thing.
</div>
<ol start="15" style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>The hardest thing is spending time on the most important things in life.</li>
<li><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parkinson%27s_law_of_triviality">Bike shedding</a> - Spending a lot of time on discussions on relatively unimportant but simple issues, while neglecting the more important but complex issues.</li>
<li>Playing Saxophone taught him how to breathe, how to be on stage in front of people, how to listen and respond, how to co-compose on the fly, how to learn new things and how to practice deliberately.</li>
<li>If you only practise the things you are good at you’ll never get better at the things you are not good at.</li>
<li>Business Judo: what can we do that google can’t do?</li>
<li>Advice to his twenty year-old-self: Slow down to go further. Build foundations. Build things that last long term.</li>
<li>Take time for yourself, meditate, focuss on the present moment.</li>
</ol>
<div class="quote">
Everyone is interesting! If you’re bored, the problem is with you not the other person. It’s all about figuring out what someone is into or what they are passionate about.
</div>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 13 May 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-05-13-the-tim-ferriss-show-matt-mullenweg.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>The James Altucher Show Interviews Seth Godin</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-05-13-the-james-altucher-show-seth-godin.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Some interesting ideas from <a href="https://www.stansberryradio.com/James-Altucher/Latest-Episodes/Episode/886/Ep-86-Seth-Godin-It-s-Your-Turn-Now-What">The James Altucher Show with Seth Godin</a></p>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>Keep track of the impact that you make on people.</li>
<li>People go where they grow.</li>
<li>The story is always about the person hearing the story.</li>
<li>The story is about the common ground.</li>
<li>Atmosphere Cancer: Was “Global Warming” a case of good publicity?</li>
<li>Do things that are easy for you to do that adds value but hard for other people to do.</li>
</ol>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 13 May 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-05-13-the-james-altucher-show-seth-godin.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>River</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-05-13-river.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<div class="haiku">
The warm sun on the water
</div>
<div class="haiku">
Shining like a million diamonds
</div>
<div class="haiku">
Gratitude
</div>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 13 May 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-05-13-river.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>If I had only focussed ...</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-05-13-if-i-had-only-focussed.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<div>
<div class="quote">
If I had only focused on big successes, then I would be disappointed most of the time. You have to focus on the small successes and make sure to celebrate them.
</div>
<div class="attribution">
Chris Hadfield
</div>
<div>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 13 May 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-05-13-if-i-had-only-focussed.html</guid>
</item>

    </channel> 
</rss>
