<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>BabylonCandle</title>
        <link>http://blog.ssanj.net</link>
        <description><![CDATA[The blog of Sanjiv Sahayam]]></description>
        <atom:link href="http://blog.ssanj.net/feed.xml" rel="self"
                   type="application/rss+xml" />
        <lastBuildDate>Sun, 08 Mar 2015 00:00:00 UT</lastBuildDate>
        <item>
    <title>Surround yourself with Smart People</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-03-08-surround-yourself-with-smart-people.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>In <a href="http://paulgraham.com/ecw.html">How to Be an Expert in a Changing World</a> Paul Graham states:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Surround yourself with the sort of people new ideas come from. If you want to notice quickly when your beliefs become obsolete, you can’t do better than to be friends with the people whose discoveries will make them so.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Make it a point to befriend people smarter than yourself. Challenge your thinking. Do things differently. Follow a different crowd. Pay it forward by being a “smarter” person to someone else.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 08 Mar 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-03-08-surround-yourself-with-smart-people.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Time Poor. Priority Rich</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-02-22-time-poor-priority-rich.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<h1 id="i-want-all-the-things">I want all the things</h1>
<p>As developers we have many projects on the go. Many new technologies we want to try out. Many new ways of working we want to trial. Many new concepts we need to understand. All these activities compete for our limited free time. Most likely you’ll only get a few hours of continuous time to spend across all these activities per week. So how can we focus on all these interests with limited time?</p>
<h1 id="three-please">Three please</h1>
<p>The first thing to realise is that you can’t focus on everything at the same time. You’ll never get anything done if you do. You need to chose. I’ve found that prioritising the work I do to be the simplest tool to ensure I get the most important work done. I write down the top three activities I’d like to either complete or focus on in my limited time. The way I choose my most important task is by asking the question: “Would I feel good about the time I spent working on this task if I got nothing else done?”. Then I repeat the same question for the second and third items. I do not list more than 3 items. I only focus on this small list and assume I’ll probably only get through first task. I may not even finish the first task. I have realised that I have to be okay with leaving work unfinished - if I run out of time. I turn off all social media. Then I get to work.</p>
<h1 id="enforce-the-gap">Enforce the gap</h1>
<p>I take a break when I finish a task on the list. It could be small as a minute to walk around or it could be a few minutes to grab a coffee etc or it could be longer. This break marks the end of a task and prevents me from jumping from task to task mindlessly. It helps me feel like I accomplished something. It also resets my brain to make it ready for the next task. This is helpful if my three tasks vary greatly in their implementation. Eg. Maybe I am moving from some backend code to frontend design and then onto installing some infrastructure software.</p>
<h1 id="same-time-next-week">Same time next week</h1>
<p>If I run out of time to finish even the first task, I can rest assured that I spent my time wisely focusing on the most important tasks at hand at the time. As I am okay with leaving the task unfinished for now, I know that I’ll get back to it next week - if it is still one of my top three tasks. I also try to wind down any tasks I might be doing ten to fifteen minutes prior to running out of all my alloted time. This helps me to stop when I need to without working overtime or rushing to get something done which obviously needs more time. Some things take time. You can’t complete everything in a day or a week or even a month.</p>
<h1 id="its-all-equal">It’s all equal</h1>
<p>What if I have tasks that are about equal in priority? I still choose only three. Then I split my time into three parts plus time for two breaks. I wind down each part ten to fifteen minutes prior to the end of the its alloted time. I then take a break as before. I then start the following task. This allows me to make reasonable progress across multiple tasks.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 22 Feb 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-02-22-time-poor-priority-rich.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Remove Untracked Changes with Git</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-02-15-remove-untracked-changes-with-git.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>So you’ve got a bunch of untracked files and folders in your git repo and you don’t want to delete them all manually one-by-one. How do you use the power of git to do this for you?</p>
<p><strong>git clean</strong> will remove all untracked files for you.</p>
<p>There are several variants:</p>
<p>Perform a dry run to display which files will be deleted:</p>
<p><code>git clean -dn</code></p>
<p>Once you are satisfied with the output then run:</p>
<p><code>git clean -df</code></p>
<p>This will remove all files and directories that are not tracked.</p>
<p>If you would like to perform an interactive removal of files and directories then use:</p>
<p><code>git clean -di</code></p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-02-15-remove-untracked-changes-with-git.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Logstash and Other Things</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-02-14-logstash-and-other-things.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>An very interesting and insightful presentation by Jordan Sissel about why and how <a href="http://logstash.net">Logstash</a> came about. This is from PuppetConf 2012.</p>
<iframe id="movie1" width="800" height="470" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/RuUFnog29M4" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>Yearly <a href="http://sysadvent.blogspot.com.au">Sysadvent</a> blog.</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/jordansissel/fpm">FPM - Build packages for multiple platforms (deb, rpm, etc) with great ease and sanity</a></li>
<li>There’s too much data to read in a log file. We need some way of filtering it to make sense.</li>
</ol>
<p class="quote">
What else sucks? Shitty error messages!
</p>

<ol start="4" style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>Write better error messages.</li>
<li>Hacks work as one-offs - not everyday. Hard to maintain. You are asked to write hacks all the time.</li>
</ol>
<div class="figure">
<img src="http://imgs.xkcd.com/comics/regular_expressions.png" alt="xkcd - regular expressions" /><p class="caption">xkcd - regular expressions</p>
</div>
<ol start="6" style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>People are using you as their computer interface.</li>
</ol>
<p class="quote">
Don’t be a human keyboard.
</p>

<ol start="7" style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>What is a log?</li>
</ol>
<p class="quote">
DATA + TIMESTAMP = LOG
</p>

<ol start="8" style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>Lifecycle of a log entry: record &gt; transmit &gt; analyse &gt; store &gt; delete</li>
<li><p>Opensource tools: transport: flume, fluentd, scribe, rsyslog, syslog-ng search+analytics: hadoop, graylog2, elsa storage: hdfs, cassandra, elasticsearch</p></li>
<li>Use Grok:
<ul>
<li>named pattern: %{patternName:Name}.</li>
<li>reuse matched patterns and transformations.</li>
<li>has types: Numbers, Strings etc.</li>
<li>patterns are unit tested.</li>
<li>multiline matches for Stacktraces etc.</li>
</ul></li>
</ol>
<p class="quote">
Stop inventing shitty time formats!
</p>

<ol start="12" style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>Statsd metrics can be visualized with tools like:
<ul>
<li>graphite</li>
<li>ganglia</li>
<li>circonus</li>
<li>boundary</li>
<li>librato</li>
<li>opentsdb</li>
<li>graylog2</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Apache uses gettimeofday() which changes when NTP synchronizes its clock. Leads to negative time values.</li>
</ol>
<p class="quote">
Does Apache have a Time Machine?
</p>

<ol start="14" style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>Features:
<ul>
<li>Transport and process logs to and from anywhere.</li>
<li>Search and analytics.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Design:
<ul>
<li>Logstash should fit your infrastructure.</li>
<li>Logstash is extendable (via plugins).</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Community:
<ul>
<li>If a newbie has a hard time it’s a bug (in the code or documentation etc).</li>
<li>Contributions are more than code (file bugs, feature requests, ideas,documentation etc).</li>
<li>Tools: Kibana, puppet module, logstash cli.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Links:
<ul>
<li><a href="http://logstash.net">logstash.net</a></li>
<li><a href="https://groups.google.com/forum/#!forum/logstash-users">logstash-user@googlegroups.com</a></li>
<li>#logstash on freenode (I am Whack)</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/elasticsearch/logstash/issues">issues</a></li>
<li><a href="https://twitter.com/jordansissel">@jordansissel</a></li>
</ul></li>
</ol>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sat, 14 Feb 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-02-14-logstash-and-other-things.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>The Feature-Positive Effect</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-02-11-the-feature-positive-effect.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>While investigating a system outage, a coworker was discussing looking for what was missing as opposed to what was present in the log files. That didn’t seem to make much sense to me initially. To illustrate his point he recalled a story from World War II. Many of the allied planes were being shot down and the ones that returned to the base were very badly damaged. A group of scientists were tasked with figuring out which parts of the planes needed extra armour to make it back home. Most scientist chose to add armour in places where the planes that returned to the base had the most bullet holes. The very fact that these planes returned to the base implied that the locations where they were shot in were not catastrophic. Hence the location of the current bullet holes were not the locations to re-enforce. But their first reaction was to be biased to what was present not what was absent. What they really needed was to examine a plane that did not make it back to the base.</p>
<p>This ties in with the “Feature-Positive Effect” described in the book <a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/The-Art-Thinking-Clearly-Decisions/dp/144475954X">The Art of Thinking Clearly by Rolf Dobelli</a>. It states that:</p>
<ul>
<li>We place greater emphasis on what is present than on what is absent.</li>
<li>We have problems perceiving non-events.</li>
<li>We are blind to what does not exist.</li>
</ul>
<p>Some other simple examples from the book:</p>
<ul>
<li>We realise if there is a war, but we do not appreciate the absence of war during peacetime.</li>
<li>If we are healthy, we rarely think about being sick.</li>
<li>If we get off a plane in Cancun, we do not stop to notice we did not crash.</li>
</ul>
<p>What I found most interesting about this was that, a psychological phenomenon or bias, was directly applicable to problem-solving in everyday life.</p>
<p>Think about the following when faced with a dilemma:</p>
<ul>
<li>What is present? What is absent?</li>
<li>What have you been shown? What have you not been shown?</li>
<li>What are its positive effects? What are its negative effects?</li>
<li>What have you been told? What have you not been told?</li>
</ul>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 11 Feb 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-02-11-the-feature-positive-effect.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>The Obstacle is the Way - Ryan Holiday</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-02-08-the-obstacle-is-the-way-ryan-holiday-notes.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Ideas from the book <a href="http://www.amazon.com/The-Obstacle-Is-Way-Timeless/dp/1591846358">The Obstacle is the Way by Ryan Holiday</a></p>
<p>“Obstacles are actually opportunities to test ourselves, try new things, and, ultimately, to triumph.” - Ryan Holiday</p>
<h2 id="perception">Perception</h2>
<ul>
<li>When faced with insurmountable obstacles we should try to:
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>Be objective.</li>
<li>Control emotions and keep an even keel.</li>
<li>Choose to see the good in the situation.</li>
<li>Ignore what disturbs and limits others.</li>
<li>Focus on what can be controlled.</li>
</ol></li>
<li>We decide what we make of each and every situation.</li>
<li>The observing eye sees simply what is there. The perceiving eye sees more than what is there.</li>
<li>Take your situation and pretend it is not happening to you. Pretend it is not important and that it doesn’t matter.</li>
<li>Is your perspective truly giving you <em>perspective</em> or is it actually causing you problems?</li>
<li>Focus on what you can change.</li>
</ul>
<p>“The trick to forget about the big picture is to look at everything close up” - Chuck Palahniuk</p>
<ul>
<li>Focus on the moment not the monsters that may or may not be up ahead.</li>
<li>Obstacles illuminate new options.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="action">Action</h2>
<ul>
<li>Doing new things invariably means obstacles. A new path is by definition uncleared.</li>
<li>It’s okay to be discouraged. It’s not okay to quit.</li>
<li>Settle in for the long haul and then try each and every possibility, and you’ll get there.</li>
</ul>
<p>“What is defeat? Nothing but education; nothing but the first steps to something better.” - Wendell Phillips</p>
<ul>
<li>Lessons come hard only if you are deaf to them.</li>
<li>Failure shows us the way by showing us what isn’t the way.</li>
<li>Excellence is a matter of steps. Excelling at this one, then that one, and then the one after that.</li>
<li>Even mammoth tasks become a series of component parts.</li>
<li>Take your time, don’t rush. Some problems are harder than others.</li>
</ul>
<p>“Whatever is rightly done, however humble, is noble” - Sir Henry Royce</p>
<p>“The cucumber is bitter? Then throw it out. There are brambles in the path? Then go around. That’s all you need to know.” - Marcus Aurelius</p>
<ul>
<li>Do the best with what you’ve got.</li>
</ul>
<p>“I don’t care if the cat is black or white as long as it catches mice.” - Deng Xiaoping</p>
<ul>
<li>Start thinking like a radical pragmatist.</li>
</ul>
<p>“Whoever cannot seek the unforeseen sees nothing, for the known way is an impasse” - Heraclitus</p>
<ul>
<li>Sometimes the longest way around is the shortest way home.</li>
</ul>
<p>“You never want a serious crisis to go to waste.” - Rahm Emanuel</p>
<p>“In the meantime, cling tooth and nail to the following rule: not to give into adversity, not to trust prosperity, and always take full note of fortune’s habit of behaving just as she pleases” - Seneca</p>
<ul>
<li>We must be willing to roll the dice and lose. Prepare at the end of the day for none of it to work.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="will">Will</h2>
<ul>
<li>Always try to:
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>Prepare yourself for more difficult times.</li>
<li>Accept what you are unable to change.</li>
<li>Manage your expectations.</li>
<li>Persevere.</li>
<li>Learn to love your fate and what happens to you.</li>
<li>Protect your inner self and retreat into yourself.</li>
<li>Submit to a greater, larger cause.</li>
<li>Remind yourself of your mortality.</li>
</ol></li>
<li>Have a premortem for your projects. Look at what could and will go wrong before you start.</li>
<li>You must never lower yourself to becoming a person you don’t like.</li>
<li>Don’t inflate your role and your importance.</li>
</ul>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 08 Feb 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-02-08-the-obstacle-is-the-way-ryan-holiday-notes.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Zero to One - Peter Thiel</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-01-31-zero-to-one-peter-thiel-notes.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Ideas from the book <a href="http://zerotoonebook.com/">Zero to one by Peter Thiel</a></p>
<h2 id="progress">Progress</h2>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>Horizontal - Copying things that work. Going from 1 to x. Eg. You take one typewriter and then build another hundred copies.</li>
<li>Vertical - Doing new things. Going from 0 to 1. Eg. You take a typewriter and build a word processor.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="startup-thinking">Startup Thinking</h2>
<ul>
<li>A new company’s most important strength is new thinking.</li>
<li>A startup has to question received ideas and rethink business from scratch.</li>
<li>A lone genius might create a classic work of art or literature but he will never create an entire industry on his own.</li>
<li>Startups operate on the principle that you need to work with other people to get things done. You also need to stay small enough so you actually can.</li>
<li>A startup is the largest group of people you can convince of a plan to build a different future.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="monopolies">Monopolies</h2>
<ul>
<li>Competition and Capitalism are opposites.</li>
<li>Monopolies exaggerate the power of their (nonexistent) competition to avoid scrutiny.</li>
<li>Entrepreneur’s exaggerate how powerful they are and understate the competition. “We are in a league of our own”.</li>
<li>The value of a business today is the sum of all the money it will make in the future. You also have to discount future cash flow to its present worth due to depreciation.</li>
<li>Ask yourself “will this business be around a decade from now?”</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="how-to-build-a-monopoly">How to Build a Monopoly</h2>
<h3 id="proprietary-technology">1. Proprietary Technology</h3>
<ul>
<li>A proprietary technology must be at least 10 times better than its closest substitute in some important dimension.</li>
<li>The easiest way to be 10 times better is to invent something new. Where there was nothing before, the increase in value is theoretically infinite.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="network-effects">2. Network Effects</h3>
<ul>
<li>Network effects make a product more useful as more people use it. Eg. Twitter.</li>
<li>To reap the benefits of network effects, your product must be useful to its very first users, when the network is naturally small.</li>
<li>You must start will specially small markets.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="economies-of-scale">3. Economies of Scale</h3>
<ul>
<li>The cost of creating another copy of your software should be close to zero.</li>
<li>A good startup should have the potential for great scale built into its first design.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="branding">4. Branding</h3>
<ul>
<li>A technology company can’t be built on brand alone.</li>
<li>Begin with substance then build your brand.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="how-to-choose-a-market">How to Choose A Market</h2>
<ul>
<li>Start with a very small market. Always err on the side of starting too small.</li>
<li>It’s easier to dominate a small market than a large one.</li>
<li>Choose a small group of particular people, concentrated together and served by few or no competition.</li>
<li>It’s a red flag to talk about 1% of a very large market. You’ll have to fight too many competitors to get that 1%.</li>
<li>Once you create and dominate a niche market, gradually expand into related and slightly broader markets. Eg. Amazon wanted to dominate all online retail but started with books.</li>
<li>Don’t disrupt. Avoid competition as much as possible</li>
<li>“You must study the endgame before anything else” - Grandmaster José Raúl Capablanca</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="the-power-law">The Power Law</h2>
<ul>
<li>A small handful of companies radically outperform all others.</li>
<li>The differences between companies dwarf differences in roles within companies.</li>
<li>Before you focus relentlessly on something you’re good at, think hard about whether it will be valuable in the future.</li>
<li>For startups this means you should not necessarily start your own company, even if you are extraordinarily talented. It might be better to join a successful company when it’s growing fast.</li>
<li>You could have 100% equity if you fully fund your own company. If it fails you will have a 100% of nothing. Owning just 0.01% of Google will give you millions.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="secrets">Secrets</h2>
<ul>
<li>There are two kinds of secrets:
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>Secrets about nature - Undiscovered aspects of the physical world.</li>
<li>Secrets about people - Things people don’t know about themselves or things people want to hide from you.</li>
</ol></li>
<li>What secrets is nature not telling you?</li>
<li>What secrets are people not telling you?</li>
<li>You can’t find secrets without looking for them.</li>
<li>The best place to look for secrets is where no one else is looking for them.</li>
<li>A great company is a conspiracy to change the world.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="selling">Selling</h2>
<p>Your company needs to sell more than its product. You must sell your company to employees and investors.</p>
<h2 id="computers-are-a-tool">Computers are a Tool</h2>
<p>“How can computers help humans solve hard problems?”</p>
<h2 id="planning">Planning</h2>
<ul>
<li>Jobs saw that you can change the world through planning; not by listening to focus group feedback or copying others’ success.</li>
<li>Long-term planning is often undervalued in our indefinite short-term world - If you see the future as random why plan?</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="questions-every-business-must-answer">7 Questions Every Business must Answer</h2>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>Can you create breakthrough technology instead of incremental improvements?</li>
<li>Is now the right time to start your particular business?</li>
<li>Are you starting with a big share of a small market?</li>
<li>Do you have the right team?</li>
<li>Do you have a way to create and deliver your product?</li>
<li>Will your market position be defensible 10 to 20 years into the future?</li>
<li>Have you identified a unique opportunity others don’t see?</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="the-future">The Future</h2>
<ul>
<li>Focus on making new things.</li>
<li>Make the future not just different but better.</li>
<li>Think for yourself.</li>
<li>Look at the world with fresh perspective similar to the ancients.</li>
</ul>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sat, 31 Jan 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-01-31-zero-to-one-peter-thiel-notes.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Skdet dependency for RKHunter</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2014-11-23-install-skdet-for-rkhunter-linux.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Here’s how to install the Skdet dependency for RKHunter.</p>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li><p>Download the following files:</p>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li><a href="http://dvgevers.home.xs4all.nl/skdet/skdet-1.0.sha1">skdet-1.0.sha1</a></li>
<li><a href="http://dvgevers.home.xs4all.nl/skdet/skdet-1.0.tar.bz2">skdet-1.0.tar.bz2</a></li>
<li><a href="http://dvgevers.home.xs4all.nl/skdet/skdet-fix-includes.diff">skdet-fix-includes.diff</a></li>
</ol></li>
<li><p>Extract the archive:</p>
<pre class="scrollx"><code>tar -jxf skdet-1.0.tar.bz2</code></pre></li>
<li><p>Copy the <strong>.diff</strong> file into the <strong>skdet-1.0/</strong> directory.</p></li>
<li><p>Update the <strong>skdet-1.0.sha1</strong> file and add an extra space between the sha1 for the diff file and the file name. (otherwise the check won’t run against it.)</p></li>
<li><p>Go into the <strong>skdet-1.0/</strong> directory and run:</p>
<pre class="scrollx"><code>make clean</code></pre>
<p>This will remove any previously compiled files.</p></li>
<li><p>Check the sha1 values of all files from the parent directory of the skdet-1.0 directory:</p>
<pre class="scrollx"><code>sha1sum skdet-1.0.sha1</code></pre></li>
<li><p>Make the skdet library with:</p>
<pre class="scrollx"><code>make</code></pre></li>
<li><p>Verify that the skdet library works with:</p>
<pre class="scrollx"><code>sudo skdet -c</code></pre></li>
<li><p>Copy the <strong>skdet</strong> executable somewhere on your path with root priviledges:</p>
<pre class="scrollx"><code>/usr/bin</code></pre></li>
<li><p>Run a RKHunter scan with:</p>
<pre class="scrollx"><code>sudo rkhunter -c --sk</code></pre>
<p>You should see this in your summary for your scan in the <strong>/var/log/rkhunter.log</strong> file:</p>
<pre class="scrollx"><code>Info: Found the &#39;skdet&#39; command: /usr/bin/skdet
     Running skdet command                         [ OK ]
     Suckit Rookit additional checks               [ OK ]</code></pre>
<p>You should get the following error:</p>
<pre class="scrollx"><code>Warning: The file &#39;/usr/bin/skdet&#39; exists on the system, but it is not present in the &#39;rkhunter.dat&#39; file.</code></pre></li>
<li><p>Update your data file with:</p>
<pre class="scrollx"><code>sudo rkhunter --propupd</code></pre>
<p>And you should see something like:</p>
<pre class="scrollx"><code>[ Rootkit Hunter version 1.4.0 ]
File updated: searched for 168 files, found 138</code></pre>
<p>And you’re done.</p></li>
</ol>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2014 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2014-11-23-install-skdet-for-rkhunter-linux.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Install and configure RKHunter on Linux</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2014-11-23-install-and-configure-rkhunter-linux.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<h2 id="install">Install</h2>
<p>To install rkhunter run:</p>
<pre class="scrollx"><code>sudo apt-get install rkhunter</code></pre>
<p>Choose <strong>no mail server</strong> when prompted.</p>
<h2 id="configure">Configure</h2>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li><p>Check for database updates with:</p>
<pre class="scrollx"><code>sudo rkhunter --update</code></pre></li>
<li><p>Run a full scan with:</p>
<pre class="scrollx"><code>sudo rkhunter -c</code></pre></li>
<li>Add the following to the <strong>rkhunter.conf</strong> file to ignore known issues:
<ol style="list-style-type: lower-alpha">
<li>ALLOWDEVFILE=“/dev/.udev/rules.d/root.rules”</li>
<li>ALLOWHIDDENDIR=“/dev/.udev”</li>
<li>ALLOWHIDDENFILE=“/dev/.blkid.tab”</li>
<li>ALLOWHIDDENFILE=“/dev/.blkid.tab.old”</li>
<li>ALLOWHIDDENFILE=“/dev/.initramfs”</li>
<li>SCRIPTWHITELIST=“/usr/bin/unhide.rb”</li>
</ol></li>
<li><p>Check the RKHunter configuration updates just made with:</p>
<pre class="scrollx"><code>sudo rkhunter -C</code></pre></li>
<li>Remove ssh configuration issues by disabling root login and password login by editing <strong>/etc/ssh/sshd_config</strong> and updating the following:
<ol style="list-style-type: lower-alpha">
<li>PermitRootLogin no</li>
<li>PasswordAuthentication</li>
</ol></li>
<li><p>Run a full scan to ensure there are no other errors:</p>
<pre class="scrollx"><code>sudo rkhunter -c</code></pre></li>
<li><p>Once there are no errors, update the RKHunter data file:</p>
<pre class="scrollx"><code>sudo rkhunter --propupd</code></pre></li>
</ol>
<h2 id="maintain">Maintain</h2>
<p>If your system is infected with rootkits or if you install any new packages you could get RKHunter errors. You can fix them as follows:</p>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li><p>Rescan the system</p>
<pre class="scrollx"><code>sudo rkhunter -c</code></pre></li>
<li>Fix any errors</li>
<li><p>Update the data file</p>
<pre class="scrollx"><code>sudo rkhunter --propupd</code></pre></li>
</ol>
<h2 id="other-useful-commands">Other useful commands</h2>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li><p>To check for a new version:</p>
<pre class="scrollx"><code>sudo rkhunter --versioncheck</code></pre></li>
<li><p>To run without manual intervention, remove colour codes and only output warnings:</p>
<pre class="scrollx"><code>sudo rkhunter --cronjob --rwo</code></pre></li>
</ol>
<h2 id="additional-dependencies">Additional Dependencies</h2>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li><p>Install Unhide to find hidden processes and ports:</p>
<pre class="scrollx"><code>sudo apt-get install unhide</code></pre></li>
<li><p><a href="http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2014-11-23-install-skdet-for-rkhunter-linux.html">Install Skdet for additional Suckit Rookit checks</a>.</p></li>
<li><p>Tripwire - It is recommended that Tripwire be installed as a standalone package and not run through RKHUnter.</p></li>
</ol>
<h2 id="useful-links">Useful links</h2>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li><a href="http://sourceforge.net/p/rkhunter/wiki/browse_pages/">RKHunter Wiki</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.digitalocean.com/community/tutorials/how-to-use-rkhunter-to-guard-against-rootkits-on-an-ubuntu-vps">How to use RKHunter to Guard Against Rootkits on an Ubuntu Vps</a></li>
<li><a href="https://help.ubuntu.com/community/RKhunter">Ubuntu RKHunter</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.faqforge.com/linux/reconfigure-rkhunter-to-avoid-false-positive-warninngs-on-debian-5-0/">Reconfigure RKHunter to Avoid False Positive Warninngs on Debian 5.0</a></li>
</ol>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2014 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2014-11-23-install-and-configure-rkhunter-linux.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Shipping vs Quality</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2014-10-23-shipping-vs-quality.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Say you had two applications. One that is of high “quality”, but doesn’t ship. The other is of low “quality”, but ships. Which application do you reckon would bring you the most business benefit?</p>
<p>If you were funding a startup your choice would be very clear. You’d want something to bring in business value ASAP. The low quality application that shipped would be the winner.</p>
<p>We behave somewhat differently in an “enterprise” environment. We hardly run any “experiments” or <a href="http://theleanstartup.com/principles">MVPs</a>. Everything must have a hundred features even for a 0.0.1 release. We agonize about the “quality” of our software. We often prefer not to release something unless it is of “acceptable quality”. Sometimes these quality exercises take months. Often we are just shining a useless artifact that may never ship. This obviously doesn’t add any business value. So why do we do it?</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2014 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2014-10-23-shipping-vs-quality.html</guid>
</item>

    </channel> 
</rss>
