<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>BabylonCandle</title>
        <link>http://blog.ssanj.net</link>
        <description><![CDATA[The blog of Sanjiv Sahayam]]></description>
        <atom:link href="http://blog.ssanj.net/feed.xml" rel="self"
                   type="application/rss+xml" />
        <lastBuildDate>Sun, 26 Apr 2015 00:00:00 UT</lastBuildDate>
        <item>
    <title>Get Away from the Computer</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-04-26-get-away-from-the-computer.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>For most programmers, programming is usually our day job as well as our hobby. But “working” all the time dulls our intuition.</p>
<p>We think we get a “lot done” but in reality we might be efficiently working on something that we shouldn’t work on at all.</p>
<p>Take time to get away from the computer. Spend time with nature. Catch up with friends or family. Do something fun! Get some exercise!</p>
<p>You will find that rather than hindering your “progress”, it leads to insights and questions you would never have had otherwise. “Obvious” answers will pop into your head. Your brain just needs the time to find the connections between all the information you feed it on a daily basis.</p>
<p>Most of all it will help you balance your life.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 26 Apr 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-04-26-get-away-from-the-computer.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Get a Different Perspective</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-04-26-get-a-different-perspective.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://twitter.com/pamelafox">Pamela Fox</a> shared this idea on Twitter a while back:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Do something in a new way each day. Whether it’s eating a different lunch or walking a different way to work or writing with your left hand. Keep doing things that give you a new perspective.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Doing something differently to the way you “always do it” has the side effect of waking up your brain. You are forced to “tune in” as opposed to “tuning out”. You notice new things. You enjoy your experience more. You learn. :)</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 26 Apr 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-04-26-get-a-different-perspective.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Show Committers on a Git Repository</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-04-24-show-committers-on-a-git-repository.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>How is git so awesome? Today I was wondering how I’d go about listing all the unique committers to a git repository. As usual there was some git fu that I had yet to learn:</p>
<pre class="command"><code>git shortlog -ns</code></pre>
<p>Running this on the Scala <a href="https://github.com/puffnfresh/wartremover">Wartremover repository</a> returns the following:</p>
<pre class="terminal"><code>   126  Brian McKenna
    15  Michal Rus
     9  Michał Rus
     7  Rob Norris
     7  George Leontiev
     6  Nikolay Stanchenko
     6  Pedro Furlanetto
     3  Maxwell Swadling
     3  Jonathan Ferguson
     2  xuwei-k
     2  James Earl Douglas
     2  Dale Wijnand
     2  Cody Allen
     2  Zach Weatherby
     1  Leif Warner
     1  Peter Hausel
     1  Lars Hupel
     1  Jason Zaugg
     1  ChrisNeveu
     1  Vladimir Kostyukov</code></pre>
<p>If you want to further order by email use:</p>
<pre class="command"><code>git shortlog -nes</code></pre>
<p>enjoy! :)</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Fri, 24 Apr 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-04-24-show-committers-on-a-git-repository.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Do Something Nice</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-04-22-do-something-nice.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Try to do something nice for a complete stranger at least once a week. I’m not sure where I came across this idea but it’s a good one. If you find it hard to do things for strangers, try this on your work colleagues, friends or family.</p>
<p>This practice helps you to stop focussing on yourself all the time. It enables you think about someone else at least once a week. It also makes you feel great. :)</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 22 Apr 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-04-22-do-something-nice.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Disconnect</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-04-22-disconnect.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>People are too “connected” these days. Connected with their devices that is. The more “connected” we are with our devices, the less connected we seem to be with real people and the world around us.</p>
<p>Take time everyday to disconnect. Put away your mobile phone. Unplug those headphones. This practice will help you reconnect with the physical world and people around you. It will make your life a lot richer than when staring at a screen all day.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 22 Apr 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-04-22-disconnect.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Banishing Multitasking from our Repertoire</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-04-22-banishing-multitasking-from-our-repertoire.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Ideas from the chapter “Banishing Multitasking from our Repertoire” from the book <a href="http://99u.com/book/manage-your-day-to-day-2">Manage Your Day-To-Day</a> by Christian Jarrett.</p>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>Switching tasks sends us down a rabbit hole, pulling our attention away from our priority work for much longer than we anticipate.</li>
<li>A good stopping point on a project helps to free your mind from nagging questions and gives you mental closure.</li>
</ol>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 22 Apr 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-04-22-banishing-multitasking-from-our-repertoire.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Ignore Everybody</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-04-20-ignore-everybody.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Ideas from the chapter “Ignore Everybody” from the book <a href="http://gapingvoid.com/ie">Ignore Everybody And 39 other Keys to Creativity</a> by Hugh MacLeod.</p>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>The more original your idea is, the less good advice other people will be able to give you.</li>
<li>You don’t know if your idea is any good the moment it is created. Neither does anyone else.</li>
<li>A big idea will change you.</li>
<li>Good ideas alter the power balance in relationships. That is why good ideas are initially resisted.</li>
<li>Good ideas come with a heavy burden, which is why so few people execute them.</li>
</ol>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Mon, 20 Apr 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-04-20-ignore-everybody.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Honing your Creative Practice</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-04-20-honing-your-creative-practice.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Ideas from the chapter “Honing your creative practice” from the book <a href="http://99u.com/book/manage-your-day-to-day-2">Manage Your Day-To-Day</a> with Seth Godin.</p>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>Lots and lots of people are creative when they feel like it, but you are only going to become a professional if you do it when you don’t feel like it. And that emotional waiver is why this is your work and not your hobby.</li>
<li>Practice is a big part of being creative.</li>
<li>Being creative means you have to sell your ideas. Selling is part of it because if you don’t sell it, there is no art.</li>
<li>It’s much easier to whine and sabotage yourself and blame the client, the system, and the economy. This is what you hide from - the noise in your head that says you are not good enough, that says it is not perfect, that says it could have been better.</li>
</ol>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Mon, 20 Apr 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-04-20-honing-your-creative-practice.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Harnessing the Power of Frequency</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-04-20-harnessing-the-power-of-frequency.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Ideas from the chapter “Harnessing the power of frequency” from the book <a href="http://99u.com/book/manage-your-day-to-day-2">Manage Your Day-To-Day</a> by Gretchen Rubin.</p>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>We tend to overestimate what we can do in a short period, and underestimate what we can do over a long period, provided we work slowly and consistently.</li>
<li>What we do everyday matters more than what we do once in a while.</li>
</ol>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Mon, 20 Apr 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-04-20-harnessing-the-power-of-frequency.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Why Your Company should have a Creed</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-04-19-why-your-company-should-have-a-creed.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://automattic.com">Automattic</a> is a company founded by Matt Mullenweg. He also developed <a href="https://en-au.wordpress.org">Wordpress</a> ten years ago. He talks of the notion of a “company creed” which codifies the culture and values of a company. Here’s the Autommatic creed (as of September 19th, 2011):</p>
<div class="quote">
I will never stop learning. I won’t just work on things that are assigned to me. I know there’s no such thing as a status quo. I will build our business sustainably through passionate and loyal customers. I will never pass up an opportunity to help out a colleague, and I’ll remember the days before I knew everything. I am more motivated by impact than money, and I know that Open Source is one of the most powerful ideas of our generation. I will communicate as much as possible, because it’s the oxygen of a distributed company. I am in a marathon, not a sprint, and no matter how far away the goal is, the only way to get there is by putting one foot in front of another every day. Given time, there is no problem that’s insurmountable.
</div>
<p>Matt further says that:</p>
<div class="quote">
If you’re building a startup or any sort of organisation, take a few moments to reflect on the qualities that the people you most enjoy working with embody and the user experience of new people joining your organisation, from the offer letter to their first day.
</div>
<p>Finally Matt has an innovative way of introducing the company’s creed to new hires:</p>
<div class="quote">
Finally, as a hack to introduce new folks to our culture, we put a beta “Automattic Creed”, basically a statement of things important to us, written in the first person. We put it after the legal gobbledygook and before the signature area; if you chose to accept the offer, you’d sign your name next to the values before starting work. This seemed like a powerful statement and might affect people’s perceptions in the same way that putting signatures at the top of forms increases honesty.
</div>
<p><a href="http://ma.tt/2011/09/automattic-creed">Read the full article on Matt’s blog</a>.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-04-19-why-your-company-should-have-a-creed.html</guid>
</item>

    </channel> 
</rss>
