<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
    xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
    <channel>
        <title>BabylonCandle</title>
        <link>http://blog.ssanj.net</link>
        <description><![CDATA[The blog of Sanjiv Sahayam]]></description>
        <atom:link href="http://blog.ssanj.net/feed.xml" rel="self"
                   type="application/rss+xml" />
        <lastBuildDate>Sun, 05 Jul 2015 00:00:00 UT</lastBuildDate>
        <item>
    <title>What Happens when you don&apos;t Care</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-07-05-what-happens-when-you-don%27t-care.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>In <a href="http://www.jamesaltucher.com/2015/06/what-happens-when-you-dont-care">his post on not caring</a>, James Altucher shares some keen insights.</p>
<p>Only say “yes” to opportunities you love:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>I say “No” to any opportunities that will take me from what I love doing.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Do what you love to have more opportunities:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>I have NEVER seen someone who ultimately couldn’t get opportunities that they wanted if they simply stopped caring and started doing the best at what they loved.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Speak less and listen more:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>I like to try and speak less than that. It builds up mental energy to speak less. And forces me to listen more when everyone else has their opinions.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Push the boundaries of what’s possible:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>When I don’t care, it’s much easier to over-promise and over-deliver. That’s what makes you a magnet of opportunity.</p>
</blockquote>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 05 Jul 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-07-05-what-happens-when-you-don%27t-care.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>sanjiv sahayam</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>How to Destroy your Business</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-07-05-how-to-destroy-your-business.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Something I’ve been doing to <a href="http://sanj.ink/posts/2015-04-26-get-a-different-perspective.html">get a different perspective</a> has been to visit different coffee shops during the week.</p>
<p>A few weeks ago I had seen an interesting coffee shop near the train station and thought I’d give it a try. This coffee shop that will go unnamed, broke one of the golden rules of running a business:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Never deliver a sub par product in a highly competitive market.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Given the number of coffee shops per square metre in the Brisbane CBD, a coffee shop can’t afford to serve bad coffee. This is coffee shop suicide. If that wasn’t bad enough, I was hit with the “Five dollar minimum on fpos” statement. This was followed by the “you can pre-purchase your weekly coffee on this card” scam. Um, no thanks.</p>
<p>Five minutes later I dumped their crappy coffee in the bin and headed back to <a href="https://www.facebook.com/coffeeanthology">my usual</a> for an awesome coffee.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 05 Jul 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-07-05-how-to-destroy-your-business.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>sanjiv sahayam</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Your App should Release Endorphins</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-07-02-your-app-should-release-endorphins.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Most current apps are frustrating to use. They constantly crash - an <a href="http://theleanstartup.com/principles">MVP</a> mentality where we are the guinea pigs in an elaborate entrepreneurial experiment.</p>
<p>They are cluttered and chaotic. We are constantly bombarded with decisions we don’t want or need to make. “Would you like to subscribe to this newsletter?” or “App X wants to access your contacts/your friends list/your location”. Hell no! These apps cause stress hormones like Adrenaline and Norepinephrine to be released into our bloodstream. Shitty apps are bad for our health.</p>
<p>I recently read about <a href="http://blog.invisionapp.com/why-empty-states-deserve-more-design-time">why empty states deserve more design time</a>. This made me think about how apps could be different.</p>
<p>What if apps were fun to use? What if they were so enjoyable that it resulted in the release of Endorphins into our bloodstream? What if the guiding principle of apps design was to never stress the user? How would we need to change our current design mindset to achieve that?</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Thu, 02 Jul 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-07-02-your-app-should-release-endorphins.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>sanjiv sahayam</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>More Please</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-06-21-more-please.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>I had seen him selling the <a href="http://www.thebigissue.org.au">Big Issue</a> by Central station. He had a beard and wore a singlet of some description. He was in shorts. I had never purchased the Big Issue myself but always thought I should buy one - someday.</p>
<p>Somewhere in the back of my mind I recalled that the Big Issue was sold by homeless and disadvantaged people. It had never occurred to me that he might have been cold in this weather and didn’t have a warm jacket. I guess I was too busy worrying about my own “big” issues; being self-centred as most of us are these days.</p>
<p>Recently while walking out of the train station I noticed a lady chatting with the Big Issue-selling bearded gentleman. He had a nice warm, long coat on. He had a big smile on his face. She was talking to him about how she had thought about him and brought him the coat. She was all enthusiastic. Two lives changed for the better.</p>
<p>This scene totally blew me away. When you help someone you not only help that person, but you also enrich your own life. Your benevolence also affects all who witness it. I want to see more of this in the world. Please, can I see some more?</p>
<p>I have since donated a swag through <a href="http://swags.org.au">Swags for homeless</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Swags for Homeless is a not-for-profit charity working to provide emergency relief Backpack Beds to every homeless person turned away from shelter.</p>
</blockquote>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jun 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-06-21-more-please.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>sanjiv sahayam</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Death by Coffee</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-06-18-death-by-coffee.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>We’ve all heard of people who have multiple shots of coffee. Two, three or even four shots in one go. This anecdote shares a somewhat more startling trend.</p>
<iframe width="100%" height="100" scrolling="no" frameborder="no" src="https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/210888203&amp;auto_play=false&amp;hide_related=false&amp;show_artwork=false&amp;show_comments=true&amp;show_user=false&amp;show_reposts=false&amp;visual=false">
</iframe>
<p>My wife, since listening to this, sent me through <a href="http://www.caffeineinformer.com/coffee-overdose-14-shots-of-espresso">this article</a> which has an even more bizarre tale. I love how <a href="http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/england/wear/6944026.stm">Jasmine’s mum says this about her</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>I have always stressed to my children the importance of moderation but Jasmine got caught out on this occasion.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>But the comments section is a must read. Here’s a taste:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>A fellow barista promised me she could drink more shots. I told her she was foolish. 27 shots were pulled for both of us as we gulped them shot for shot. She got woozy at 24 so I downed her last 3 making my count an even 30. They rushed her to the ER and I bolted to the bathroom. After shooting nasty acid out my mouth and meatloaf milkshake out my ass, I flew home on my Rockhopper, took a warm bath,. My coworker was sick for at least 2 days and I got the blame.</p>
</blockquote>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Thu, 18 Jun 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-06-18-death-by-coffee.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>sanjiv sahayam</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>How Many Coffees should you have a Day?</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-06-17-how-many-coffees-should-you-have-a-day.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>My coffee consumption has doubled. Where will it end?</p>
<iframe width="100%" height="100" scrolling="no" frameborder="no" src="https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/210730718&amp;auto_play=false&amp;hide_related=false&amp;show_artwork=false&amp;show_comments=true&amp;show_user=false&amp;show_reposts=false&amp;visual=false">
</iframe>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jun 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-06-17-how-many-coffees-should-you-have-a-day.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>sanjiv sahayam</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Buy the Impossible Cheap</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-06-14-buy-the-impossible-cheap.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.jamesaltucher.com/2015/02/10-things-i-learn-from-richard-branson">Something James Altucher learned from Richard Branson</a> is that:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>When people think a problem is impossible they value it at zero. Successful people buy ideas low (zero) and sell them high.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>What “impossible” ideas do you have?</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 14 Jun 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-06-14-buy-the-impossible-cheap.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>sanjiv sahayam</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Where&apos;s your Git HEAD at?</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-06-07-where%27s-your-git-HEAD-at.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Sometimes you want to know which branch and commit HEAD points to. With this magical Git incantation you can:</p>
<pre class="command"><code>git log --oneline --decorate --graph --all</code></pre>
<div class="figure">
<img src="/images/git_head_branch.jpg" alt="showing git branches with HEAD" />
<p class="caption">showing git branches with HEAD</p>
</div>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 07 Jun 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-06-07-where%27s-your-git-HEAD-at.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>sanjiv sahayam</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Obstacle Subtraction</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-06-07-obstacle-subtraction.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>James Altucher in his <a href="http://www.jamesaltucher.com/2015/02/10-things-i-learn-from-richard-branson">Things I learned from Richard Branson</a> blog post, talks about what he calls “idea subtraction”. He removes any perceived obstacles he may encounter when pursuing an idea. He then finds that he is left with more possibilities:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>I call this IDEA SUBTRACTION. Subtract the perceived obstacles to an idea and (BAM!) you find that many more ideas are born from that.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I prefer to call this “obstacle subtraction”.</p>
<p>The next time you are faced with some obstacles, think about what you could do if these obstacles didn’t exist. What would be your next move?</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 07 Jun 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-06-07-obstacle-subtraction.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>sanjiv sahayam</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Fear at the Dinner Table</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-06-07-fear-at-the-dinner-table.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>“I used to drink a carton of beer and a bottle of whisky every night” said the man at the other table to his teenage son. He was joined by his wife, and three young teenage daughters.</p>
<p>My wife and I looked at each other in disapproval. This was hardly the story any parent should be recounting to his teenage children.</p>
<p>A few minutes later his son received a text message and was looking at his phone. “What have I said about phones at the dinner table?” he boomed. This drama was starting to get quite uncomfortable. He then followed that with an exclamation of: “Give me your phone. NOW!”. Everyone else at his table went quiet. His wife said nothing. His daughters didn’t know what to do. His son handed over his phone. The fear at their table was palpable.</p>
<p>My wife and I wondered what would happen to the kid once he got home.</p>
<p>I really felt for the kid. I felt like saying “Don’t worry kid. Your life is going to get better. You will leave your parents one day. You can have your own life. You can do anything you want to do. Hang in there in the meantime.”</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 07 Jun 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-06-07-fear-at-the-dinner-table.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>sanjiv sahayam</dc:creator>
</item>

    </channel>
</rss>
