<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>BabylonCandle</title>
        <link>http://blog.ssanj.net</link>
        <description><![CDATA[The blog of Sanjiv Sahayam]]></description>
        <atom:link href="http://blog.ssanj.net/feed.xml" rel="self"
                   type="application/rss+xml" />
        <lastBuildDate>Wed, 18 Mar 2015 00:00:00 UT</lastBuildDate>
        <item>
    <title>Sanity in Numbers</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-03-18-sanity-in-numbers.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>If you’ve been tasked with doing something stressful or potentially disastrous, ask to be part of team - even if it means working with only one additional person. Some of the reasons why you might want to do this are:</p>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>It shares the stress amongst the team. No one person carries the full load.</li>
<li>Pushing back on unreasonable requests is much easier when you have more voices of “reason”.</li>
<li>You get second/third/fourth opinions about what needs to be done, when it needs to be done by and how it should be done.</li>
<li>Your team becomes the sanity check in insane situations.</li>
</ol>
<p>Some scenarios where having a team is useful:</p>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>Unreasonable deadlines.</li>
<li>Massive architectural changes.</li>
<li>“Quick” fixes that could potentially destroy your production system.</li>
<li>“Must have” features then need to be completed ASAP.</li>
<li>Migration/deletion of production data.</li>
</ol>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 18 Mar 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-03-18-sanity-in-numbers.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Slowing Down</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-03-15-slowing-down.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>In her book <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Inner-Simplicity-Regain-Peace-Nourish/dp/078688097X">Inner Simplicity</a>, Elaine St. James, says that “Hurrying becomes a habit”. Hurrying seems to have its own momentum.</p>
<p>She also posits that being around busy people makes it that much harder for you to slow down. She advises that we should start to think about how we can slow down our routine. This might include things like waking up a little earlier so you can really enjoy your breakfast instead of rushing out the door, focusing on a single task when you have ten other tasks pending, or leisurely walking to work instead of speed-walking. She also recommends avoiding fast-paced restaurants for lunch and to instead head to a park or a quite place and spend time in nature.</p>
<p>One thing I’ve been trialling has been to stop constantly learning new technologies on the train ride to and from work. I’ve started just listening to some music or simply staring out the window for at least one of the daily commutes. This has really freed up my mind to ponder things more deeply. It has also stopped me rushing as much as I used to.</p>
<p>Elaine observes that:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Over and over I found that rushing through a project meant getting it wrong and losing time in the end by having to do it over either partially or completely. Take your time to do it right in the first place and enjoy the process as you go along.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is something I’ve found to be true. Rushing a project never gives you any satisfaction. The results are always less than optimal. The best part about slowing down is the enjoyment you get by being more present in what you are doing. You notice more things around you. You do better work. You react less. You enjoy life more. :)</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 15 Mar 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-03-15-slowing-down.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Don't Wait for Moods</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-03-15-dont-wait-for-moods.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p class="quote">
I don’t wait for moods. You accomplish nothing if you do that. Your mind must know it has to get down to work. <span class="attribution">Pearl S. Buck</span>
</p>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 15 Mar 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-03-15-dont-wait-for-moods.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Do your Best Work Everyday</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-03-15-do-your-best-work-everyday.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Do your best work every day. No excuses. No exceptions.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 15 Mar 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-03-15-do-your-best-work-everyday.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Creating an Effective Routine</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-03-15-creating-an-effective-routine.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>In the last article, <a href="2015-03-14-it-takes-time-to-build-something-great.html">It Takes Time to Build Something Great</a> we thought about the idea of spending a long period of time to create something truly great.</p>
<p>So where do we find time to get all this work done? The book <a href="http://99u.com/book/manage-your-day-to-day-2">Manage your day-to-day</a> recommends routines as a way of getting into a regular rhythm of creating things. Routines train your mind to get into “creative” mode. They also help you plan your time more predictably.</p>
<p>Set up a weekly schedule of when you will work and for how long. This will ensure you always have time set aside to do your (great) work.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 15 Mar 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-03-15-creating-an-effective-routine.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>It Takes Time to Build Something Great</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-03-14-it-takes-time-to-build-something-great.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>The book <a href="http://99u.com/book/manage-your-day-to-day-2">Manage your day-to-day</a> says that:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Truly creative achievements require hundreds, if not thousands of hours of work.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Doing great work means spending thousands of hours on your craft. Sounds tiresome. But in reality there is no way around it. Working consistently and regularly over a long period of time leads to huge payoffs. This idea nudges us to focus on what can be achieved in the long-term over “quick” wins.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sat, 14 Mar 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-03-14-it-takes-time-to-build-something-great.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Writing Code is Easy</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-03-11-writing-code-is-easy.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Writing code is easy. After a few years of practice, a programmer can solve any given problem in a variety of ways. It’s almost automatic.</p>
<p>Thinking is not so easy. Thinking takes effort. Think is not automatic. Thinking forces us to evaluate our assumptions. Sometimes we don’t want our assumptions questioned. We want to just start “work”. “The sooner I start coding the sooner I can get this feature/bug finished” - or so we tell ourselves. In reality we don’t want to think about all things we want to ignore. We just want to code. We want to get “something” finished.</p>
<p>Unfortunately if we don’t think about the problem we are about to solve, we’ll never completely solve it. There’ll always be “holes” in our logic.</p>
<p>I’ve been trying to spend more time thinking about a problem before diving into code the solution. The results have been really great. I understand the problem more and ask more of the “right” questions. I spend time thinking of the different implementation options and their pros and cons. The time spent thinking actually speeds up the coding process. Since I know exactly what has to be done, all that remains is for me to code the solution. Simple. :)</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 11 Mar 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-03-11-writing-code-is-easy.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Excellence is a Habit</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-03-11-excellence-is-a-habit.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p class="quote">
We are what we repeatedly do. Excellence, then, is not an act, but a habit.<span class="attribution">Artistole</span>
</p>
]]></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 11 Mar 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-03-11-excellence-is-a-habit.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Surround yourself with Smart People</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-03-08-surround-yourself-with-smart-people.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>In <a href="http://paulgraham.com/ecw.html">How to Be an Expert in a Changing World</a>, Paul Graham states:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Surround yourself with the sort of people new ideas come from. If you want to notice quickly when your beliefs become obsolete, you can’t do better than to be friends with the people whose discoveries will make them so.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Make it a point to befriend people smarter than yourself. Challenge your thinking. Do things differently. Follow a different crowd. Pay it forward by passing on your learning to someone else.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 08 Mar 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-03-08-surround-yourself-with-smart-people.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Time Poor. Priority Rich</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-02-22-time-poor-priority-rich.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<h1 id="i-want-all-the-things">I want all the things</h1>
<p>As developers we have many projects on the go. Many new technologies we want to try out. Many new ways of working we want to trial. Many new concepts we need to understand. All these activities compete for our limited free time. Most likely you’ll only get a few hours of continuous time to spend across all these activities per week. So how can we focus on all these interests with limited time?</p>
<h1 id="three-please">Three please</h1>
<p>The first thing to realise is that you can’t focus on everything at the same time. You’ll never get anything done if you do. You need to chose. I’ve found that prioritising the work I do to be the simplest tool to ensure I get the most important work done. I write down the top three activities I’d like to either complete or focus on in my limited time. The way I choose my most important task is by asking the question: “Would I feel good about the time I spent working on this task if I got nothing else done?”. Then I repeat the same question for the second and third items. I do not list more than 3 items. I only focus on this small list and assume I’ll probably only get through first task. I may not even finish the first task. I have realised that I have to be okay with leaving work unfinished - if I run out of time. I turn off all social media. Then I get to work.</p>
<h1 id="enforce-the-gap">Enforce the gap</h1>
<p>I take a break when I finish a task on the list. It could be small as a minute to walk around or it could be a few minutes to grab a coffee etc or it could be longer. This break marks the end of a task and prevents me from jumping from task to task mindlessly. It helps me feel like I accomplished something. It also resets my brain to make it ready for the next task. This is helpful if my three tasks vary greatly in their implementation. Eg. Maybe I am moving from some backend code to frontend design and then onto installing some infrastructure software.</p>
<h1 id="same-time-next-week">Same time next week</h1>
<p>If I run out of time to finish even the first task, I can rest assured that I spent my time wisely focusing on the most important tasks at hand at the time. As I am okay with leaving the task unfinished for now, I know that I’ll get back to it next week - if it is still one of my top three tasks. I also try to wind down any tasks I might be doing ten to fifteen minutes prior to running out of all my alloted time. This helps me to stop when I need to without working overtime or rushing to get something done which obviously needs more time. Some things take time. You can’t complete everything in a day or a week or even a month.</p>
<h1 id="its-all-equal">It’s all equal</h1>
<p>What if I have tasks that are about equal in priority? I still choose only three. Then I split my time into three parts plus time for two breaks. I wind down each part ten to fifteen minutes prior to the end of the its alloted time. I then take a break as before. I then start the following task. This allows me to make reasonable progress across multiple tasks.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 22 Feb 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-02-22-time-poor-priority-rich.html</guid>
</item>

    </channel> 
</rss>
