<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>BabylonCandle</title>
        <link>http://blog.ssanj.net</link>
        <description><![CDATA[The blog of Sanjiv Sahayam]]></description>
        <atom:link href="http://blog.ssanj.net/feed.xml" rel="self"
                   type="application/rss+xml" />
        <lastBuildDate>Wed, 22 Apr 2015 00:00:00 UT</lastBuildDate>
        <item>
    <title>Do something Nice</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-04-22-do-something-nice.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Try to do something nice for a complete stranger at least once a week. I’m not sure where I came across this idea but it’s a good one. If you find it hard to do things for strangers, try this on your friends or family.</p>
<p>This helps you to stop focussing on yourself all the time and think about someone else. It also makes you feel great. :)</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 22 Apr 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-04-22-do-something-nice.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Disconnect</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-04-22-disconnect.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>People are too “connected” these days. Connected with their devices that is. The more “connected” we are with our devices the less connected we seem to be with real people and the world around us.</p>
<p>Take time everyday to disconnect. Put away your mobile phone. Unplug those headphones. This practice will help you reconnect with the physical world and people around you. It will make your life a lot richer than when staring at a screen all day.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 22 Apr 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-04-22-disconnect.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Banishing Multitasking from our Repertoire</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-04-22-banishing-multitasking-from-our-repertoire.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Ideas from the chapter “Banishing Multitasking from our Repertoire” from the book <a href="http://99u.com/book/manage-your-day-to-day-2">Manage Your Day-To-Day</a> by Christian Jarrett.</p>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>Switching tasks sends us down a rabbit hole, pulling our attention away from our priority work for much longer than we anticipate.</li>
<li>It’s best to find a good stopping point on a project - one that frees your mind from nagging questions, before moving onto another task. That way you’ll find it easier to achieve mental closure and apply all your energy to the next challenge.</li>
</ol>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 22 Apr 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-04-22-banishing-multitasking-from-our-repertoire.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Ignore Everybody</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-04-20-ignore-everybody.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Ideas from the chapter “Ignore Everybody” from the book <a href="http://gapingvoid.com/ie">Ignore Everybody And 39 other Keys to Creativity</a> by Hugh MacLeod.</p>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>The more original your idea is, the less good advice other people will be able to give you.</li>
<li>You don’t know if your idea is any good the moment it is created. Neither does anyone else.</li>
<li>A big idea will change you.</li>
<li>Good ideas alter the power balance in relationships. That is why good ideas are initially resisted.</li>
<li>Good ideas come with a heavy burden, which is why so few people execute them.</li>
</ol>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Mon, 20 Apr 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-04-20-ignore-everybody.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Honing your Creative Practice</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-04-20-honing-your-creative-practice.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Ideas from the chapter “Honing your creative practice” from the book <a href="http://99u.com/book/manage-your-day-to-day-2">Manage Your Day-To-Day</a> with Seth Godin.</p>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>Lots and lots of people are creative when they feel like it, but you are only going to become a professional if you do it when you don’t feel like it. And that emotional waiver is why this is your work and not your hobby.</li>
<li>Practice is a big part of being creative.</li>
<li>Being creative means you have to sell your ideas. Selling is part of it because if you don’t sell it, there is no art.</li>
<li>It’s much easier to whine and sabotage yourself and blame the client, the system, and the economy. This is what you hide from - the noise in your head that says you are not good enough, that says it is not perfect, that says it could have been better.</li>
</ol>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Mon, 20 Apr 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-04-20-honing-your-creative-practice.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Harnessing the Power of Frequency</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-04-20-harnessing-the-power-of-frequency.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Ideas from the chapter “Harnessing the power of frequency” from the book <a href="http://99u.com/book/manage-your-day-to-day-2">Manage Your Day-To-Day</a> by Gretchen Rubin.</p>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>We tend to overestimate what we can do in a short period, and underestimate what we can do over a long period, provided we work slowly and consistently.</li>
<li>What we do everyday matters more than what we do once in a while.</li>
</ol>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Mon, 20 Apr 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-04-20-harnessing-the-power-of-frequency.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Why Your Company should have a Creed</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-04-19-why-your-company-should-have-a-creed.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://automattic.com">Automattic</a> is a company founded by Matt Mullenweg. He also developed <a href="https://en-au.wordpress.org">Wordpress</a> ten years ago. He talks of the notion of a “company creed” which codifies the culture and values of a company. Here’s the Autommatic creed (as of September 19th, 2011):</p>
<div class="quote">
I will never stop learning. I won’t just work on things that are assigned to me. I know there’s no such thing as a status quo. I will build our business sustainably through passionate and loyal customers. I will never pass up an opportunity to help out a colleague, and I’ll remember the days before I knew everything. I am more motivated by impact than money, and I know that Open Source is one of the most powerful ideas of our generation. I will communicate as much as possible, because it’s the oxygen of a distributed company. I am in a marathon, not a sprint, and no matter how far away the goal is, the only way to get there is by putting one foot in front of another every day. Given time, there is no problem that’s insurmountable.
</div>
<p>Matt further says that:</p>
<div class="quote">
If you’re building a startup or any sort of organisation, take a few moments to reflect on the qualities that the people you most enjoy working with embody and the user experience of new people joining your organisation, from the offer letter to their first day.
</div>
<p>Finally Matt has an innovative way of introducing the company’s creed to new hires:</p>
<div class="quote">
Finally, as a hack to introduce new folks to our culture, we put a beta “Automattic Creed”, basically a statement of things important to us, written in the first person. We put it after the legal gobbledygook and before the signature area; if you chose to accept the offer, you’d sign your name next to the values before starting work. This seemed like a powerful statement and might affect people’s perceptions in the same way that putting signatures at the top of forms increases honesty.
</div>
<p><a href="http://ma.tt/2011/09/automattic-creed">Read the full article on Matt’s blog</a>.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-04-19-why-your-company-should-have-a-creed.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>How to run a Company with (almost) no Rules</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-04-12-how-to-run-a-company-with-almost-no-rules.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Some interesting ideas from Ricardo Semler’s Ted Talk: <a href="http://www.ted.com/talks/ricardo_semler_radical_wisdom_for_a_company_a_school_a_life">How to run a company with (almost) no rules</a>:</p>
<div class="quote">
What if your job didn’t control your life?
</div>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>Start working through your bucket list now. Don’t wait until you are in dire straights to do so.</li>
</ol>
<div class="quote">
Instead of going mountain climbing when you’re 82, why don’t you do it next week?
</div>
<ol start="2" style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>Employees are given freedom over what they ware, when they work and how they behave.</li>
<li>Employees can buy back one day of the week for 10% of their salary.</li>
<li>Employees are contracted for a piece of work and given autonomy.</li>
<li>All leaders in the company must be interviewed and approved by their future subordinates. Every 6 months everyone gets anonymously reviewed as a leader. If existing leaders are graded poorly they are replaced.</li>
<li>People are allowed to set their own salaries given three pieces of information:</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>How much money people make inside the company.</li>
<li>The market rate for a similar position in a similar company.</li>
<li>Whether the company can afford to give them the salary they want.</li>
</ul>
<div class="quote">
How do we design, how do we organise, for more wisdom?
</div>
<ol start="7" style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>If an employee finishes all their work early they get to take the rest of the week off.</li>
</ol>
<div class="quote">
We said things like, we don’t want to see your expense report, we don’t want to know how many holidays you’re taking, we don’t want to know where you work.
</div>
<ol start="8" style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>Information is open and democratic. The board has two vacant seats with the equal voting rights. Any two employees from the company can show up and vote on company issues. This keeps the board honest. Eg. Cleaners voting on the direction of the company.</li>
<li>We know nothing about the important things in life:</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>Love</li>
<li>Death</li>
<li>Our purpose</li>
</ul>
<div class="quote">
If you say “I have to give back”, then you took too much.
</div>
<ol start="10" style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>Free yourself from past achievements. Give yourself the freedom to start something new.</li>
</ol>
<div class="quote">
We’ve all learned how to work from home on Sunday night, but very few of us have learned how to go to the movies on Monday afternoon.
</div>
<ol start="11" style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>Ask yourself: “Why am I doing this?”.</li>
</ol>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 12 Apr 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-04-12-how-to-run-a-company-with-almost-no-rules.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Laying the Groundwork for an Effective Routine</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-04-11-laying-the-groundwork.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Ideas from the chapter “Laying the Groundwork for an Effective Routine” from the book <a href="http://99u.com/book/manage-your-day-to-day-2">Manage Your Day-To-Day</a> by Mark McGuinness.</p>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>To create something truly worthwhile, you need to make room for the work you consider important. This means delaying or not doing the work you consider unimportant.</li>
<li>To create something great you need:
<ul>
<li>Time</li>
<li>Thought</li>
<li>Craft</li>
<li>Persistence</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Do creative work first. Do reactive work second.</li>
<li>Do your creative work when you have the most energy during the day.</li>
<li>Use triggers like using the same tools, listening to the same music or working in the same environment each day to enter your creative zone.</li>
<li>Have a very small daily TODO list. Most things can wait until tomorrow.</li>
</ol>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sat, 11 Apr 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-04-11-laying-the-groundwork.html</guid>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Hire for the Future</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-04-09-hire-for-the-future.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>First of all, hire only the best people for your company. If you can’t find good people, then use your money elsewhere.</p>
<p>Second, hire people who can take your company to where you want it to be in the future not just to sustain it where it is now.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Thu, 09 Apr 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-04-09-hire-for-the-future.html</guid>
</item>

    </channel> 
</rss>
