<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
    xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
    <channel>
        <title>BabylonCandle</title>
        <link>http://blog.ssanj.net</link>
        <description><![CDATA[The blog of Sanjiv Sahayam]]></description>
        <atom:link href="http://blog.ssanj.net/feed.xml" rel="self"
                   type="application/rss+xml" />
        <lastBuildDate>Thu, 28 Jan 2016 00:00:00 UT</lastBuildDate>
        <item>
    <title>2 Devs Podcast Discusses Agile is the New Waterfall</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2016-01-28-2-devs-podcast-discusses-agile-is-the-new-waterfall.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>In this week’s episode we discuss the article <a href="https://medium.com/swlh/agile-is-the-new-waterfall-f7baef5d026d#.gsly4byrx">Agile is the New Waterfall by Ayasin</a>. Have a read of the article before jumping into this week’s episode.</p>
<p>Read the <a href="http://www.agilemanifesto.org/">Agile Manifesto</a> for core Agile principles. <a href="http://www.martinfowler.com/articles/itsNotJustStandingUp.html">It’s Not Just Standing Up: Patterns for Daily Standup Meetings by Jason Yip</a> is a nice primer for better standups in general.</p>
<p>If you liked the episode or just have some feedback please leave a comment here or contact us on twitter <a href="https://twitter.com/@ssanj">@ssanj</a> or <a href="https://twitter.com/@nippysaurus">@nippysaurus</a>.</p>
<iframe class="movie" width="100%" height="450" scrolling="no" frameborder="no" src="https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/244224119&amp;auto_play=false&amp;hide_related=false&amp;show_comments=true&amp;show_user=true&amp;show_reposts=false&amp;visual=true">
</iframe>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Thu, 28 Jan 2016 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2016-01-28-2-devs-podcast-discusses-agile-is-the-new-waterfall.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>sanjiv sahayam</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Play Application Fails to Start with play&period;crypto&period;secret Parameter on Linux with Bash</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2016-01-27-play-application-fails-to-start-with-play-crypto-secret-parameter-on-linux-with-bash.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://playframework.com/documentation/2.4.x/Production">The playframework production documentation</a> states that one of the ways to pass the application secret to your application is through a system variable:</p>
<pre class="terminal scrollx"><code>java -jar target/scala-2.XX/&lt;yourprojectname&gt;-assembly-&lt;version&gt;.jar -Dplay.crypto.secret=abcdefghijk</code></pre>
<p>The recommended way to <a href="https://playframework.com/documentation/2.4.x/ApplicationSecret">generate the application secret</a> is by running:</p>
<pre class="command scrollx"><code>sbt playGenerateSecret</code></pre>
<p>Now if the secret generated contains a backtick like so:</p>
<pre class="terminal scrollx"><code>QCY?tAnfk?aZ?iwrNwnxIlR6CTf:G3gf:90Latabg@5241AB`R5W:1uDFN];Ik@n</code></pre>
<p>You’re in for a rude surprise when you try to start your application in a Bash shell:</p>
<pre class="terminal scrollx"><code>java -jar target/scala-2.XX/&lt;yourprojectname&gt;-assembly-&lt;version&gt;.jar -Dplay.crypto.secret=&quot;QCY?tAnfk?aZ?iwrNwnxIlR6CTf:G3gf:90Latabg@5241AB`R5W:1uDFN];Ik@n&quot;</code></pre>
<p>The result with be a prompt indicating that you need to close the backtick:</p>
<pre class="terminal"><code>&gt;</code></pre>
<p>instead of starting the application. <em>Backticks are used for <a href="http://www.tldp.org/LDP/Bash-Beginners-Guide/html/sect_03_04.html#sect_03_04_04">command expansion</a> in Bash.</em></p>
<p>Now there are a couple of ways to workaround this:</p>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>Escape the backtick:</li>
</ol>
<pre class="terminal scrollx"><code>QCY?tAnfk?aZ?iwrNwnxIlR6CTf:G3gf:90Latabg@5241AB\`R5W:1uDFN];Ik@n</code></pre>
<ol start="2" style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>Replace it with a single quote:</li>
</ol>
<pre class="terminal scrollx"><code>QCY?tAnfk?aZ?iwrNwnxIlR6CTf:G3gf:90Latabg@5241AB&#39;R5W:1uDFN];Ik@n</code></pre>
<ol start="3" style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>Remove the backtick:</li>
</ol>
<pre class="terminal scrollx"><code>QCY?tAnfk?aZ?iwrNwnxIlR6CTf:G3gf:90Latabg@5241ABR5W:1uDFN];Ik@n</code></pre>
<p>One thing to keep in mind with other Shells is that any special characters generated by the secret generator will probably have the same issues as Bash does.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 27 Jan 2016 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2016-01-27-play-application-fails-to-start-with-play-crypto-secret-parameter-on-linux-with-bash.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>sanjiv sahayam</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>How to Install El Capitan on a New SSD</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2016-01-21-how-to-install-el-capitan-on-a-new-ssd.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>Download El Capitan installation from the App store. It might complain that you already have it installed but download it anyway. It will be downloaded to <strong>/Applications</strong> and be named <strong>Install OS X El Capitan.app</strong></li>
<li><a href="https://support.apple.com/en-au/HT201372">Create a bootable image from the El Capitan installer</a> on a USB stick larger than 6GB. In a terminal run:</li>
</ol>
<pre class="terminal scrollx"><code>sudo /Applications/Install\ OS\ X\ El\ Capitan.app/Contents/Resources/createinstallmedia --volume /Volumes/MyVolume --applicationpath /Applications/Install\ OS\ X\ El\ Capitan.app</code></pre>
<p><em>where MyVolume is the name of your USB stick. Change this to match the name of your USB stick.</em></p>
<ol start="3" style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>Physically install SSD into the target laptop.</li>
<li>Insert the El Capitan USB stick into the target laptop and power up. (<em>This might take a while.</em>)</li>
<li>When the menu finally turns up, choose <strong>Disk Utility</strong> and format the SSD as <strong>Mac OS Extended (Journaled)</strong> with a unique name.</li>
<li>Once complete, exit from <strong>Disk Utility</strong> and return the main menu.</li>
<li>Choose to <strong>Install OS X</strong> on the formatted SSD.</li>
<li>Follow the prompts until El Capitan is installed.</li>
</ol>
<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=F82ThP-6jeA">Here’s link to a video on how to physically install the SSD as well as run the software installation</a>.</p>
<p>If you’d rather install Yosemite on the SSD then follow the <a href="http://sanj.ink/posts/2015-07-12-how-to-instal-yosemite-on-a-new-ssd.html">How to Install Yosemite on a New SSD</a> guide.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Thu, 21 Jan 2016 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2016-01-21-how-to-install-el-capitan-on-a-new-ssd.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>sanjiv sahayam</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Scoverage Breaks with java.lang.No Class Def Found Error&colon; scoverage &sol; Invoker&dollar;</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2016-01-14-scoverage-breaks-with-java-lang-NoClassDefFoundError-scoverage-Invoker.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>If you’ve been using <a href="https://github.com/scoverage/sbt-scoverage">Scoverage</a> with <a href="http://www.scala-sbt.org">SBT</a> to get some code coverage on your Scala code, you may come across an error while trying to run a main class on instrumentation turned on:</p>
<div class="sourceCode"><pre class="sourceCode scala scrollx"><code class="sourceCode scala">java.<span class="fu">lang</span>.<span class="fu">NoClassDefFoundError</span>: scoverage/Invoker$</code></pre></div>
<p>This is quite puzzling as the tests run fine. I came across a possible <a href="https://github.com/scoverage/sbt-scoverage/issues/84">Github issue</a> while hunting around for a solution. It sounds like there is a runtime dependency on Scoverage classes.</p>
<p>One way to overcome this issue, is to turn off coverage when running your main class through SBT:</p>
<pre class="terminal scrollx"><code>;clean;coverageOff;run</code></pre>
<p>If you’re running SBT externally you can use:</p>
<pre class="terminal scrollx"><code>sbt clean coverageOff run</code></pre>
<p>When you want your coverage back on for your tests, you can use:</p>
<pre class="terminal scrollx"><code>;clean;coverage;test</code></pre>
<p>Or externally:</p>
<pre class="terminal scrollx"><code>sbt clean coverage test</code></pre>
<p><a href="https://github.com/alexflav23">@alexflav23</a> recommends turning off coverage when publishing or packaging:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>You need to disable coverage with coverageOff before publishing or packaging and everything will be just fine. I’ve ran into this issue myself and that was the quick fix.</p>
</blockquote>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Thu, 14 Jan 2016 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2016-01-14-scoverage-breaks-with-java-lang-NoClassDefFoundError-scoverage-Invoker.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>sanjiv sahayam</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>How to be a High Performer</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2016-01-14-how-to-be-a-high-performer.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>We all want to be the best we can be. We are constantly pushing ourselves to do more. Be more. We can often forget to rest between one challenging task and the next. We still have so much further to go to reach our goal. Resting is for the weak right?</p>
<p>I was recently reading a <a href="https://medium.com">Medium</a> article that came up with a nice analogy for this. I couldn’t find the article again to reference it so I’ll paraphrase:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Even when you’re pushing yourself in the gym, you still stop between sets to take a break. No one turns up and does a hundred sets without any breaks. That would just lead to massive muscle fatigue and serious side effects. You would not get stronger over time. You’d probably tear a muscle or worse.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>We can also apply this principle to our daily lives. Work hard. Then take a breather. You’ll find that just like with your muscles, this practice of resting will make your mind and your motivation grow stronger over time.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Thu, 14 Jan 2016 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2016-01-14-how-to-be-a-high-performer.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>sanjiv sahayam</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Trading Money for Time</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2016-01-08-trading-money-for-time.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://fourhourworkweek.com/2014/07/11/james-altucher">James Altucher in his interview with Tim Ferriss</a> states that:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>People say time is money, time is not money. Time is much more valuable than money, an infinite times more valuable than money</p>
</blockquote>
<p>We can’t make time. So why do we squander time by doing things we hate? Doing things out of obligation? Doing things to keep up appearances?</p>
<p>Most of us work in jobs we detest. We “need the money”. We end up exchanging a lot of time for money. What if we lead simpler, cheaper lives? This would give us more time. Time to live. Time to do the things we love. Time to spend with our loved ones. Time to make a difference.</p>
<p>Given that everyone knows this fact at some cerebral level, why do we continue to waste our most scarce resource?</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Fri, 08 Jan 2016 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2016-01-08-trading-money-for-time.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>sanjiv sahayam</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>The Dip - Seth Godin</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2016-01-03-the-dip-seth-godin.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Ideas from the book <a href="http://www.amazon.com/The-Dip-Little-Teaches-Stick/dp/1591841666">The Dip by Seth Godin</a>.</p>
<div>
<div class="quote">
It’s about being the best in the world
</div>
</div>
<ul>
<li>Winners quit all the time. They just quit the right stuff at the right time.</li>
<li>You can’t try to do everything.</li>
<li>Everyone looks for the best choice, as a result the rewards for being first are enormous.</li>
<li>It’s typical for the number one in an industry to get ten times the benefit of number ten and hundred times the benefit of number hundred.</li>
<li>The best means the best for your customers right now, based on what they believe, what they know, what they can afford and how they want to work.</li>
<li>There are a million micromarkets, but each micromarket still has a <em>best</em>.</li>
</ul>
<div>
<div class="quote">
Only talented people fret about mediocrity
</div>
</div>
<h2 id="the-dip">The Dip</h2>
<div class="figure">
<img src="/images/the_dip.png" alt="" />

</div>
<ul>
<li>The Dip is the slog between starting and mastery.</li>
<li>Scarcity is the secret to value. The Dip causes scarcity.</li>
<li>Quit dead-end jobs as fast as you can. They keep you from doing something worthwhile.</li>
</ul>
<div>
<div class="quote">
What’s the point of sticking it out if you’re not going to get the benefits of being the best in the world?
</div>
</div>
<ul>
<li>In a competitive world, adversity is your ally. The harder it gets, the better chance you have of insulating yourself from the competition.</li>
<li>The reason we are here is to solve hard problems.</li>
</ul>
<div>
<div class="quote">
Real success goes to those who obsess
</div>
</div>
<ul>
<li>If you want to be a superstar, then you need to find a field with a steep Dip - a barrier between those who try and those who succeed.</li>
<li>Don’t quit in the Dip.</li>
<li>There’s no reason to keep investing in something that isn’t going to get better.</li>
<li>If you are going to quit, quit before you start. Reject the system. Don’t play the game if you realise you can’t be the best in the world.</li>
</ul>
<div>
<div class="quote">
Use the Dip as an opportunity to create something so extraordinary that people can’t help but talk about it, recommend it, and, yes, choose it
</div>
</div>
<h2 id="quitting">Quitting</h2>
<ul>
<li>The best time to look for a new job is when you don’t need one. The time to switch jobs is before it feels comfortable.</li>
<li>The problem with coping is that it never leads to exceptional performance.</li>
<li>If the best you can do is cope, then you’re better off quitting.</li>
<li>Quitting is better than coping because quitting frees you up to excel at something else.</li>
<li>Never quit something with great long-term potential just because you can’t deal with the stress of the moment.</li>
<li>The choice to stick with anything without forward progress - is a waste.</li>
<li>You should outline your quitting strategy before the discomfort sets in.</li>
<li>Write down under what circumstances you’re willing to quit and when. Then stick with it.</li>
<li>The opposite of quitting is rededication. The opposite of quitting is an invigorated new strategy designed to break the problem apart.</li>
<li>Persistent people are able to visualise the idea of light at the end of the tunnel when others can’t see it.</li>
</ul>
<div>
<div class="quote">
You’re busy defending the mediocre work your organisation does because it’s the best you can do under the circumstances (it’s not). You don’t want to quit. It’s not fun. It’s not easy. So you haven’t. But you should. You must!
</div>
<div class="quote">
Or, you could just settle for being average.
</div>
</div>
<h2 id="the-market">The Market</h2>
<ul>
<li>Influencing a market is more of a hill than a wall. You can make progress, one step at a time, and as you get higher, it actually gets easier. People in the market talk to each other. They are influenced by each other. So every step of progress you make actually gets amplified.</li>
<li>Choose a market that’s the right size for you.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="questions">Questions</h2>
<ul>
<li>Is my persistence going to pay off in the long run?</li>
<li>Am I engaged with one person or organisation, or do my actions in this situation spill over into the entire marketplace?</li>
<li>If I quit this task, will it increase my ability to get through the Dip on something more important?</li>
<li>If I was going to quit anyway, is there something dramatic I can do instead that will change the game?</li>
<li>Who decides what <em>best</em> is?</li>
<li>Can we make the <em>world</em> smaller?</li>
</ul>
<div>
<div class="quote">
We succeed when we do something remarkable
</div>
</div>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 03 Jan 2016 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2016-01-03-the-dip-seth-godin.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>sanjiv sahayam</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Software Development is all about Improvisation</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2016-01-03-software-development-is-all-about-improvisation.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>When you start using any new technology everything seems so easy. So straightforward. Follow these steps and all will be well, or so we think while reading the shiny new documentation.</p>
<p>Unfortunately reality is never that simple. There are always things that don’t work as described. Bugs. Corner cases. The real world.</p>
<p>I believe this is where real software development comes into play. It’s an improvisation where you have to roll with the punches and make hard calls to get something to work consistently. It’s the band aid that keeps production running. It’s crease on your otherwise perfect shirt.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 03 Jan 2016 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2016-01-03-software-development-is-all-about-improvisation.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>sanjiv sahayam</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Docker Machine Looses Volume Data on Restart</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2016-01-03-docker-machine-looses-volume-data-on-restart.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>I had something interesting happen to me yesterday. I had setup a <a href="https://docs.docker.com">Docker</a> MySQL container which I ran on my OSX laptop using <a href="https://docs.docker.com/machine">Docker Machine</a> (<em>version 0.4.1 (e2c88d6)</em>). I had mapped the MySQL data directory to the host using a volume:</p>
<pre class="terminal scrollx"><code>-v /home/docker/config/mysql/data:/var/lib/mysql</code></pre>
<p>After running the container from the Dockerfile, I created an additional database, a couple of tables and some data. I could see the database files created within my mapped directory on the host under <strong>/home/docker/config/mysql/data</strong>. These changes survived a restart of the Docker image I was running. Everything seemed to be working swimmingly until I had to restart my laptop after a software update.</p>
<p>When I restarted Docker Machine and the Docker image for MySQL, none of my changes were present in the mapped directory! The only databases and tables where those created through the Dockerfile. All other changes had been lost! The only reason I was using volumes was to not have this problem and yet here the problem was!</p>
<p>I inspected the container and didn’t see any issues with the mounts. My friend <a href="http://nippysaurus.com">Michael</a> did some more digging around and found that the file system mounted on root was <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tmpfs">tmpfs</a>. Since files stored in tmpfs are stored in volatile memory, they are wiped on a restart. Running a df on the host revealed the issue more clearly:</p>
<pre class="terminal scrollx"><code>df -h
Filesystem                Size      Used Available Use% Mounted on
tmpfs                     1.8G    115.3M      1.6G   6% /
tmpfs                  1001.4M     64.0K   1001.3M   0% /dev/shm
/dev/sda1                18.2G      2.2G     15.0G  13% /mnt/sda1
cgroup                 1001.4M         0   1001.4M   0% /sys/fs/cgroup
none                    280.3G    113.7G    166.6G  41% /Users
/dev/sda1                18.2G      2.2G     15.0G  13% /mnt/sda1/var/lib/docker/aufs</code></pre>
<p>The only safe place to store files seems to be in the /mnt directory. I had two options going forward:</p>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>Map the MySQL data directory as a volume to a subdirectory under /mnt directory on the host.</li>
<li>Expose the MySQL data directory as a volume without an explicit host map.</li>
</ol>
<p>I chose to go with option 2 as on my laptop as it involved less stuffing around and I knew it would be persisted between restarts.</p>
<p>I updated my Dockerfile and exposed the MySQL data directory as a volume:</p>
<pre class="terminal scrollx"><code>VOLUME  [&quot;/var/lib/mysql&quot;]</code></pre>
<p>That fixed the problem. This seems like an unnecessary complication though. I do realise that Docker Machine is in beta and this might be something they fix in the full release. In the meantime this issue is something to be aware of when running on OSX.</p>
<p>As this seems to be a Docker Machine issue, when deploying to production on a Linux/Unix box you can map a volume to a host directory as per usual without any dramas.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 03 Jan 2016 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2016-01-03-docker-machine-looses-volume-data-on-restart.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>sanjiv sahayam</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>2 Devs Podcast</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-12-27-2-devs-podcast.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>My friend <a href="https://twitter.com/nippysaurus">Michael</a> and I recorded a few episodes of our podcast “2 Devs” a while back. We have yet to release any of the episodes but I thought I’d share one here. Enjoy.</p>
<iframe class="movie" width="100%" height="450" scrolling="no" frameborder="no" src="https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/239284458&amp;auto_play=false&amp;hide_related=false&amp;show_comments=true&amp;show_user=true&amp;show_reposts=false&amp;visual=true">
</iframe>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 27 Dec 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-12-27-2-devs-podcast.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>sanjiv sahayam</dc:creator>
</item>

    </channel>
</rss>
