<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
    xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
    <channel>
        <title>BabylonCandle</title>
        <link>http://blog.ssanj.net</link>
        <description><![CDATA[The blog of Sanjiv Sahayam]]></description>
        <atom:link href="http://blog.ssanj.net/feed.xml" rel="self"
                   type="application/rss+xml" />
        <lastBuildDate>Sun, 20 Sep 2015 00:00:00 UT</lastBuildDate>
        <item>
    <title>The Right Culture</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-09-20-the-right-culture.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>The problem with working at a company that doesn’t have the right culture is that you spend a lot of time during work, at lunch, at home, discussing and railing against a system which is clearly broken.</p>
<p>You should be using that time and energy for many useful things. To innovate. To make the world a better place. To spend time with our loved ones. To recuperate. Instead you waste it all fighting the system.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 20 Sep 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-09-20-the-right-culture.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>sanjiv sahayam</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>If You Want to Work for a Startup</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-09-20-if-you-want-to-work-for-a-startup.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>You should <a href="http://tech.co/dont-work-startup-wouldnt-start-2014-10">consider</a> this advice first:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“Never work for a startup that you wouldn’t start yourself.”</p>
</blockquote>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 20 Sep 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-09-20-if-you-want-to-work-for-a-startup.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>sanjiv sahayam</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Essentialism - Greg McKeown</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-09-20-essentialism-greg-mckeon.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Ideas from the book <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Essentialism-The-Disciplined-Pursuit-Less/dp/0804137382">Essentialism by Greg McKeown</a>.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Essentialism is the disciplined, systematic approach for determining where our highest point of contribution lies, then making execution of those things almost effortless.</p>
</blockquote>
<div class="figure">
<img src="/images/essentialism_highest_point_of_contribution.png" alt="The Highest Point of Contribution" />
<p class="caption">The Highest Point of Contribution</p>
</div>
<h2 id="essence">Essence</h2>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>“I choose to”.</li>
<li>Only few things matter.</li>
<li>I can do “anything” but “not everything”.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>A choice is an action.</li>
<li>Reject the idea what we can fit it all in.</li>
<li>By investing in fewer things we have the satisfying experience of making significant progress in the things that matter most.</li>
<li>Deliberately distinguish the vital few from the trivial many.</li>
<li>Eliminate the non-essential.</li>
<li>Remove obstacles so that the essential things have a clear, smooth passage.</li>
<li>Everything changes when we give ourselves permission to be more selective about what we choose to do.</li>
<li>Trade-offs represent a significant opportunity. By forcing us to weight our options and strategically select the best one for us, we significantly increase our chance of achieving the outcome we want.</li>
<li>Clarity == success</li>
</ul>
<div class="figure">
<img src="/images/essentialism_energy.png" alt="Focussed Impact" />
<p class="caption">Focussed Impact</p>
</div>
<h3 id="questions">Questions</h3>
<ul>
<li>Which problem do I want? (trade-off)</li>
<li>Is there a point where doing less (but thinking more) will actually produce better outcomes?</li>
<li>What is the most valuable result I could achieve in this job?</li>
<li>What do I want to go “big” on?</li>
</ul>
<div class="quote">
If you don’t prioritise your life someone else will.
</div>
<h2 id="step-1---explore">Step 1 - Explore</h2>
<p>Essentialists systematically explore and evaluate a broad set of options before committing to any. Because they will commit and “go big” on one or two ideas or activities, they deliberately explore more options at first to ensure that they pick the right one later.</p>
<ul>
<li>Create space to escape and explore life.</li>
<li>Focus is something we have and something we do.</li>
<li>Play doesn’t just help us to explore what is essential. It is essential in and of itself.</li>
<li>If we undereinvest in our minds, our bodies and our spirits, we damage the very tool we need to make our highest contribution.</li>
<li>Choose to do one fewer thing right now in order to do more tomorrow.</li>
<li>Our highest priority is to protect our ability to prioritise.</li>
<li>Say “Yes” to only the top 10% of opportunities.</li>
<li>You should just do that one thing that you are passionate about and that you can be best at.</li>
<li>Look for the one thing where you can make your absolute highest point of contribution.</li>
</ul>
<div class="quote">
It is our ability to choose that makes us human.
</div>
<div class="attribution">
Madeleine L’Engle
</div>
<h3 id="the-90-rule">The 90% Rule</h3>
<p>When you evaluate an option, think about the single most important criterion for that decision and then give it a score between 0 and 100. If you rate it any lower than 90%, then change the rating to 0 and reject it.</p>
<h3 id="sleep">Sleep</h3>
<ul>
<li>One hour more of sleep == several more hours of much higher productivity.</li>
<li>Sleep is for high performers.</li>
<li>Sleep breeds creativity.</li>
<li>Sleep enables the highest level of mental contribution.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="questions-1">Questions</h3>
<ul>
<li>Is this exactly what I’m looking for?</li>
<li>What am I deeply passionate about?</li>
<li>What taps my talent?</li>
<li>What meets a significant need in the world?</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="step-2---eliminate">Step 2 - Eliminate</h2>
<p>It’s about the emotional discipline necessary to say “No” to social pressure.</p>
<ul>
<li>Make the one decision that eliminates thousand later decisions.</li>
<li>The clarity of what is essential fuels us with the strength to say “No” to the non-essential.</li>
<li>When we push back effectively, it shows people that our time is highly valuable. It distinguishes the professional from the amateur.</li>
<li>Force your superiors to make trade-offs instead of “expecting it all”.</li>
<li>We have to get rid of options or activities that maybe good, or even really good but get in the way.</li>
<li>Have an overarching intent by which you can check yourself.</li>
<li>Hesitate before stepping into a problem. Wait. Observe. See how things develop.</li>
<li>Set rules in advance that eliminate the need for a direct “No”.</li>
<li>Set boundaries.</li>
<li>Setting limits will make you limitless.</li>
<li>Give people and opportunity to solve their own problems.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="deal-breakers">Deal Breakers</h3>
<p>Make a list of the types of requests or activities that you simply refuse to say “Yes” to, unless they somehow overlap with your own priorities or agenda.</p>
<p>To find out your deal breakers write down any time you feel violate or put upon by someone’s request.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>It is hard to imaging executives in most companies who would be comfortable with employees bringing in their children to work on Monday morning, yet they seem to have no problem expecting their employees to come into the office or to work on a project on a Saturday or Sunday.</p>
</blockquote>
<h3 id="zero-based-budgeting">Zero-based Budgeting</h3>
<p>Every item in the proposed budget must be justified from scratch each time. (Every year, month, iteration etc)</p>
<h3 id="reverse-pilot">Reverse Pilot</h3>
<p>You test whether removing an initiative or activity will have any negative consequences.</p>
<h3 id="questions-2">Questions</h3>
<ul>
<li>If I didn’t have this opportunity what would I be willing to do to acquire it?</li>
<li>What will I say “No” to?</li>
<li>How will we know when we are “done” ?</li>
<li>What else could I do with this time and money if I pulled the plug now?</li>
</ul>
<div class="quote">
Tell me, what it is you plan to do with your one wild and precious life?
</div>
<div class="attribution">
Mary Oliver
</div>
<h2 id="step-3---execute">Step 3 - Execute</h2>
<p>Essentialists invest the time they have saved into creating a system for removing obstacles and making execution as easy as possible.</p>
<ul>
<li>Build in buffers for unexpected events.</li>
<li>Practise extreme and early preparation.</li>
<li>Celebrate small acts of progress.</li>
<li>Make small improvements in the things that you do often.</li>
<li>There is power in steadiness and repetition.</li>
<li>There is power in visibly seeing progress towards a goal.</li>
<li>Design routines that enshrine what is essential.</li>
<li>Make the essential the default position.</li>
<li>Do your hardest task of the day the first thing in the morning.</li>
<li>Make a list of everything vying for your attention and cross out the non-essential right now.</li>
</ul>
<div class="quote">
Give me six hours to chop down a tree and I will spend the first four sharpening the axe.
</div>
<div class="attribution">
Abraham Lincoln
</div>
<h3 id="the-present">The Present</h3>
<ul>
<li>Focus on the present.</li>
<li>Tune into what’s important right now.</li>
<li>Enjoy the moment.</li>
<li>Write down things that trigger you to be in the moment. Try to recreate them each day.</li>
</ul>
<div class="quote">
In work, do what you enjoy. In family life be completely present.
</div>
<div class="attribution">
Lao Tzu
</div>
<h3 id="scenario-planning">Scenario Planning</h3>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>What are the risks?</li>
<li>What are the worse-case scenarios?</li>
<li>What are the social impacts?</li>
<li>What are the financial impacts?</li>
<li>How can you invest to strengthen social and financial resilience?</li>
</ol>
<h3 id="questions-3">Questions</h3>
<ul>
<li>What obstacle is keeping you back from achieving what really matters to you?</li>
<li>What is the smallest amount of progress that will be useful and valuable to the essential task we are trying to get done?</li>
<li>What is the minimal amount I could do right now to prepare.</li>
</ul>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 20 Sep 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-09-20-essentialism-greg-mckeon.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>sanjiv sahayam</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>The Most Important Criteria.</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-09-16-the-most-important-criteria.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>When we approach a job opportunity we mostly look for things that are not all that important. How much does it pay? Can I use technology X? How close is it to my home?</p>
<p>What we should be looking for are two main things:</p>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>Ethical leaders.</li>
<li>Meaningful work.</li>
</ol>
<p>Everything else is irrelevant.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 16 Sep 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-09-16-the-most-important-criteria.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>sanjiv sahayam</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Seth Godin on After You&apos;ve Done Your Best Work.</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-09-16-seth-godin-on-after-you%27ve-done-your-best-work.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Seth Godin in his article <a href="http://sethgodin.typepad.com/seths_blog/2015/08/after-youve-done-your-best-work.html">After You’ve Done Your Best Work</a> says that if your best work has been ignored then:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>You really have no choice but to do it again. To do your best work again, as impossible and unfair as that seems.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Because:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>It compounds over time.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>And:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Best work followed by best work followed by more best work is far more useful and generous than merely doing your best work once and insisting we understand you.</p>
</blockquote>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 16 Sep 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-09-16-seth-godin-on-after-you%27ve-done-your-best-work.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>sanjiv sahayam</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Secrets.</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-09-16-secrets.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Will destroy your company. There is no place for secrets - especially in small close-knit teams. Secrets lead to speculation, gossip and worse - people leaving for the wrong reasons. It also gives employees the message that “you can’t handle the truth” or “you’re not in the inner circle”. Both these messages should be avoided.</p>
<p>This takes me back to a client-site I worked at a few years back. There were two team leaders across the various teams. One day one of the team leaders just stopped coming in. There were rumours of “disciplinary action”. But no announcement was made. When I asked the surviving team lead what had happened he said “We don’t talk about X”. I never saw team lead X again. It was like the company wanted to erase all evidence his existence. It felt like anyone could be “erased” at a moments notice.</p>
<p>This type of reality distortion just doesn’t work. It would have good to know what had happened to team lead X. After all how would we know not to do what he did? Unfortunately this was a missed opportunity to reinforce the company code of conduct or to behave in a decent way.</p>
<p>Secrets are about fear. If sharing some information with your employees has got you scared then you absolutely must share it with them. If they find out your secret from other sources or figure it out for themselves the consequences will be much worse.</p>
<p>Contrast this with companies like <a href="https://buffer.com/about">buffer</a> that are <a href="https://open.bufferapp.com/transparent-pricing-buffer">open</a> about most things like <a href="https://open.bufferapp.com/introducing-open-salaries-at-buffer-including-our-transparent-formula-and-all-individual-salaries">salaries</a>, <a href="https://open.bufferapp.com/buffer-values">core values</a> etc.</p>
<p>And the most important reason not to have secrets is because it’s not a decent way to operate any company.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 16 Sep 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-09-16-secrets.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>sanjiv sahayam</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>No Matter What Stones</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-09-16-no-matter-what-stones.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<div>
<div class="quote">
To stand for your dreams + heart’s desires and deepest values no matter what stones those who do not understand may toss at you.
</div>
<div class="attribution">
<a href="http://www.robinsharma.com/blog/08/for-real-human-beings-only">Robin Sharma</a>
</div>
</div>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 16 Sep 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-09-16-no-matter-what-stones.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>sanjiv sahayam</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Negotiate for the One Thing you Need.</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-09-16-negotiate-for-the-one-thing-you-need.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Many workplaces have the “potential” to be great. Few rarely live up to that potential. If you’ve been contemplating leaving unless things change, try to be clear about what will make you stay. Discard any notions about what “should” have happened or what was “owed” to you or how you were “lied” to.</p>
<p>Ask yourself “what would it take to make me stay?”. Once you have the answer negotiate to achieve that. Only that. Or leave.</p>
<p>When negotiating make sure to only talk with decision-makers. You are wasting your time with anyone else.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 16 Sep 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-09-16-negotiate-for-the-one-thing-you-need.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>sanjiv sahayam</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Seth Godin on The One Thing that will Change Everything.</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-09-06-seth-godin-on-the-one-thing-that-will-change-everything.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Another great article sent to me by my friend <a href="http://ryandrake.com">Ryan</a> was this one by <a href="http://sethgodin.typepad.com/seths_blog/2015/08/the-one-thing-that-will-change-everything.html">Seth Godin on waiting for the one thing that will change everything</a>. In it Seth talks about that one thing:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>That introduction you need.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The capital that your organization is trying to raise.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The breakthrough in what you’re building…</p>
</blockquote>
<p>And the real effect that one thing has once you get it:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Have you noticed that as soon as you get that one thing, everything doesn’t change? In fact, the only thing that changes is that you realize that you don’t need that one thing as much as you thought you did.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>He advises to stop waiting for a silver bullet:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>It turns out that nothing will change everything for the better. It works better to focus on each step instead of being distracted by a promised secret exit.</p>
</blockquote>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 06 Sep 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-09-06-seth-godin-on-the-one-thing-that-will-change-everything.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>sanjiv sahayam</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Seth Godin on Creating Something Remarkable</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-09-06-seth-godin-on-creating-something-remarkable.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Seth Godin in his <a href="http://sethgodin.typepad.com/seths_blog/2015/06/pulling-a-hat-out-of-a-rabbit.html">article on pulling a hat out of a rabbit</a> says that:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>It’s tempting to do what’s been done before, certain in the belief that if you do it, it’ll be a little better and a little more popular, merely because you’re the one doing it.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>In fact, though, that’s unlikely. You’ll care more, but it’s unlikely the market will.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Consider doing it differently:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Consider the alternative, which is choosing to turn the question upside down, to do it backwards, sideways, or in a significantly more generous or risky way.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Remarkable often starts with the problem you set out to solve and the way you choose to solve it.</p>
</blockquote>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 06 Sep 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-09-06-seth-godin-on-creating-something-remarkable.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>sanjiv sahayam</dc:creator>
</item>

    </channel>
</rss>
