<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
    xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
    <channel>
        <title>BabylonCandle</title>
        <link>http://blog.ssanj.net</link>
        <description><![CDATA[The blog of Sanjiv Sahayam]]></description>
        <atom:link href="http://blog.ssanj.net/feed.xml" rel="self"
                   type="application/rss+xml" />
        <lastBuildDate>Thu, 22 Oct 2015 00:00:00 UT</lastBuildDate>
        <item>
    <title>Git Commit Message Format</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-10-22-git-commit-message-format.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>There are <a href="http://tbaggery.com/2008/04/19/a-note-about-git-commit-messages.html">rules</a> on how to <a href="https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/GitCommitMessages">structure</a> a Git <a href="https://github.com/phonegap/phonegap/wiki/Git-Commit-Message-Format">commit message</a>. Here are some of the common ones.</p>
<h2 id="the-50-character-subject">The 50 character subject</h2>
<p>The first line of a Git commit should be 50 characters long. This is because commits were initially meant to be shared via email where this first line acted as the subject. As such it should not have an ending period.</p>
<p>Some reasons for following this are:</p>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>The output from git log –oneline is easier to read.</li>
<li>Github subjects that are over 72 characters are truncated.</li>
</ol>
<div class="figure">
<img src="/images/git_comment_wrapped_subject.png" alt="Github truncates subjects over 72 characters" />
<p class="caption">Github truncates subjects over 72 characters</p>
</div>
<h2 id="the-blank-second-line">The blank second line</h2>
<p>The second line should be blank and separates the subject from the commit body.</p>
<p>This ensures proper parsing when sending commits by email and Github.</p>
<h2 id="the-72-character-body">The 72 character body</h2>
<p>The following lines should be a maximum of 72 characters in length. This can include multiple paragraphs each of 72 characters which are separated by a blank line.</p>
<p>This helps with reading the commit message on terminals that are usually around 80 characters wide.</p>
<h2 id="link-to-featureissue">Link to feature/issue</h2>
<p>Another convention is to add a link to the issue or feature being worked on as the last line. This could be a link to Jira or Youtrack issue etc.</p>
<p>Here’s an example of a Git commit message with all of the above rules:</p>
<pre class="terminal scrollx"><code>Add support for reverse sorting of imports

Natural sorting, sorts from upper to lowercase. This reverses the sort
order because we want packages to sort first before class names.

An example would be:
import scala.concurrent._
import ExecutionContext.Implicits.global

[https://yourtracker/project/PORT-120]</code></pre>
<h2 id="some-additional-rules">Some additional rules</h2>
<h3 id="imperative-mood">Imperative Mood</h3>
<p>Some people advocate using <a href="http://www.grammar-monster.com/glossary/imperative_mood.htm">imperative mood</a> for the subject. This is basically a command-like phrase:</p>
<pre class="terminal scrollx"><code>Add W
Fix X
Delete Y
Create Z</code></pre>
<p>Your commit message is meant to complete the sentence:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>This commit will …</p>
</blockquote>
<p>When you write the subject in imperative mode it completes as:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>This commit will Fix X</p>
</blockquote>
<p>If you wrote “Fixes X” then it won’t read correctly:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>This commit will Fixes X</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I’ve tried this for a few months now and don’t see any real benefit in using one tense over the other. As long as what the commit does is clear it should be fine. Your mileage may vary.</p>
<div class="figure">
<img src="/images/git-comment_imperative_mood.png" alt="Docker commits using imperative mood" />
<p class="caption">Docker commits using imperative mood</p>
</div>
<h3 id="issue-number-in-subject">Issue number in Subject</h3>
<p>Some use the issue number as the first entry in the subject.</p>
<div class="figure">
<img src="/images/git_comment_issue_no_in_subject.png" alt="Issue number at start of the subject" />
<p class="caption">Issue number at start of the subject</p>
</div>
<p>Others use it somewhere in the subject.</p>
<div class="figure">
<img src="/images/git_comment_issue_no_in_subject_end.png" alt="Issue number in the subject" />
<p class="caption">Issue number in the subject</p>
</div>
<p>If you find all these rules too constrictive, then <a href="http://zachholman.com/posts/git-commit-history">you’re not alone</a>. I agree with Zach on this for personal projects. I think following the rules leads to better commit messages that are easier to understand. This is important when we need to collaborate with other developers.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Thu, 22 Oct 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-10-22-git-commit-message-format.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>sanjiv sahayam</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Culture Flow</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-10-22-culture-flow.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Some companies have good work cultures. They are an environment where employees can thrive and do their best work. Happy and effective employees lead to customers who are well <a href="http://sethgodin.typepad.com/seths_blog/2015/09/tires-coffee-and-people.html">looked-after</a>.</p>
<p>Other companies have cultures that are not so good. The lack of access to clean facilities in a first-world country like Australia still astounds me. Ergonomic chairs to sit on is another basic need that is often neglected. Taking a customer’s money and then not providing them with the service they paid for, fearing change because it will “break” things and <a href="http://sanj.ink/posts/2015-09-16-secrets.html">keeping secrets</a> are some other signs.</p>
<p>Industrial age working conditions like having rigid work hours, having to be “seen” to know that you are working and where you have to be micromanaged because you can’t be “trusted” are not very effective in the information age.</p>
<p>Unfortunately if you do work for one of these “other” companies then you should strive to change the culture should you choose to stay. It will take a monumental effort and it might be fleeting. You owe it to yourself to try. Most companies will ignore any issues that they have. They might say things like “we have improved dramatically over the last year, you should have seen it when ….” Culture flows from top to bottom. If you are in a bad culture you only have to look to the leaders to see where it flows from.</p>
<p>You owe it to yourself to have a good working environment. Fight for it if you have to. Leave if you can’t change it.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Thu, 22 Oct 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-10-22-culture-flow.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>sanjiv sahayam</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>When the Learning Stops</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-10-21-when-the-learning-stops.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>the hurting starts, I mentioned to a mate at work. If you are not learning anything new then you are stagnating. There is no excuse to stagnate for eight hours a day, five days a week.</p>
<p>While you are learning new things you might turn a blind eye to other obvious issues with your workplace. You might trade learning for somewhat dubious work conditions and practices. Once you are no longer getting any benefit from learning new things, the issues with your workplace will become magnified and move into focus.</p>
<p>If you find yourself in a dead end job where you’re not learning anything useful it’s time for you to start looking for new opportunities.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 21 Oct 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-10-21-when-the-learning-stops.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>sanjiv sahayam</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Is it a One Line Change?</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-10-21-is-it-a-one-line-change.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>I’ve heard managers ask developers this question. It’s like the number of lines changed is going to mitigate risk somehow. The unstated assumption is: the more code this guy writes the higher the chance of him introducing a bug. Trust is at an all time low; the brittleness of the system an all time high.</p>
<p>Almost every system could be compromised with a one line change. Ask yourself what that one line would be for your system. I’m sure you’ll come up with one.</p>
<p>What’s disturbing about this question is that managers are now making calls on how and how much code is written. That’s like me asking an electrician “is it a one wire change?” It makes no more sense in that scenario either.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 21 Oct 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-10-21-is-it-a-one-line-change.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>sanjiv sahayam</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Hiring the Cheapest Developers</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-10-21-hiring-the-cheapest-developers.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>A disturbing trend specially in startups is hiring the cheapest, most junior developers out there. The thought process is that “they are good enough” or that “programming is easy” or most of all “they’re cheap”. Some of these misconceptions have been fuelled by stories of yet another 8-year old making an iPhone app. “How hard can this stuff be?” The reality is that it is hard - if you want any software beyond a prototype that you can charge your customers for.</p>
<p>Unfortunately when you hire these more junior developers, they become a massive strain on your existing developers. Your existing developers need to spend a considerable amount of chaperoning these juniors for at least three to six months. You probably don’t want to hand production releases to them either so that’s on your existing developers as well. In the meantime all critical production issues are also handled by your existing developers who also have to juggle their own workload along with everything else. All this happens while management is left scratching their heads as to why productivity has not gone up.</p>
<p>Another aspect of this is that when you hire junior developers they have to struggle very hard to catch up. Getting to a basic level of competency is going to take work - a lot of work. They’ve got to learn the technologies, the systems, keep up with new developments and transition into taking on more responsibility. It seems unreasonable to expect these developers to help push your company to new heights in the short term.</p>
<p>Do yourself a favour and hire the right mix of developer for your task at hand (seniors, intermediates and juniors). If not you might find that as you hire more junior developers that your existing developers choose to work elsewhere.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 21 Oct 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-10-21-hiring-the-cheapest-developers.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>sanjiv sahayam</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>My Ideal Work Culture</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-10-14-my-ideal-work-culture.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Since resigning from my current workplace, I’ve been thinking about the attributes I’d like to see in my next one. Here are my thoughts:</p>
<ul>
<li>Meaningful work. Helping people and changing the world for the better in some small way.</li>
<li>Leaders who are ethical. Not people just out to make a buck. Idealists who have a vision for making humanity better. Someone who leads from the front. Someone who is a part of the team instead of some elitist-untouchable. Someone who listens to ideas from even the most junior employees.</li>
<li>Freedom to work how you want to work, when you want to work and from where you want to work.</li>
<li>Trusted to do the right thing.</li>
<li>Being part of a great hard-working team that focuses on delivering quality products or outcomes.</li>
<li>Real work/life balance.</li>
<li>Having learning and doing culture.</li>
<li>Active in the community, be it charities, open source, hosting meet ups etc. Giving back somehow.</li>
</ul>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 14 Oct 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-10-14-my-ideal-work-culture.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>sanjiv sahayam</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Enjoyable Work</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-10-14-enjoyable-work.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Here are some of the ways I enjoy to work.</p>
<div class="figure">
<img src="/images/enjoyable_work_mm_2.png" alt="Mind map of what I find enjoyable about work" />
<p class="caption">Mind map of what I find enjoyable about work</p>
</div>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 14 Oct 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-10-14-enjoyable-work.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>sanjiv sahayam</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Daring Greatly - Brené Brown</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-10-14-daring-greatly-brene-brown.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Ideas from the book <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Daring-Greatly-Courage-Vulnerable-Transforms/dp/1592408419">Daring Greatly by Brené Brown</a></p>
<blockquote>
<p>It is not the critic who counts; not the man who points out how the strong man stumbles, or where the doer of deeds could have done them better.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The credit belongs to the man who is actually in the arena, whose face is marred by dust and sweat and blood; who strives valiantly; who errs, who comes short again and again,</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>because there is no effort without error and shortcoming; but who does actually strive to do the deeds; who knows great enthusiasms, the great devotions; who spends himself in a worthy cause;</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>who at the best knows in the end the triumph of high achievement, and who at the worst, if he fails, at least fails while daring greatly…</p>
</blockquote>
<ul>
<li>If we want to reignite innovation and passion, we have to rehumanize work.</li>
<li>When failure is not an option we can forget about learning, creativity and innovation.</li>
</ul>
<div class="quote">
What we know matters, but who we are matters more
</div>
<ul>
<li>The ability to acknowledge our risks and exposure, greatly increases our chances of adhering to some kind of positive health regimen.</li>
<li>We love seeing raw truth and openness in other people, but we are afraid to let them see it in us.</li>
<li>Speak openly about failing.</li>
</ul>
<div class="quote">
What’s worth doing even if I fail?
</div>
<ul>
<li>Sharing appropriately, with boundaries, means sharing with people with whom you’ve developed relationships that can bear the weight of our story.</li>
<li>Until we can receive with an open heart, we are never really giving with an open heart. When we attach judgement to receiving help, we knowingly or unknowingly attach judgement to giving help.</li>
<li>A sense of worthiness inspires us to be vulnerable, share openly, and persevere.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="shame">Shame</h2>
<div class="quote">
Shame is the intensely painful feeling or experience of believing that we are flawed and therefore unworthy of love and belonging
</div>
<ul>
<li>Shame derives its power from being unspeakable.</li>
<li>Shame is fear of disconnection.</li>
<li>People believe they deserve their shame; they do not believe they deserve their humiliation.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<p>The secret killer of innovation is shame. You can’t measure it, but it is there. Every time someone holds back on a new idea, fails to give their manager much needed feedback, and is afraid to speak up in front of a client you can be sure shame played a part. That deep fear we all have of being wrong, of being belittled and of feeling less than, is what stops us taking the very risks required to move out companies forward.</p>
</blockquote>
<ul>
<li>You are only as sick as your secrets.</li>
<li>Real belonging doesn’t necessitate disdain.</li>
<li>We judge people in areas where we are vulnerable to shame.</li>
<li>We’re hard on each other because we’re using each other as a launching pad out of our own perceived shaming deficiency.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="shame-resilience">Shame Resilience</h2>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>Practise courage and reach out by sharing your experience with someone who has earned the right to hear it.</li>
<li>Talk to yourself the way you would to someone you really love and who you are trying to comfort.</li>
<li>Own your story - don’t bury it. “If you own the story you get to write the ending.”</li>
</ol>
<blockquote>
<p>Love is not something we give or get; it is something we nurture and grow, a connection that can only be cultivated between two people when it exists within each one of them - we can only love others as much as we love ourselves.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Shame, blame, disrespect, betrayal, and the withholding of affection damage the roots from which love grows. Love can only survive these injuries if they are acknowledged, healed and rare.</p>
</blockquote>
<div class="quote">
Vulnerability is the last thing I want you to see in me, but the first thing I look for in you
</div>
<h2 id="joy">Joy</h2>
<ul>
<li>Participants described happiness as an emotion that’s connected to circumstance and they described joy as a spiritual way of engaging with the world that’s connected to a practising of gratitude.</li>
<li>Joy comes to us in ordinary moments. Scarcity culture may keep us afraid of living small, ordinary lives.</li>
<li>Be grateful for what you have. Celebrate it. Share your gratitude with others.</li>
<li>Don’t squander joy. We can’t prepare for tragedy and loss.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<p>But every time we allow ourselves to learn into joy and give in to those moments, we build resilience and we cultivate hope. The joy becomes part of who we are, and when bad things happen, we are stronger.</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="perfectionism">Perfectionism</h2>
<ul>
<li>Healthy striving is self-focused: How can I improve? Perfectionism is other-focused: What will they think?</li>
<li>The fear of failing, making mistakes, not meeting people’s expectations, and being criticised keeps us outside the arena.</li>
<li>Perfectionism is a form of shame.</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<p>I remind myself “Don’t let the perfect be the enemy of good” - (Cribbed from Voltaire.) A twenty-minute walk that I do is better than a four-hour run that I don’t do. The imperfect book that gets published is better than the perfect book that never leaves my computer. The dinner party of take-out Chinese food is better than the elegant dinner that I never host.</p>
</blockquote>
<ul>
<li><p>To manage perfectionism give yourself permission to do lots of things that are good enough.</p></li>
<li>Because we are hard-wired for connection, disconnection always creates pain.</li>
<li><p>If we want to fully experience love and belonging, we must believe that we are worthy of love and belonging.</p></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="rehumanise-work">Rehumanise work</h2>
<ul>
<li>Most people and most organisations can’t stand the uncertainty and the risk of real innovation. Learning and creating are inherently vulnerable. There’s never enough certainty. People want guarantees.</li>
<li>Something related to fear keeps people from going for it. They focus on what they already do well and they don’t put themselves out there.</li>
<li>No corporation or school can thrive in the absence of creativity, innovation, and learning, and the greatest threat to all three of these is disengagement.</li>
<li>When we are disengaged, we don’t show up, we don’t contribute, and we stop caring.</li>
<li>If blame is a pattern in your culture, then shame needs to addressed as an issue.</li>
<li>Cover-up cultures depend on shame keeping folks quiet.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="vulnerability-meter">Vulnerability Meter</h3>
<p>How often to people in your business, school, communities say these things?</p>
<ul>
<li>“I don’t know.”</li>
<li>“I need help.”</li>
<li>“I’d like to give it a shot.”</li>
<li>“It’s important to me.”</li>
<li>“I disagree - can we talk about it?”</li>
<li>“It didn’t work, but I learned a lot.”</li>
<li>“Yes, I did it.”</li>
<li>“Here’s what I need.”</li>
<li>“Here’s how I feel.”</li>
<li>“I’d like some feedback.”</li>
<li>“Can I get your take on this?”</li>
<li>“What can I do better next time?”</li>
<li>“Can you teach me how to do this?”</li>
<li>“I played a part in that.”</li>
<li>“I accept responsibility for that.”</li>
<li>“I’m here for you.”</li>
<li>“I want to help.”</li>
<li>“Let’s move on.”</li>
<li>“I’m sorry.”</li>
<li>“That means a lot to me.”</li>
<li>“Thank you.”</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="parenting">Parenting</h2>
<ul>
<li>Certainty often breeds absolutes, intolerance and judgement.</li>
</ul>
<div class="quote">
Are you the adult you want your child to grow up to be?
</div>
<ul>
<li>If we want our children to love and accept who they are, our job is to love and accept who we are.</li>
<li>We can’t raise children who are more shame resilient than we are.</li>
<li>Normalising means helping our children know they’re not alone and that we’ve experienced many of the same struggles.</li>
<li>When we feel good about the choices we’re making and when we’re engaging with the world from a place of worthiness rather than scarcity, we feel no need to judge and attack.</li>
<li>Daring greatly means finding our own path and respecting what the search looks like for other folks.</li>
<li>Belonging is being somewhere you want to be, and where they want you. Fitting in is being accepted for being like everyone else.</li>
<li>Parenting perfection is not the goal. The best gifts and teaching moments happen in those imperfect moments when we allow children to help us mind the gap.</li>
</ul>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 14 Oct 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-10-14-daring-greatly-brene-brown.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>sanjiv sahayam</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Your Best Life</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-10-07-your-best-life.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Your life is meant to be beautiful. Cast into the fire anything that destroys your soul. Dream your best life. Live it.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 07 Oct 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-10-07-your-best-life.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>sanjiv sahayam</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>The Allure of Potential</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-10-07-the-allure-of-potential.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>I’ve worked at many companies over the years. Many of them had a real potential to be great. We’d say things like “Once we get more funding” or “Once we get that big customer” or “Once we fix this bug” then “things will be better”. Unfortunately most times, “things” don’t get better. In fact they usually get worse. There is no magic formula to know how long you should stick it out at a company. But there are <a href="http://sanj.ink/posts/2015-05-07-reasons.html">reasons</a>. Potential unrealised is just a false promise. A waste of time.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 07 Oct 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-10-07-the-allure-of-potential.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>sanjiv sahayam</dc:creator>
</item>

    </channel>
</rss>
