<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
    xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
    <channel>
        <title>BabylonCandle</title>
        <link>http://blog.ssanj.net</link>
        <description><![CDATA[The blog of Sanjiv Sahayam]]></description>
        <atom:link href="http://blog.ssanj.net/feed.xml" rel="self"
                   type="application/rss+xml" />
        <lastBuildDate>Tue, 27 Oct 2015 00:00:00 UT</lastBuildDate>
        <item>
    <title>Things a Little Bird Told Me - Biz Stone</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-10-27-things-a-little-bird-told-me-biz-stone.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Ideas from the book <a href="http://thingsalittlebirdtoldme.com">Things a Little Bird Told Me by Biz Stone</a>.</p>
<div class="quote">
When you’re starting a company, you sometimes have nothing more than an idea. And sometimes you don’t even have the idea - just the supreme confidence that one day you will have an idea. You have to begin somewhere, so you declare yourself an entrepreneur just like Wile E. Coyote declares himself a genius. Then you make a business card and give yourself the title FOUNDER and CEO.
</div>
<ul>
<li>There are good people everywhere.</li>
<li>A company can build a business, do good in society, and have fun. These three goals can run alongside each other, without being dominated by the bottom line.</li>
<li>People given the right tools, can accomplish amazing things.</li>
</ul>
<div class="quote">
We can change lives. We can change the world.
</div>
<ul>
<li>If we pretend to know all the answers we may get a closer look at all the questions.</li>
<li>Visualise what you want to see happen for yourself in the next two years.</li>
<li>If you take an idea and just hold it in your head, you unconsciously start to do things that advance you toward that goal.</li>
<li>Opportunity is manufactured.</li>
<li>Rather than waiting and pouncing with a high degree of failure, you might as well go ahead and create the set of circumstances on your own. If you make the opportunity, you’ll be the first in position to take advantage of it.</li>
<li>Being the person who makes something happen for yourself is the core of entrepreneurship.</li>
<li>Luck is a piece that is out of your hands. But as you create opportunities for yourself, your odds at the lottery go way up.</li>
</ul>
<div class="quote">
The way I saw it, people went to college in order to be qualified to get a job like the one I was being offered.
</div>
<ul>
<li>Believing in yourself, the genius you, means you have confidence in your ideas before they even exist. In order to have a vision for business, or your potential, you must allocate space for that vision.</li>
<li>Inventing your dreams is the first and biggest step toward making it come true.</li>
<li>Learn not to care about hard work being wasted. You can always put it in your portfolio. Don’t take rejection personally.</li>
<li>Creativity is limitless.</li>
<li>For any one problem there are infinite potential solutions.</li>
<li>Challenge yourself everyday.</li>
<li>Experience and curiosity drives us to make unexpected, offbeat connections. It is these non-linear steps that often lead to the greatest work.</li>
<li>Asking questions is free. Do it!</li>
<li>Are you in an environment where creativity thrives? Is there room for new ideas every day? Can you make room?</li>
</ul>
<div class="quote">
If you don’t love what you are building, if you’re not an avid user yourself, then you will most likely fail even if you’re doing everything else right.
</div>
<ul>
<li>You know in your heart when something is worth pursuing; you’re not sure exactly why, but it doesn’t matter. Success isn’t guaranteed, but failure is certain if you aren’t truly emotionally invested in your work.</li>
<li>It was a joy to work on Twitter.</li>
</ul>
<div class="quote">
I always tell people to back into it. Imagine working on something you love. Describe it to yourself. Don’t focus on how much money you want. Instead think about this: What type of people surround you? What sort of work are they doing? How do you get to work? What adjectives would people use to describe what you do?
</div>
<ul>
<li>Embrace your constraints, whether they are creative, physical, economic or self-imposed. They are provocative. They are challenging. They wake you up. They make you more creative. They make you better.</li>
<li>Risks breed success.</li>
</ul>
<div class="quote">
When it comes to taking risks, so many of us hedge. It’s natural to set up safety nets. I’ve often met with entrepreneurs who tell me that they are hanging on to their job and tinkering at night on their passion. Of course they are; they need to feed their families. The problem is unless you are willing to accept the worst-case scenario, you can’t expect to achieve the best-case scenario. If it is going to reach the potential you dream it will, your true calling needs all your attention. Willingness to take risks is the path to success.
</div>
<ul>
<li>In order to succeed spectacularly, you must be ready to fail spectacularly.</li>
<li>Embrace the upside of fantastic, epic, earth-shattering, life-changing failure. It’s totally worth it if you succeed. And if you fail, you’ve got a great story to tell - and some experience that gives you a serious edge the next time you go for it.</li>
<li>Gray mode - separating the system into different pieces so that if one piece failed, it could be isolated and not affect the other pieces.</li>
<li>You don’t have to advertise your failings but to hide them is, on some level, deceptive. This is linked to the value of vulnerability. When you let people understand that you are people like they are, passionate but imperfect, what you get in return is goodwill.</li>
</ul>
<div class="quote">
I believe in honesty, and I believe that explaing mistakes to the people who used our service was the best way to create a long-term relationship with them.
</div>
<ul>
<li>He wanted people to know that they were doing their best, but he didn’t want to hide or downplay their flaws. He decided that they would own their many imperfections.</li>
</ul>
<div class="quote">
If the system crashed, I’d walk down to the engineers to investigate what had happened. Then I’d go on the Twitter blog to report what I’d discovered.
</div>
<ul>
<li>The loudest complainers are often your biggest fans.</li>
<li>It doesn’t pay to act bulletproof. Nobody is flawless, and when you act as if you are, it always rings false.</li>
</ul>
<div class="quote">
Not only did we encourage angry people to email us, but I put my cell number on the home page of the site and answered the phone when it rang.
</div>
<ul>
<li>He learned that failure was part of the path and that it was worth the risk. It was a critical component of growth.</li>
<li>Every company needs an idealist.</li>
<li>Innovation comes from <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Where-Good-Ideas-Come-From/dp/1594485380">pre-existing ideas</a>.</li>
<li>When everything is wrong and broken, instead of harping on what’s wrong and broken, find what works and build on that.</li>
<li>An open, curious, optimistic mind yields solutions, and has a better time along the way.</li>
<li>Twitter was proof that leaderless self-organising systems could be true agents of change.</li>
<li>Twitter connected people everywhere instantly to what was most meaningful to them.</li>
</ul>
<div class="quote">
The point is to trust your instincts, even if you’re smaller and less powerful than the other guy.
</div>
<ul>
<li>Watching for patterns of use across the system, they built features based on those patterns.</li>
</ul>
<div class="quote">
If I was willing to face the consequences, I could play by my own rules.
</div>
<ul>
<li>Trust your instincts, know what you want, and believe in your ability to achieve it.</li>
<li>We should always seek knowledge even in the face of fear.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="assumptions-for-twitter-employees">Assumptions for Twitter Employees</h2>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>We don’t always know what’s going to happen.</li>
<li>There are more smart people out there than in here.</li>
<li>We will win if we do the right thing for our users.</li>
<li>The only deal worth doing is a win-win deal.</li>
<li>Our coworkers are smart and they have good intentions.</li>
<li>We can build a business, change the world and have fun.</li>
</ol>
<h3 id="we-dont-always-know-whats-going-to-happen">We don’t always know what’s going to happen</h3>
<ul>
<li>If we think we know what will come next, we’ll fail. Instead, we need to leave the door open, for unknown developments and surprises. The core element of this assumption is humility.</li>
<li>The ability to listen, watch, and draw lessons from the obvious and unlikely places breeds originality and growth.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="there-are-more-smart-people-out-there-than-in-here">There are more smart people out there than in here</h3>
<ul>
<li>We shouldn’t look only internally for answers to challenges.</li>
<li>Ask people. Look around. Research. Keep a level head. Don’t think you are so great. Don’t assume that we’re the only people who can solve our problem.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="we-will-win-if-we-do-the-right-thing-for-our-users">We will win if we do the right thing for our users</h3>
<ul>
<li>Does it make the experience better for people?</li>
<li>More than 99% of people just leave the settings on default.</li>
<li>Making a feature that is optional is like throwing it into the junk drawer.</li>
<li>It’s our responsibility to decide what features make the most sense. If we are going to build it, let’s use it.</li>
</ul>
<div class="quote">
<p>The place where companies most frequently lose sight of what’s best for their customers is when it comes to monetisation.</p>
<p>Should we make ads 50 percent bigger so we can make more money? It makes the page ugly and hard to read. Is that good for the users? No.</p>
<p>Should we split our company into two separate buildings because we can’t afford one building? It leads to confusion and poor decisions on the product end. Is that good for our users? No.</p>
<p>Should we deceive the user into clicking on an ad? Obviously not. Should we trick our users into clicking on anything? Hell no!</p>
<p>These can be tough choices especially if you really need the money. But there’s got to be another way. Creativity is a renewable resource. Don’t sell out your product. Keep thinking. Consider whether the average person is going to benefit. Measure every decision against that requirement.</p>
</div>
<h3 id="the-only-deal-worth-doing-is-a-win-win-deal">The only deal worth doing is a win-win deal</h3>
<ul>
<li>There’s no such thing as a good deal in which one party gets the short end of the stick. Deals are like relationships. We want deals that are going to last.</li>
<li>To some extent, in every deal your reputation and your business are at stake.</li>
</ul>
<div class="quote">
If you have a list of people that you don’t want to lose at any cost, don’t wait until they quit to offer them more money and more stock options.
</div>
<h3 id="we-can-build-a-business-change-the-world-and-have-fun">We can build a business, change the world and have fun</h3>
<div class="quote">
Traditionally, companies are driven by financial success. But I want the new definition to include making a positive impact on the world - and loving your work. I want to set a higher bar for success. If any one of these three tenets is missing, then you shouldn’t be considered successful by your own terms or those of society.
</div>
<ul>
<li>Helping others is helping yourself.</li>
<li>Helping others gives us a feeling of success. It makes our lives meaningful.</li>
<li>If you give people a simple way to help others, they will.</li>
<li>People are good, and if you give them the right tools, they’ll use them for the right thing.</li>
<li>In times of abundance, it’s human nature to seek a more purposeful life. This is often best satisfied by practising selfless concern for the well-being of others.</li>
</ul>
<div class="quote">
We could do business with a higher level of ambition and better ways to measure success. We could embrace our employees’ innate desire to do good. There is value in selflessness. Companies must understand this pattern and develop products that deliver deeper meaning. It’s important to recognise value before profit.
</div>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Tue, 27 Oct 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-10-27-things-a-little-bird-told-me-biz-stone.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>sanjiv sahayam</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Where are the Default Packages for Sublime Text Located on OSX</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-10-25-where-are-the-default-packages-for-sublime-text-located-on-osx.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>If you have a look in your Sublime Text installation on OSX under:</p>
<pre class="terminal"><code>/Users/sanj/Library/Application Support/Sublime Text 3/Packages</code></pre>
<p>you’ll notice that none of the default plugins or configurations are to be found.</p>
<p>They live in at another <a href="http://www.sublimetext.com/forum/viewtopic.php?f=2&amp;t=13236">location</a> at:</p>
<pre class="terminal"><code>/Applications/Sublime Text 3.app/Contents/MacOS/Packages/</code></pre>
<p>If you can’t find the Sublime Text 3.app folder try:</p>
<pre class="terminal"><code>/Applications/Sublime Text.app/Contents/MacOS/Packages</code></pre>
<p>All .sublime-package files are zip files. To have a look at their contents simply rename them to .zip files and extract.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 25 Oct 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-10-25-where-are-the-default-packages-for-sublime-text-located-on-osx.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>sanjiv sahayam</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>How to Use Sublime Text as Your Default Git Editor</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-10-25-how-to-use-sublime-text-as-your-default-git-editor.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>If you want to use Sublime Text to edit your Git comments then you are just a couple of steps away.</p>
<p>First, you need to make sure your sublime executable is on your system or user path. I have my user’s bin directory (~/bin) on my path. I create a symlink to the <a href="http://www.sublimetext.com/docs/3/osx_command_line.html">subl</a> executable as ~/bin/sublime.</p>
<pre class="terminal"><code>ln -s /Applications/Sublime Text.app/Contents/SharedSupport/bin/subl ~/bin/sublime</code></pre>
<p><em>Notice how I’ve renamed the executable from subl to sublime.</em></p>
<p>Next you need to <a href="https://help.github.com/articles/associating-text-editors-with-git">edit your Git config</a> and set your default editor:</p>
<pre class="terminal"><code>git config --global core.editor &quot;sublime -n -w&quot;</code></pre>
<p>The editor options are:</p>
<pre class="terminal"><code>n - Open a new window
w - Wait for the files to be closed before returning</code></pre>
<p>The next time you need to edit anything for Git you’ll be doing it in Sublime! :)</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 25 Oct 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-10-25-how-to-use-sublime-text-as-your-default-git-editor.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>sanjiv sahayam</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Git Workflow</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-10-25-git-workflow.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>There are quite a <a href="https://www.atlassian.com/git/tutorials/comparing-workflows/">few</a> git workflows out there. <a href="http://nvie.com/posts/a-successful-git-branching-model">Vincent Driessen</a> came up with the first Gitflow that I followed for my own projects. Other companies like Github use a <a href="http://scottchacon.com/2011/08/31/github-flow.html">simpler version</a> to that:</p>
<ul>
<li>Anything in the master branch is deployable.</li>
<li>To work on something new, create a descriptively named branch off of master (ie: new-oauth2-scopes).</li>
<li>Commit to that branch locally and regularly push your work to the same named branch on the server.</li>
<li>When you need feedback or help, or you think the branch is ready for merging, open a pull request.</li>
<li>After someone else has reviewed and signed off on the feature, you can merge it into master.</li>
<li>Once it is merged and pushed to ‘master’, you can and should deploy immediately.</li>
</ul>
<p>Even with the variety of flows linked to above, we are experimenting with yet another variant at my current workplace. I prefer the simplicity of the Gihub flow but we had additional requirements like deploying to staging that it does not seem to support. Here are the steps we used:</p>
<ul>
<li>To work on something new, create a descriptively named branch off of develop (ie: new-oauth2-scopes).</li>
<li>Commit to that branch locally and regularly push your work to the same named branch on the server. Committing to the server will run an automated build and test suite.</li>
<li>When you need feedback or help, or you think the branch is ready for merging, open a pull request against develop.</li>
<li>At this point your PR will be reviewed by one or more developers. You make any changes suggested and push again to verify that your reviewers are happy with the changes.</li>
<li>Once your PR is merged into develop, another automated build and test suite will run. Once it passes, your build is deployed to a staging environment for additional scripted or manual testing.</li>
<li>When the changes of your branch need to be pushed to production, a PR is created between develop and master.</li>
<li>Someone will review all the changes from develop that will be merged into master. There could be many so it’s a good idea to have at least a glance at everything that will hit master. Once the PR is merged into master it will run an automated build and test suite.</li>
<li>Once the master build passes we create a Github release with release notes and a tag.</li>
<li>When we are ready to deploy the changes from master to production we manually kick off a build to create our production deployment.</li>
</ul>
<div class="figure">
<img src="/images/git_workflow_2.png" alt="Git Workflow" />
<p class="caption">Git Workflow</p>
</div>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 25 Oct 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-10-25-git-workflow.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>sanjiv sahayam</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>A Life Worth Living</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-10-25-a-life-worth-living.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>There are reasons we choose to lead lives we don’t love. Jobs we detest. Relationships that don’t nourish us. Doing something about a bad situation takes a lot of courage. A lot of effort. You need to prove yourself again. Prove that you are good enough. That you are worthy. It’s so much easier to complain about your life, your job, your relationships and stay where you are. It’s scary to think about doing something about it. But that’s exactly what you must do make a life worth living.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 25 Oct 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-10-25-a-life-worth-living.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>sanjiv sahayam</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>The Right Attitude</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-10-22-the-right-attitude.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>People think that having the right attitude about a bad situation will help. When you’ve got no options, what else can you do?</p>
<p>By choosing to see the best in your current bad situation you start deluding yourself that things are not so bad. You start seeing the “positive” around you. Soon you don’t want change because you have fooled yourself with cognitive dissonance. All the while you loose part of your soul each day. Soon you stop dreaming. You settle for the garbage that’s fed to you.</p>
<p>Sometimes you need the wrong attitude. You need to know what you deserve and make the hard choices now so you can have a better future. Sometimes you need to take a stance and then look for options.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Thu, 22 Oct 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-10-22-the-right-attitude.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>sanjiv sahayam</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Git Commit Message Format</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-10-22-git-commit-message-format.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>There are <a href="http://tbaggery.com/2008/04/19/a-note-about-git-commit-messages.html">rules</a> on how to <a href="https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/GitCommitMessages">structure</a> a Git <a href="https://github.com/phonegap/phonegap/wiki/Git-Commit-Message-Format">commit message</a>. Here are some of the common ones.</p>
<h2 id="the-50-character-subject">The 50 character subject</h2>
<p>The first line of a Git commit should be 50 characters long. This is because commits were initially meant to be shared via email where this first line acted as the subject. As such it should not have an ending period.</p>
<p>Some reasons for following this are:</p>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>The output from git log –oneline is easier to read.</li>
<li>Github subjects that are over 72 characters are truncated.</li>
</ol>
<div class="figure">
<img src="/images/git_comment_wrapped_subject.png" alt="Github truncates subjects over 72 characters" />
<p class="caption">Github truncates subjects over 72 characters</p>
</div>
<h2 id="the-blank-second-line">The blank second line</h2>
<p>The second line should be blank and separates the subject from the commit body.</p>
<p>This ensures proper parsing when sending commits by email and Github.</p>
<h2 id="the-72-character-body">The 72 character body</h2>
<p>The following lines should be a maximum of 72 characters in length. This can include multiple paragraphs each of 72 characters which are separated by a blank line.</p>
<p>This helps with reading the commit message on terminals that are usually around 80 characters wide.</p>
<h2 id="link-to-featureissue">Link to feature/issue</h2>
<p>Another convention is to add a link to the issue or feature being worked on as the last line. This could be a link to Jira or Youtrack issue etc.</p>
<p>Here’s an example of a Git commit message with all of the above rules:</p>
<pre class="terminal scrollx"><code>Add support for reverse sorting of imports

Natural sorting, sorts from upper to lowercase. This reverses the sort
order because we want packages to sort first before class names.

An example would be:
import scala.concurrent._
import ExecutionContext.Implicits.global

[https://yourtracker/project/PORT-120]</code></pre>
<h2 id="some-additional-rules">Some additional rules</h2>
<h3 id="imperative-mood">Imperative mood</h3>
<p>Some people advocate using <a href="http://www.grammar-monster.com/glossary/imperative_mood.htm">imperative mood</a> for the subject. This is basically a command-like phrase:</p>
<pre class="terminal scrollx"><code>Add W
Fix X
Delete Y
Create Z</code></pre>
<p>Your commit message is meant to complete the sentence:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>This commit will …</p>
</blockquote>
<p>When you write the subject in imperative mode it completes as:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>This commit will Fix X</p>
</blockquote>
<p>If you wrote “Fixes X” then it won’t read correctly:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>This commit will Fixes X</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I’ve tried this for a few months now and don’t see any real benefit in using one tense over the other. As long as what the commit does is clear it should be fine. Your mileage may vary.</p>
<div class="figure">
<img src="/images/git-comment_imperative_mood.png" alt="Docker commits using imperative mood" />
<p class="caption">Docker commits using imperative mood</p>
</div>
<h3 id="include-issue-number-in-subject">Include issue number in subject</h3>
<p>Some use the issue number as the first entry in the subject.</p>
<div class="figure">
<img src="/images/git_comment_issue_no_in_subject.png" alt="Issue number at start of the subject" />
<p class="caption">Issue number at start of the subject</p>
</div>
<p>Others use it somewhere in the subject.</p>
<div class="figure">
<img src="/images/git_comment_issue_no_in_subject_end.png" alt="Issue number in the subject" />
<p class="caption">Issue number in the subject</p>
</div>
<h3 id="explain-what-and-why">Explain what and why</h3>
<p>Another <a href="http://chris.beams.io/posts/git-commit">guideline</a> on writing good comments is to use the body to explain the <strong>what</strong> and <strong>why</strong> instead of the how.</p>
<div class="figure">
<img src="/images/git_comment_what_and_why.png" alt="Explain what and why" />
<p class="caption">Explain what and why</p>
</div>
<p>If you find all these rules too constrictive, then <a href="http://zachholman.com/posts/git-commit-history">you’re not alone</a>. I agree with Zach on this for personal projects. I think following the rules leads to better commit messages that are easier to understand. This is important when we need to collaborate with other developers.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Thu, 22 Oct 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-10-22-git-commit-message-format.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>sanjiv sahayam</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Culture Flow</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-10-22-culture-flow.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Some companies have good work cultures. They are an environment where employees can thrive and do their best work. Happy and effective employees lead to customers who are well <a href="http://sethgodin.typepad.com/seths_blog/2015/09/tires-coffee-and-people.html">looked-after</a>.</p>
<p>Other companies have cultures that are not so good. The lack of access to clean facilities in a first-world country like Australia still astounds me. Ergonomic chairs to sit on is another basic need that is often neglected. Taking a customer’s money and then not providing them with the service they paid for, fearing change because it will “break” things and <a href="http://sanj.ink/posts/2015-09-16-secrets.html">keeping secrets</a> are some other signs.</p>
<p>Industrial age working conditions like having rigid work hours, having to be “seen” to know that you are working and where you have to be micromanaged because you can’t be “trusted” are not very effective in the information age.</p>
<p>Unfortunately if you do work for one of these “other” companies then you should strive to change the culture should you choose to stay. It will take a monumental effort and it might be fleeting. You owe it to yourself to try. Most companies will ignore any issues that they have. They might say things like “we have improved dramatically over the last year, you should have seen it when ….” Culture flows from top to bottom. If you are in a bad culture you only have to look to the leaders to see where it flows from.</p>
<p>You owe it to yourself to have a good working environment. Fight for it if you have to. Leave if you can’t change it.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Thu, 22 Oct 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-10-22-culture-flow.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>sanjiv sahayam</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>When the Learning Stops</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-10-21-when-the-learning-stops.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>the hurting starts, I mentioned to a mate at work. If you are not learning anything new then you are stagnating. There is no excuse to stagnate for eight hours a day, five days a week.</p>
<p>While you are learning new things you might turn a blind eye to other obvious issues with your workplace. You might trade learning for somewhat dubious work conditions and practices. Once you are no longer getting any benefit from learning new things, the issues with your workplace will become magnified and move into focus.</p>
<p>If you find yourself in a dead end job where you’re not learning anything useful it’s time for you to start looking for new opportunities.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 21 Oct 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-10-21-when-the-learning-stops.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>sanjiv sahayam</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Is it a One Line Change?</title>
    <link>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-10-21-is-it-a-one-line-change.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>I’ve heard managers ask developers this question. It’s like the number of lines changed is going to mitigate risk somehow. The unstated assumption is: the more code this guy writes the higher the chance of him introducing a bug. Trust is at an all time low; the brittleness of the system an all time high.</p>
<p>Almost every system could be compromised with a one line change. Ask yourself what that one line would be for your system. I’m sure you’ll come up with one.</p>
<p>What’s disturbing about this question is that managers are now making calls on how and how much code is written. That’s like me asking an electrician “is it a one wire change?” It makes no more sense in that scenario either.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 21 Oct 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>http://blog.ssanj.net/posts/2015-10-21-is-it-a-one-line-change.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>sanjiv sahayam</dc:creator>
</item>

    </channel>
</rss>
